<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data Science on The Stats Guy</title>
    <link>/categories/data-science/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Data Science on The Stats Guy</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/data-science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Why ensemble modelling works so well - and one often neglected principle</title>
      <link>/2019/12/25/why-ensemble-modelling-works-so-well-and-one-often-neglected-principle/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/25/why-ensemble-modelling-works-so-well-and-one-often-neglected-principle/</guid>
      <description>Putting models together in an ensemble learning fashion is a popular technique amongst Data Scientists
Ensemble learning is the simultaneous use of multiple predictive models to arrive at a single prediction, based on a collective decision made together by all models in the ensemble. It&#39;s a common and popular technique used in predictive modelling, especially when individual models are failing to produce the required performance levels, in terms of e.g. accuracy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seven tips for working on analytics delivery projects</title>
      <link>/2019/03/17/seven-tips-for-working-on-analytics-delivery-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/03/17/seven-tips-for-working-on-analytics-delivery-projects/</guid>
      <description>Following are seven tips / tricks / hacks that I came to learnt (some of them the hard way) and compiled as a data scientist / delivery consultant / data science consultant. In brief, they are:
You to Yourself
 Develop a strategy
 Keep a delivery journal
 Plan your daily activities
 Frontload your projects
  You to Others
 Show mediocre output to no one</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Master of Science in Statistics programme in NUS</title>
      <link>/2019/02/09/my-master-of-science-in-statistics-programme-in-nus/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/02/09/my-master-of-science-in-statistics-programme-in-nus/</guid>
      <description>I have gotten quite a couple of questions regarding my current MSc Statistics programme in NUS. Here are some broadstroke information about the programme and how I am approaching it.
 I&amp;rsquo;m doing the MSc by Coursework programme, which means a research thesis is not part of my curriculum. A MSc by Research option is available.
 Under the Coursework programme, there is a Track 1 (40MC) programme and a Track 2 (80MC) one.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>