<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Books on The Stats Guy</title>
    <link>/tags/books/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Books on The Stats Guy</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/books/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>What are your 50 books?</title>
      <link>/post/2020/10/21/what-are-your-50-books/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020/10/21/what-are-your-50-books/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In Rolf Dobelli&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/36340275-the-art-of-the-good-life&#34;&gt;The Art of The Good Life&lt;/a&gt;, Dobelli talks about the way we are reading, and how that is &amp;ldquo;wrong&amp;rdquo;, in this &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dobelli.com/en/essays/how-to-read-books/&#34;&gt;short essay&lt;/a&gt;. Let me partially quote some bits here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s the point of reading a book when the content largely seeps away? &amp;hellip; Why is it we retain so little of what we read?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re reading wrong. We&amp;rsquo;re reading neither selectively nor thoroughly enough. Today I read differently than I did a few years ago. Just as much, but fewer books - only I read them better, and twice. I&amp;rsquo;ve become radically selective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dobelli also gives a motivating example, prior to the section above:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don’t read correctly. We don’t read selectively nor do we read carefully enough. We need to read differently: here is my case for a radical book regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A multi-trip train ticket in Switzerland has six spaces. Before each journey you insert your card into an orange-coloured machine which stamps it with the date and time and removes a tiny corner from the margin on the left-hand side. Once all six spaces have been stamped, the ticket is used up and worthless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now imagine a reading ticket for books with fifty spaces. Same system: Before you read a book, you must stamp a space. But unlike the multi-trip train ticket this reading ticket for books is the only one you’ll ever have. It will be impossible for you to get another one. Once the ticket is used up, you won’t be able to open any other books – and while you may beat the transport system by evading the fare, there is no cheating with the reading ticket. Fifty books only for an entire lifetime – a non-issue for many but for you as a reader of this newspaper an appalling prospect. How is one supposed to get through life even half-civilised with so few books?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dobelli suggests that we could read more selectively, and read each shortlisted book at least twice, which does make sense. Books can be enjoyed more than once, like a song. Furthermore, if we would like to &amp;ldquo;practise&amp;rdquo; what&amp;rsquo;s written in the book, like practising playing the guitar, we would indeed play the same song on the guitar more than once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now suppose you were to take on his idea, and specially curate a list of 50 books that you would read more than once, and in principle, be able to better to embody and apply the learnings from these 50 books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I gave it a shot, and my list stops at 10. Either I have not read enough, or I am being very selective. The following list of books are however, highly aligned to how I view and/or how I choose to interact with the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personal Finance&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://yourmoneyoryourlife.com/book-summary/&#34;&gt;Your Money or Your Life by Vicki Robins&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The corporate world, dealing with other people&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.surroundedbyidiots.com/en/books/surrounded-by-idiots/&#34;&gt;Surrounded by Idiots by Thomas Erikson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/232079.The_Rules_of_Work&#34;&gt;The Rules of Work by Richard Templar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stoicism, living life&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/28257707-the-subtle-art-of-not-giving-a-f-ck&#34;&gt;The Subtle Art of Not Giving a Fuck by Mark Manson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meditations&#34;&gt;Meditations by Marcus Aurelius&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/36340275-the-art-of-the-good-life&#34;&gt;The Art of the Good Life by Rolf Dobelli&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:Yes-a-little-met&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:Yes-a-little-met&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/29093292-the-daily-stoic&#34;&gt;The Daily Stoic by Ryan Holiday&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern Psychology&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thinking,_Fast_and_Slow&#34;&gt;Thinking, Fast and Slow by Daniel Kahneman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Success&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/3228917-outliers&#34;&gt;Outliers by Malcolm Gladwell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finance&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Black_Swan:_The_Impact_of_the_Highly_Improbable&#34;&gt;The Black Swan by Nassim Taleb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:One-of-the-very&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:One-of-the-very&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about you? What would be your 50 books?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:Yes-a-little-met&#34;&gt;Yes a little &amp;ldquo;meta&amp;rdquo;, but this book is really good. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:Yes-a-little-met&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:One-of-the-very&#34;&gt;One of the very first books that I seriously read, and that inspired me about finance, statistics, and most importantly taking time to learn something and go deep in them. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:One-of-the-very&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[short] Book Review: Rich by Retirement by Joshua Giersch</title>
      <link>/post/2018/09/16/short-book-review-rich-by-retirement-by-joshua-giersch/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018/09/16/short-book-review-rich-by-retirement-by-joshua-giersch/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/I/51kcmMI3s7L._SX331_BO1,204,203,200_.jpg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34;&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joshua Giersch, better known as “Shiny Things”, is an investment guru who has been generously giving investing advice on &lt;a href=&#34;https://forums.hardwarezone.com.sg/money-mind-210/%2Aofficial%2A-shiny-things-club-part-2-a-5813566.html&#34;&gt;HardwareZone&lt;/a&gt; and his &lt;a href=&#34;https://moneygowherefind.com/joshua-giersch-aka-shiny-things-hwz/&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;. His advice are consistently dished out with the SG context in mind, and his book &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Rich-Retirement-Singaporeans-Invest-Wealthy-ebook/dp/B01JXW17ZM&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Rich by Retirement: How Singaporeans Can Invest Smart and Retire Wealthy&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, is, in essence, the consolidation of all of his tips and hacks on being a successful investor in SG.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most interesting component of his philosophy is his very simple portfolio strategy. Whether it is too simple for your liking is for you to decide, and in this post I will summarize, from my perspective, the key points in his book. Enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;emergency-fund&#34;&gt;Emergency fund&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep an emergency fund with 6 months worth of expense&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;insurance&#34;&gt;Insurance&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get hospitalization plan (paid in part using Medisave), and term life if you have dependents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All other forms of insurance are neither necessary nor worthwhile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Especially avoid ILPs and endowments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;brokerage-accounts&#34;&gt;Brokerage accounts&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only pay &amp;lt;= 0.2% for trading SG stocks, &amp;lt;= 0.3% for US/UK stocks; UTs/ETFs with &amp;lt;= 0.5% expense ratio are ok&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anything beyond these percentages are not acceptable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ideally regulated in SG or US&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No custody or dividend handling fees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recommended: SCB, Interactive Brokers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exception to the &amp;lt;= 0.2% recommendation: POSB Invest-Saver, because of the lack of min amount per txn. Good for small investors who are just starting out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;asset-class-allocation&#34;&gt;Asset class allocation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stocks: 110 – current age; bonds: the rest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For stocks, 50:50 on SG and int’l&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For bonds, only SG&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;exchange-traded-funds&#34;&gt;Exchange traded funds&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ETFs are great because of the instant diversification. The ideal ETF would be one with &amp;lt;= 0.3% expense ratio, &amp;gt; 100mil in assets, and is a physical ETF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-shiny-things-3-etf-portfolio&#34;&gt;The Shiny Things 3-ETF portfolio&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IWDA.LN (iShares Core MSCI World UCITS ETF – for Int’l exposure)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ES3.SI (SPDR Straits Times Index ETF – for SG exposure)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A35.SI (ABF Singapore Bond Index Fund – for SG bonds)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;cpf-srs&#34;&gt;CPF/SRS&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep CPF in cash, don’t buy any counters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider using SRS top-ups for tax breaks; can use SRS to buy ES3 (use OCBC BCIP – though A35 is not available)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;dollar-cost-averaging&#34;&gt;Dollar cost averaging&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t time the market – “time in market” &amp;gt; “time the market”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;POSB Invest-Saver is great for DCA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;portfolio-rebalancing&#34;&gt;Portfolio rebalancing&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only rebalance in May and Nov every year&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simple enough? Pick up his book from Amazon or NLB (I had to make a reservation – $1.55 reservation fee) and you will be able to understand his justifications for each of these pointers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[short] Scientific desktop research: tentative conclusions</title>
      <link>/post/2017/02/13/scientific-desktop-research-tentative-conclusions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017/02/13/scientific-desktop-research-tentative-conclusions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Useful tip I got from &amp;ldquo;Extreme Productivity&amp;rdquo; by Robert Pozen, still reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desktop research, or simply known as googling in today&amp;rsquo;s context, is the act of collecting information about a particular topic or domain, with a broad/generic question in mind, or even without any question at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to do this is simply keep googling related search terms and noting down facts and statistics, and constantly drilling down on a specific term until it&amp;rsquo;s milked - sort of like a depth-first search of collecting information. After we are satisfied with all the information we collect, we then try to piece together a story. But is this a good approach?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pozen argues that &amp;ldquo;although extensive research might seem a logical first step, it&amp;rsquo;s actually very inefficient.&amp;rdquo; This is because &amp;ldquo;there are literally thousands of facts that could be relevant to any project; do you really want to collect them all?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, Pozen suggests that we first form &amp;ldquo;tentative conclusions&amp;rdquo;, by first thinking hard about our problem. &amp;ldquo;After a day or so of gathering relevant information, write down your tentative conclusions for the project. These will allow you to more quickly engage in analysis - rather than description - by providing a focus for your subsequent research.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think about it, this makes a lot of sense and sounds more productive. And it&amp;rsquo;s a pretty scientific way of doing things - scientists don&amp;rsquo;t endeavour to do all the experiments that they can possibly imagine and then collecting all the data. Instead, they formulate hypotheses and design experiments to refute their claims. If their claims are not refuted, or are even proven, then they become published and reliable facts, for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this applies to more than just desktop research:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Think of how you first learn a programming language outside of a school setting. Odds are you &amp;ldquo;hacked&amp;rdquo; your way through to your current level of proficiency, by relying on Google and Stackoverflow. You were probably required to write some production or project code, had an idea, didn&amp;rsquo;t work out, googled, and try again and again. Not going through things like &amp;ldquo;Basic data structures in Python&amp;rdquo; and work from thereon. I am definitely guilty of this - when I first started learning about Spark and writing PySpark code, I tried multiple times to start from some tutorial and slowly work my way up toward proficiency. Each time, I failed either because the material gets boring, or I lose patience, or something like that. It just doesn&amp;rsquo;t work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which is the more efficient of doing exploratory data analysis - plotting every single plot and collecting every single summary statistics there is to your data, or coming up with several hypotheses and then visualising and testing them? &amp;ldquo;My guess is that age is not normally distributed in this dataset, let&amp;rsquo;s see.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[short] Book Review: The McKinsey Edge</title>
      <link>/post/2016/12/31/book-review-the-mckinsey-edge/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2016/12/31/book-review-the-mckinsey-edge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The McKinsey Edge by Shu Hattori is a collection of &amp;ldquo;principles&amp;rdquo; that the author collected while he was at
consultant at McKinsey. The forty-odd principles in the book, while easily understood, stood out
when they are collated together in a single book, as many productivity and professional hacks
strung together. A rather interesting read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following are his principles divided into four chapters, and in bold are those that I thought to be
particularly useful, and would like to expound on them in future writings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building the Better Self&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on what really matters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start with the hard stuff in the morning&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Catch small signals and make a difference&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have a 30-second answer to everything&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Frontload your project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create the right end output image&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Smile when you are under stress&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go beyond your self-perceived limit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always imagine the worst-case scenario&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start following up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Push back with less emotion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be flexible on the perception of your passion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;What would Marvin do?&amp;rdquo; Find your role models&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Know what gives your the most energy in your day&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go jogging to smell the flowers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a commitment plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growing with Others&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always memorize the first three sentences of a presentation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communicate using fewer words&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pause three seconds before answering difficult questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Question more and talk less&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Turn no into yes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t show half-baked output&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Instantly find a connection in the room&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be a giver, not a receiver&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find the best intent in people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn team member&amp;rsquo;s defining moments and personal sides&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Think of everyone as a helpful individual, not a &amp;ldquo;resource&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go out for a meal with interesting people every week&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consciously gauge your people&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assign team members meaningful tasks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create followership through deliberate on-the-job coaching&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deliver feedback using positive criticism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Please your assistants and support staff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Execlling in Process Management&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always prepare an agenda before meetings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create &amp;ldquo;four boxes&amp;rdquo; to dos&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focus on outcomes not activities&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Know your meeting modes in advance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proactively manage e-mail communication using the 5D rules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speak up as early as possible&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a minimalist presentation toolkit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create an easy-to-use template for updates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going the Extra mile&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Give away knowledge and tools unsparingly&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get rid of your physical barriers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask the second order questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn to write fewer notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prepare to renew your life&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create your own profile as a leader&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
