<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>On Life on The Stats Guy</title>
    <link>/categories/on-life/</link>
    <description>Recent content in On Life on The Stats Guy</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/on-life/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The banquet of life</title>
      <link>/post/2021/03/21/the-banquet-of-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021/03/21/the-banquet-of-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Epictetus once compared life to a banquet - the banquet of life - and reminded us that how we conduct ourselves at a banquet should be how we conduct ourselves in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember to conduct yourself in life as if at a banquet. As something being passed around comes to you, reach out your hand and take a moderate helping. Does it pass you by? Don’t stop it. It hasn’t yet come? Don’t burn in desire for it, but wait until it arrives in front of you. Act this way with children, a spouse, toward position, with wealth—one day it will make you worthy of a banquet with the gods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As good food and drinks are being passed around, don&amp;rsquo;t be too eager for them, or even snatch them from someone else. Be patient and graceful. We don&amp;rsquo;t have to anxiously sought them out - we also don&amp;rsquo;t have to pretentiously reject them to look good. By all the means, enjoy the good food, and savor the moment. It&amp;rsquo;s what the banquet of life has come to offer to you, after your long wait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, when not-so-tasty food and drinks come along, take them in stride. They may taste unpleasant, but at least they are a new experience. Like a good guest, we won&amp;rsquo;t complain about the unpleasant food. We simply wait for the next dish to arrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the pleasant food leaves you, don&amp;rsquo;t hope that it lingers, or try to grab more onto your plate out of greed. Be grateful that you had a taste of it, and commit its taste to your memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, as the unpleasant food leaves you, don&amp;rsquo;t rejoice out loud. Instead, be appreciative that it&amp;rsquo;s now going away, and take a moment to prepare for the next dish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every chapter in our lives is like a dish in this banquet. Regardless whether it&amp;rsquo;s a good chapter or a bad chapter, a good dish or a bad dish - always try to be patient and be genuine. Always try to be respectful and be grateful. Always try to be appreciative and be prepared.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The truth is always in the middle</title>
      <link>/post/2021/02/21/the-truth-is-always-in-the-middle/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021/02/21/the-truth-is-always-in-the-middle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A former boss of mine once told me &amp;ldquo;the truth is always in the middle&amp;rdquo;. He meant that as a rule of thumb to life&amp;rsquo;s many problems, if not all. Whenever there are two or more competing options to choose from, the best one is likely the one in the middle - the middleground, so to speak. This middleground balances the pros and the cons of the various options, advantageous in some way and sacrificing in some other way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have used his rule of thumb as a heuristic, or a mental shortcut, ever since. It makes sense to me. The reason why it makes sense is because of incomplete information - to be precise, it&amp;rsquo;s because of the incomplete information available to different people in a given problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may be familiar with the story of the three blind men and an elephant. Three blind men were asked to name the object that they are touching. The first blind man touches the elephant&amp;rsquo;s trunk, and says that the object is a snake. The second blind man touches the elephant&amp;rsquo;s leg, and says that the object is a tree trunk. The third blind man touches the elephant&amp;rsquo;s side, and says that the object is a wall. The three blind men have access to different sets of incomplete information, and make conclusions based on what they know. The truth, however, lies somewhere in the middle of a snake, a tree trunk, and a wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all have different perspectives when facing the same problem - some of us may be more different than others. Despite the differences, one thing is for sure - all of us likely have incomplete information to work with, even if we think that we already have all the important information. We may not know what we don&amp;rsquo;t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So don&amp;rsquo;t be too quick to judge the next time you have to make a decision. Between competing options, the truth is always in the middle.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On punctuality</title>
      <link>/post/2021/01/30/on-punctuality/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021/01/30/on-punctuality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t be late. Always be early or punctual. Being on time for appointments is a basic form of respect for others and for others&amp;rsquo; time. It shows you regard the others as important people in your life - important enough for you to properly plan your time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common reason I hear to justify lateness is this: since others will be late, I should not waste my time to be early or punctual, and then wait for others to arrive. Instead, I should be late as well. A tit for a tat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First and foremost, two wrongs don&amp;rsquo;t make a right. Just because others are late, does not give us a free pass to be late; just because others disrespect our time, does not give us a free pass to disrespect theirs. Our principles for punctuality and respect hold true always - regardless of others&amp;rsquo; lateness and disrespect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often accompanied with this tit-for-tat reason for lateness, are frustration, irritation, possibly even anger. Remind yourself on &lt;a href=&#34;https://thestatsguy.rbind.io/post/2020/12/06/our-happiness-is-within-our-control/&#34;&gt;the separation between what is controllable and what is not&lt;/a&gt;. The actions of others are not within our control. And so, as much as possible, we should not let something not within our control to affect our emotions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tit-for-tat is also the worst scenario in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prisoner%27s_dilemma&#34;&gt;Prisoner&amp;rsquo;s Dilemma&lt;/a&gt; - a lose-lose for everyone. We can instead choose to bring everyone out of a lose-lose situation, by first being punctual consistently - an action that is definitely within our control. By showing everyone that we are willing to be punctual consistently, we are offering a gesture of goodwill. Again, whether others will return the gesture is beyond our control. But, at the very least, we know that we have tried our best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, if we have no choice but to be late, because of a traffic jam, a train breakdown, or a last minute meeting by your boss or customer, then we should have the courtesy to inform others as early as possible, and give an estimation of when we can arrive. This is again a basic form of respect, and especially practicable with the help of smartphones today. The traffic jam is not within our control, but a short WhatsApp message is, surely, within our control.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On setting goals</title>
      <link>/post/2021/01/22/on-setting-goals/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021/01/22/on-setting-goals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Do you have goals? Things that you want to achieve before you die. Most people do. Good grades and qualifications, a happy family, a well-paying job, a strong and healthy body, a thriving business, a lot of zeroes at the back of your bank account balance. It is easy to select a number of goals, some from the list above, that resonates with you - then set them as your goals. It&amp;rsquo;s a simple exercise, done by asking yourself: what do you want in your life, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; years from now? To be precise, what do you want to &lt;strong&gt;enjoy&lt;/strong&gt; in your life, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; years from now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more difficult, more important, yet often neglected question is: what do you want to &lt;strong&gt;endure&lt;/strong&gt; in your life, from now to &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; years later?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goals are about endurance - choosing the few things that you want to endure. Goals are not about enjoyment - choosing the few (or many) things that you want to enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putting this in another way: a goal that doesn&amp;rsquo;t need any labour or sacrifice or endurance, is not a goal. It is not a goal because if it needs no sacrifice, that means you can already have it right now. Goals are, by definition, painful and laborious,  back-breaking and time-consuming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask yourself then: what are you choosing to endure? What do you wish to endure? What do you think are worthy of your endurance? Perhaps these are hard questions to think about - surely harder than what do you wish to enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let&amp;rsquo;s think smaller. For your 2021 new year resolution, ask yourself: in 2021, what are you choosing to endure? In 2021, what do you wish to endure? In 2021, what do you think are worthy of your endurance? Set these as your goals for this new year.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
