<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>On Life on The Stats Guy</title>
    <link>/categories/on-life/</link>
    <description>Recent content in On Life on The Stats Guy</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/on-life/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Which costs do you want to pay?</title>
      <link>/post/2021/08/09/which-costs-do-you-want-to-pay/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021/08/09/which-costs-do-you-want-to-pay/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Everything in life comes with a cost. Income comes with tax. Success comes with stress. Love comes with emotional baggage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these costs are &amp;ldquo;happy problems&amp;rdquo; to have. For example, the fact that we may complain about income tax means we probably earn more than enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other costs can be more developmental in nature. They may help us develop a strong work ethic, a stoic mentality, a loving personality, an upsized circle of competence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recognizing the costs to everything we have in life, forces us to think whether these costs are worth incurring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of what society typically considers as a successful person. Most likely, we conjure an image in our minds, something that looks like high income, high societal status, beautiful spouse, one or two or three children, expensive house, expensive car, expensive clothes, and expensive food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now think of the costs associated with this image of a successful person. High stress, high expectations, high spending, high-strung state of mind, high competitiveness, high environmental footprint. Sounds awful when we put these together in one sentence - but I would be pretentious if I were to say to get rid of all these costs, and lead life like an ascetic. I won&amp;rsquo;t be able to do that myself either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is in the middle - we have actually don&amp;rsquo;t have to get rid of all these costs at once. We are free to choose which costs we would like to pay for, and reap the benefits. The beauty of modern life is this freedom to do largely what we choose to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So rather than always thinking about and setting goals, think instead about the costs that you are willing and able to pay. You may find this perspective more useful.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>37 moments of happiness</title>
      <link>/post/2021/07/31/37-moments-of-happiness/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021/07/31/37-moments-of-happiness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Inspired by &lt;a href=&#34;https://33moments.tumblr.com/&#34;&gt;Jin Shengtan&amp;rsquo;s 33 moments of happiness&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I satiate my hunger with a hot meal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I quench my thirst with cool, plain water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I have been working hard at a task on the computer and finished it, then shutting down the computer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I tabulate my assets and net worth, and reflect how much they have grown&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I lie down on my bed, after being busy and active for the whole day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I complete my tasks for the day, and it&amp;rsquo;s only 3pm in the afternoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I have long discussions (philosophical or otherwise) on topics with a friend - topics that we both enjoy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I finished a long and hard run&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I read a truly good book&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I hear music that makes me want to sing or hum along&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I go on a long, solo hike, taking in deep breaths, and taking in the sights and sounds of nature&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I am in position to take a great picture of a butterfly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I take a hot shower on a cold day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I sit indoors, looking at the rain outside&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I sit alone in a big canteen or dining hall, enjoying a meal and kopi, peering at the few faces seated some distance away from me&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I wake up, knowing that I have no obligations today, and there is no need to have conversations today&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I write something that I like, or on a topic that I enjoy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I ascend a peak, and admire the view I earned&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I finished a test or examination, one that I have put in my best effort to prepare&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I return home after a long day of tasks and conversations, and I close my room door behind me, finally alone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I visit a big bookstore, browsing books and titles, taking in all the ideas that flood my mind&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I am in a place where no one knows me, and I get a feeling of serene obscurity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I make plans for the future and feel optimistic about them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I finally urinate or defecate, after having to hold for some time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I am sitting in my armchair, reading, feeling not too hold or not too cold&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I drift to sleep while reading, feeling my body warmth from the sleepiness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I realize I have nothing to worry about&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I finally come across a book or idea that can succinctly express my thoughts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I tidy my room and throw old and unwanted junk away&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I spend some time in a restaurant with the family, treating them to a good meal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I enter a bookstore that I have never been to before&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I know I can toss my phone aside for the whole day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I visit somewhere new, alone, on a task or volunteering assignment or sight-seeing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I empty my bowels&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I taste a good kopi-c-kosong, after some time of not drinking coffee&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I put on fresh, clean, dry, pleasant-smelling t-shirts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I just recovered from a headache&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On procrastination</title>
      <link>/post/2021/04/27/on-procrastination/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021/04/27/on-procrastination/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Procrastinating is one of life&amp;rsquo;s biggest banes. Everyone has an episode of severe procrastination at some point in their lives. And that severe procrastination can affect any major aspect of our lives - relationship, family, work, finance, health, education, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Procrastination usually takes one of two forms - procrastinating on a decision, or procrastinating on doing the work to solve a problem. In both forms of procrastination, the underlying decision or problem is a difficult one - we don&amp;rsquo;t usually procrastinate on something simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The underlying decision or problem is also one that has a big impact on our lives - so our resistance to change pushes us away from the decision or the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Procrastinating on something that is both difficult and impactful doesn&amp;rsquo;t sound like a wise move - so why do we still procrastinate?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Procrastinating usually involves negative emotions - negative emotions that we have to experience when we make the decision or work through the problem. These negative emotions can range from sadness to anxiety to anger to regret to stress. We subconsciously choose to distract ourselves from experiencing these emotions, temporarily pleasing our &lt;a href=&#34;https://lindagraham-mft.net/the-experiencing-self-vs-the-remembering-self/&#34;&gt;experiencing self&lt;/a&gt;, and procrastinate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stopping procrastination will mean recognizing these emotions, and letting them play out - not controlling or subduing them. It&amp;rsquo;s OK to feel sad, to feel anxious, to feel angry, to feel regretful, to feel stressed. It&amp;rsquo;s alright. Let these emotions play out, feel them - and regard them from a distance. Observe or write down your thoughts as you are experiencing these emotions. These thoughts will let you learn more about yourself, and will become lessons in life that you can draw upon in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you feel the full force of your emotions, take a deep breath and regain composure. Again, regard these emotions from a distance - they are simply artefacts that you are observing from afar. Then remind yourself that you have a decision to make or a problem to solve, and go make that decision or solve that problem. Most likely, you already know what needs to be done (perhaps hence the procrastination in the first place).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gaining emotional distance - today is not one day, today is Day One</title>
      <link>/post/2021/04/23/gaining-emotional-distance-today-is-not-one-day-today-is-day-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021/04/23/gaining-emotional-distance-today-is-not-one-day-today-is-day-one/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gaining emotional distance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a friend approaches us for advice on their problems, we generally can offer good advice in an objective manner. We are able to evaluate facts, weigh pros and cons, and suggest potential solutions. We are able to do these because of the emotional distance between their problems, and ourselves. Yes we may get emotional over a close friend&amp;rsquo;s recent divorce - but not as emotional as if we were the one getting the divorce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when we are brooding over our own problems, we lose that emotional distance. We become embroiled and entangled in the all emotions - emotions within ourselves and others. We lose objectivity. We become irrational. We make decisions that allow the &lt;a href=&#34;https://lindagraham-mft.net/the-experiencing-self-vs-the-remembering-self/&#34;&gt;experiencing self&lt;/a&gt; to feel better. We think more short-term. We may procrastinate and delay some inevitable decision in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To gain this emotional distance when we are solving our own problems, we need to see ourselves from a third party&amp;rsquo;s perspective. When we do that, it is easier to extract ourselves from the current circumstances, and work on these problems - problems that have been plaguing us for weeks, months, or years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing ourselves from a third party&amp;rsquo;s perspective gives us emotional distance. And because of this emotional distance, we gain clarity of thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today is Day One&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to gain this third party&amp;rsquo;s perspective is this - today, right now, is not one day in your life. Today is not a day where there was a past, where past events accrue into today&amp;rsquo;s situations. Rather, today is Day One. Your life simply began today, right now, as if you have merely came into existence moments ago. All you have are the current moment, a number of possibilities into the future, and memories in your mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we are able to take on this perspective, we gain emotional distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Memories&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be careful with memories, though. Many of us often associate the word &amp;ldquo;memory&amp;rdquo; with a sense of nostalgia and warmth. Because of how our brains are wired, we tend to remember the good things, and subconsciously choose to forget the not-so-good. So our memories are typically depicted in a more pleasant light. Our memories are also a subset, or incomplete representation of our actual experiences. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peak%E2%80%93end_rule&#34;&gt;peak-end rule&lt;/a&gt; suggests that we only remember the highlight and the ending of our experiences, while &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duration_neglect&#34;&gt;duration neglect&lt;/a&gt; suggests that we do not remember how long- or short-lasting our experiences were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From now, towards the future&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, when we treat today as Day One, all we have is the moment now, some possibilities into the future, and preprogrammed memories that are biased in some manner. Taking on such a perspective can be liberating, because it gives you the emotional distance from what that has happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You and everything else only came into existence moments ago. There is no personal attachment to the past, because there is no past. There were no past actions that resulted in today&amp;rsquo;s effects. None at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allows you to focus on two things - what you have right now, and what you would like to achieve in the future. This future refers to both long-term and short-term future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you have right now includes your material and immaterial possessions, as well as problems that you need to solve. Remember, today is Day One - these problems came into existence moments ago, together with you. Your job is to solve these problems, or at least chip away at them, one bit at a time. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter if these are emotional problems, financial problems, health problems, or whether you feel personally responsible, guilty or attached to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today is Day One - look to the future, visualize where you want to be, chart a course towards it, and solve the problems as they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides your problems, whatever resources or advantages or strengths or possessions that you have right now, also came into existence moments ago. Make use of them. Don&amp;rsquo;t whine or complain about the lack of money or skills or knowledge or time. Today is Day One - make use of what you have, be grateful that you even have these resources when you came into existence today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we adopt such a perspective and gain emotional distance, we may start to take both problems and resources less personally. We view them as simply problems to solve, using the resources that we have - all while charting a course towards the long-term.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The banquet of life</title>
      <link>/post/2021/03/21/the-banquet-of-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021/03/21/the-banquet-of-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Epictetus once compared life to a banquet - the banquet of life - and reminded us that how we conduct ourselves at a banquet should be how we conduct ourselves in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember to conduct yourself in life as if at a banquet. As something being passed around comes to you, reach out your hand and take a moderate helping. Does it pass you by? Don’t stop it. It hasn’t yet come? Don’t burn in desire for it, but wait until it arrives in front of you. Act this way with children, a spouse, toward position, with wealth—one day it will make you worthy of a banquet with the gods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As good food and drinks are being passed around, don&amp;rsquo;t be too eager for them, or even snatch them from someone else. Be patient and graceful. We don&amp;rsquo;t have to anxiously sought them out - we also don&amp;rsquo;t have to pretentiously reject them to look good. By all the means, enjoy the good food, and savor the moment. It&amp;rsquo;s what the banquet of life has come to offer to you, after your long wait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, when not-so-tasty food and drinks come along, take them in stride. They may taste unpleasant, but at least they are a new experience. Like a good guest, we won&amp;rsquo;t complain about the unpleasant food. We simply wait for the next dish to arrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the pleasant food leaves you, don&amp;rsquo;t hope that it lingers, or try to grab more onto your plate out of greed. Be grateful that you had a taste of it, and commit its taste to your memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, as the unpleasant food leaves you, don&amp;rsquo;t rejoice out loud. Instead, be appreciative that it&amp;rsquo;s now going away, and take a moment to prepare for the next dish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every chapter in our lives is like a dish in this banquet. Regardless whether it&amp;rsquo;s a good chapter or a bad chapter, a good dish or a bad dish - always try to be patient and be genuine. Always try to be respectful and be grateful. Always try to be appreciative and be prepared.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The truth is always in the middle</title>
      <link>/post/2021/02/21/the-truth-is-always-in-the-middle/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021/02/21/the-truth-is-always-in-the-middle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A former boss of mine once told me &amp;ldquo;the truth is always in the middle&amp;rdquo;. He meant that as a rule of thumb to life&amp;rsquo;s many problems, if not all. Whenever there are two or more competing options to choose from, the best one is likely the one in the middle - the middleground, so to speak. This middleground balances the pros and the cons of the various options, advantageous in some way and sacrificing in some other way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have used his rule of thumb as a heuristic, or a mental shortcut, ever since. It makes sense to me. The reason why it makes sense is because of incomplete information - to be precise, it&amp;rsquo;s because of the incomplete information available to different people in a given problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may be familiar with the story of the three blind men and an elephant. Three blind men were asked to name the object that they are touching. The first blind man touches the elephant&amp;rsquo;s trunk, and says that the object is a snake. The second blind man touches the elephant&amp;rsquo;s leg, and says that the object is a tree trunk. The third blind man touches the elephant&amp;rsquo;s side, and says that the object is a wall. The three blind men have access to different sets of incomplete information, and make conclusions based on what they know. The truth, however, lies somewhere in the middle of a snake, a tree trunk, and a wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all have different perspectives when facing the same problem - some of us may be more different than others. Despite the differences, one thing is for sure - all of us likely have incomplete information to work with, even if we think that we already have all the important information. We may not know what we don&amp;rsquo;t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So don&amp;rsquo;t be too quick to judge the next time you have to make a decision. Between competing options, the truth is always in the middle.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On punctuality</title>
      <link>/post/2021/01/30/on-punctuality/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021/01/30/on-punctuality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t be late. Always be early or punctual. Being on time for appointments is a basic form of respect for others and for others&amp;rsquo; time. It shows you regard the others as important people in your life - important enough for you to properly plan your time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common reason I hear to justify lateness is this: since others will be late, I should not waste my time to be early or punctual, and then wait for others to arrive. Instead, I should be late as well. A tit for a tat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First and foremost, two wrongs don&amp;rsquo;t make a right. Just because others are late, does not give us a free pass to be late; just because others disrespect our time, does not give us a free pass to disrespect theirs. Our principles for punctuality and respect hold true always - regardless of others&amp;rsquo; lateness and disrespect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often accompanied with this tit-for-tat reason for lateness, are frustration, irritation, possibly even anger. Remind yourself on &lt;a href=&#34;https://thestatsguy.rbind.io/post/2020/12/06/our-happiness-is-within-our-control/&#34;&gt;the separation between what is controllable and what is not&lt;/a&gt;. The actions of others are not within our control. And so, as much as possible, we should not let something not within our control to affect our emotions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tit-for-tat is also the worst scenario in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prisoner%27s_dilemma&#34;&gt;Prisoner&amp;rsquo;s Dilemma&lt;/a&gt; - a lose-lose for everyone. We can instead choose to bring everyone out of a lose-lose situation, by first being punctual consistently - an action that is definitely within our control. By showing everyone that we are willing to be punctual consistently, we are offering a gesture of goodwill. Again, whether others will return the gesture is beyond our control. But, at the very least, we know that we have tried our best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, if we have no choice but to be late, because of a traffic jam, a train breakdown, or a last minute meeting by your boss or customer, then we should have the courtesy to inform others as early as possible, and give an estimation of when we can arrive. This is again a basic form of respect, and especially practicable with the help of smartphones today. The traffic jam is not within our control, but a short WhatsApp message is, surely, within our control.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On setting goals</title>
      <link>/post/2021/01/22/on-setting-goals/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021/01/22/on-setting-goals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Do you have goals? Things that you want to achieve before you die. Most people do. Good grades and qualifications, a happy family, a well-paying job, a strong and healthy body, a thriving business, a lot of zeroes at the back of your bank account balance. It is easy to select a number of goals, some from the list above, that resonates with you - then set them as your goals. It&amp;rsquo;s a simple exercise, done by asking yourself: what do you want in your life, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; years from now? To be precise, what do you want to &lt;strong&gt;enjoy&lt;/strong&gt; in your life, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; years from now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more difficult, more important, yet often neglected question is: what do you want to &lt;strong&gt;endure&lt;/strong&gt; in your life, from now to &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; years later?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goals are about endurance - choosing the few things that you want to endure. Goals are not about enjoyment - choosing the few (or many) things that you want to enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putting this in another way: a goal that doesn&amp;rsquo;t need any labour or sacrifice or endurance, is not a goal. It is not a goal because if it needs no sacrifice, that means you can already have it right now. Goals are, by definition, painful and laborious,  back-breaking and time-consuming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask yourself then: what are you choosing to endure? What do you wish to endure? What do you think are worthy of your endurance? Perhaps these are hard questions to think about - surely harder than what do you wish to enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let&amp;rsquo;s think smaller. For your 2021 new year resolution, ask yourself: in 2021, what are you choosing to endure? In 2021, what do you wish to endure? In 2021, what do you think are worthy of your endurance? Set these as your goals for this new year.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
