<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Philosophy on The Stats Guy</title>
    <link>/categories/philosophy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Philosophy on The Stats Guy</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 31 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Interest in transcendentalism</title>
      <link>/post/2021/07/31/interest-in-transcendentalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021/07/31/interest-in-transcendentalism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I developed an interest in the works of Ralph Waldo Emerson and Henry David Thoreau. Both Emerson and Thoreau are 19th century Transcendentalists. Of the few things that Transcendentalism stands for, individualism and the importance of nature resonate with me the most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will spending some time reading Emerson&amp;rsquo;s Nature and Self-reliance, and Thoreau&amp;rsquo;s Walden. Nature and Self-reliance are what I know to be the fundamentals of Transcendentalism. Both Emerson&amp;rsquo;s and Thoreau&amp;rsquo;s writings are closer to literary writing than philosophical writing, so I will probably need a bit of translation and transcription to modern English. After all, Emerson is recognized as the literary force in America that led the way in breaking away from Great Britain&amp;rsquo;s and Europe&amp;rsquo;s style of literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My quest is to sought and define my own philosophy of life, following Seneca: &amp;ldquo;this is is my own custom; from the many things which I have read, I claim some one part for myself.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a previous post, I identified the top three elements of my philosophy - dichotomy of control, natural and necessary needs, and lathe biosas - coming from both Epictetus and Epicurus. My reading is guiding me to explore Alderian psychology (separation of tasks, interpersonal relationships, feeling of community), the value of idleness, existentialism and general continental philosophy, as well as transcendentalism (nature, self-reliance, individualism). There are elements in each of these areas that I can pick up and unify, and define my own philosophy of life. This is my quest, and what I would like to write about the most, moving forward.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Stoicism, Epicureanism, and primary sources</title>
      <link>/post/2021/06/30/on-stoicism-epicureanism-and-primary-sources/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021/06/30/on-stoicism-epicureanism-and-primary-sources/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The ancient philosophers always regarded their teachings as tools to help ordinary people lead good and happy lives. The best examples of these philosophies are Stoicism and Epicureanism. Both philosophies first make observations of the physical world and of the gods (gods as in divine intervention, or the presence of a creator or fate), and of knowledge and learning. From these metaphysical and epistemological observations, the Stoics and Epicureans then derive their ethics - how to live a good life (the word &amp;lsquo;ethics&amp;rsquo; is used in a slightly different way today).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stoicism has become mainstream-popular these days. Personalities like Ryan Holiday and academics like Massimo Pigliucci have invested much effort to make Stoic wisdom available to the public. This is done through modern tools like podcasts, blog posts, mailing lists, and books. Writers like Robert Woolston even went as far as writing on &amp;lsquo;Stoicism 2.0&amp;rsquo; - to modernize Stoicism for 21st century consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stoicism benefitted from the survival of many great texts written by the ancients - most notably in today&amp;rsquo;s Stoicism discourses are Marcus Aurelius&amp;rsquo; &lt;em&gt;Meditations&lt;/em&gt;, Epictetus&amp;rsquo; &lt;em&gt;Discourses&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Enchiridion&lt;/em&gt; (or &amp;lsquo;&lt;em&gt;Handbook&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo;), and Seneca&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Letters&lt;/em&gt;. Because Stoic philosophy recognizes the presence of a benevolent god, the Church determined Stoicism to be compatible with Christianity, and have largely left Stoic texts untouched. Many Stoic texts have survived past antiquity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Epicureanism never had such luck. Epicureanism is often misunderstood as a luxurious lifestyle of a gourmet or connoisseur - the opposite of what Epicurus taught. This mischaracterization of Epicurean hedonism is due to the deliberate misrepresentation by the Church and medieval scholars - partly because of the nonexistence or nonchalance of a god or gods in Epicurean philosophy. Many Epicurean texts were destroyed or suppressed or have gone missing. Epicurus himself was a prolific writer, but few of his works survived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, we are left with these few great texts as primary sources of Epicureanism:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Epicurus&amp;rsquo; &lt;em&gt;Letters to Herodotus&lt;/em&gt; (on metaphysics)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Epicurus&amp;rsquo; &lt;em&gt;Letters to Pythocles&lt;/em&gt; (on meteorology)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Epicurus&amp;rsquo; &lt;em&gt;Letters to Menoeceus&lt;/em&gt; (on ethics, and living life)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Vatican Collection of Epicurus Sayings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Epicurus&amp;rsquo; &lt;em&gt;Principal Doctrines&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lucretius&amp;rsquo; &lt;em&gt;On the Nature of Things&lt;/em&gt; (a poem, in fact)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not have a Epictetus-/Arrian-style &lt;em&gt;Enchiridion&lt;/em&gt; handbook, and we rely on academics like Catherine Wilson and John Sellars to analyze and distill Epicurean wisdom on our behalf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is unfortunate that Epicureanism has suffered gravely from its loss of primary sources. I find myself relating more to Epicurean thinking (natural and necessary needs, lathe biosas, katastematic pleasures) than Stoic thinking (four virtues, role ethics) - though Epictetus&amp;rsquo; dichotomy of control is front and center in my own philosophy of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through writing this blog, I hope to study both Stoicism and Epicureanism, and write about elements of the Epicurean philosophy that my readers may relate to, as well.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Three elements of my philosophy</title>
      <link>/post/2021/06/30/three-elements-of-my-philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021/06/30/three-elements-of-my-philosophy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is my own custom; from the many things which I have read, I claim some one part for myself. - Seneca, Letters to Lucilius, Letter II&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been reading philosophy for a while now - mostly Hellenistic philosophy. So far, there are three principles from the Hellenistic philosophies of Stoicism and Epicureanism that made the biggest impression on me. In formulating elements of my own philosophy, I have placed these three elements front and centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Dichotomy of control (Stoicism)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By far the most influential element of Stoicism to me, is the dichotomy of control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are responsible for some things, while there are others for which we cannot be held responsible. The former include our judgement, our impulse, our desire, aversion, and our mental faculties in general; the latter include the body, material possessions, our reputations, status - in a word, anything not in our power to control. The former are naturally free, unconstrainted and unimpeded, while the latter are frail, inferior, subject to restraint - and none of our affair. - Epictetus, Enchiridion, Chapter I&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we realize the inevitability of the dichotomy of control, the desire for many things can be eliminated. Immense wealth, fame, power, recognition, opinions of others, promotions at work, reciprocal love - all of these lie strictly outside of our control. So placing them as goals or objectives or purposes in our lives will not lead to a good life. Instead, we should pursue needs that will directly fulfil us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Natural and necessary needs (Epicureanism)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Epicurus taught us to focus our efforts on fulfilling our natural and necessary needs. These includes food, clothes, shelter as basic needs, as well as friends, freedom, and philosophy (as in wisdom or knowledge).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cry of the flesh: not to be hungry, not to be thirsty, not to be cold. For if someone has these things and is confident of having them in the future, he might contend even with Zeus for happiness. - Epicurus, Vatican Collection of Epicurus Sayings&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the things which wisdom provides for the blessedness of one&amp;rsquo;s whole life, by far the greatest is the possession of friendship. - Epicurus, Vatican Collection of Epicurus Sayings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic needs of food, clothes and shelter should be secured not just for the present but also the future - hence the importance of financial freedom and independence. Likewise, meaningful and deep friendships, freedom to do and experience the things in life, and gaining knowledge and learning philosophy - these give meaning to our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Lathe biosas (Epicureanism)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We must free ourselves from the prison of everyday affairs and politics. - Epicurus, Vatican Collection of Epicurus Sayings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, Epicurus taught us to practise lathe biosas - to live in obscurity. In his time during the Hellenistic era, this meant to withdraw from politics, withdraw from the military, and withdraw from high posts and ranks. When we live in obscurity, not only will we rid ourselves of matters that are outside of our control (dichotomy of control), we also can spend our time and focus on constantly fulfilling our natural and necessary needs, and engage in the relevant kinetic and katastematic pleasures. We also avoid being too caught up in anything related to visibility, promotions, rank, control over others, or gaining others&amp;rsquo; validation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Our happiness is within our control</title>
      <link>/post/2020/12/06/our-happiness-is-within-our-control/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020/12/06/our-happiness-is-within-our-control/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://miro.medium.com/max/2866/1*hgdweKCUQ0l3zsUTWvrgxg.png&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Briefly re-reading Marcus Aurelius&amp;rsquo; Meditations, and this line caught my attention once again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; our will rules its own domain. Otherwise the harm they [other people] do would cause harm to me. Which is not what God intended —for my happiness to rest with someone else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not a religious person by any means, but this line in Meditations does resonate with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcus Aurelius&amp;rsquo; Meditations is well known to be one of the cornerstone texts underpinning the philosophy of Stoicism. In order to understand better what Marcus Aurelius was saying, let me briefly explain a key Stoic principle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the primary principles in Stoicism is the separation between factors that are within your control, and factors that are beyond your control. Stoics advocate for the acceptance of whatever fate brings, i.e. outside of your control (&lt;em&gt;Amor Fati&lt;/em&gt; - Latin for &amp;ldquo;love your fate&amp;rdquo;). This includes many things in life - the unexpected cancer or car accident, the unfaithful spouse - and certainly include the actions, thoughts, emotions, and words of other people. Treat these external factors objectively, and accept them in your stride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This applies for both the good and the bad. As long as they are beyond your control, we should be as humble, graceful, and accepting as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being upset by the opinions of others, for example, is a futile exercise as you cannot control how others think. Likewise, the fame and glory that we seek is also a function of the opinions&amp;rsquo; of others - hardly something we control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, people in your lives come and go - but your will, your mind, your thoughts will stay with you for as long as you live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, Stoic teachings tell us to solely focus on factors that we can indeed control. This includes how we think, what we speak, how we spend our time, how hard we work and study, how healthily we eat, how much we exercise, how much time we spend with our loved ones. By focusing our attention on these controllable factors, not only will we be at peace, we will also be steadily improving our lives as we hustle along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is what Marcus Aurelius was trying to say to himself: &amp;ldquo;our will rules its own domain&amp;rdquo;, actions by others does not harm us - our happiness rest with ourselves, not others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, it is our minds, thoughts, and actions that bring us happiness, and nothing else. This should be a liberating idea, to say the least. We do not need the right spouse or the right career or the right house or the right &amp;ldquo;fill in the blank&amp;rdquo; to be happy. Marcus Aurelius himself was a Roman Emperor (and one of the better ones at his job) and ruled over Rome for close to two decades - yet he attributes none of his authority and wealth to the peace and happiness he enjoyed&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:In-fact-he-was-r&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:In-fact-he-was-r&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our happiness is within our control. The question then is - what we can do on our
end, i.e. factors that we can control, to help ourselves achieve this happiness?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:In-fact-he-was-r&#34;&gt;In fact, he was rather explicit in Meditations that the Stoic philosophy he practiced was to help him cope with the authority that he had as a Roman Emperor. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:In-fact-he-was-r&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do Less, Better</title>
      <link>/post/2019/02/23/do-less-better/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019/02/23/do-less-better/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://dailystoic.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/ds_Podcast.jpg&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:image --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;wp-block-image&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;The Daily Stoic podcast&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:image --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:quote --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;wp-block-quote&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here’s the simple recipe for improvement and for happiness. It comes from Marcus Aurelius and the fact that it came from such a busy man with so many obligations and responsibilities should not be forgotten.&amp;nbsp;“&lt;strong&gt;If you seek tranquility&lt;/strong&gt;,” he said, “&lt;strong&gt;do less.&lt;/strong&gt;”&amp;nbsp;And then he follows the note to himself with some clarification. Not nothing, less. &lt;strong&gt;Do only what’s essential.&lt;/strong&gt; “Which brings a double satisfaction,” he writes “to do less, better.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Follow this advice today and everyday. So much of what we think we must do, so much of what we end up doing is not essential. We do it out of habit. We do it out of guilt. We do it out of laziness or we do it out of greedy ambition. And then we wonder why our performance suffers. We wonder why our heart isn’t really in it.&amp;nbsp;Of course it isn’t. &lt;strong&gt;We know deep down there’s no point&lt;/strong&gt;.&amp;nbsp;But if we could do less inessential stuff, &lt;strong&gt;we’d be able to better do what is essential.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’d also get a taste of that tranquility that Marcus was talking about. A double satisfaction.&amp;nbsp; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;The Daily Stoic&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:quote --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The transcript above (emphasis my own) comes from one of the recent episodes in &lt;a href=&#34;https://dailystoic.com/podcast/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Daily Stoic&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; podcast, talking about the idea of &lt;a href=&#34;https://open.spotify.com/episode/5WiVTsMI5oBoipBEZB4Q3X&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Do Less, Better&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; . In this modern age of rapid information and content flow day in, day out, we might sometimes find ourselves lost in figuring out our true objectives in life. There seems to be too many things to work on and optimize, with too little time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;What then, is (in)essential?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not difficult to comprehend the underlying message at first glance - focus on what&amp;rsquo;s essential (do less), and do them well (better). What then, would be considered essential? Well, for most people, it would along the lines of health, wealth, family and friends, etc.  As I reflect on my experiences and perspective in life today, these are the things that I deem are essential to me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:list --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;My health - maintaining my health with diet and exercise&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;My livelihood - increasing my proficiency and knowledge in data science and machine learning, as this is my current and (very likely) future livelihood&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;My family and friends&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Reading and writing - the best outlets for thoughts, reflections, analysis, and planning&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;My finances - investing well, seeking sustainable, feasible passive and alternative income. Instead of trading time for money like everyone in this modern rat race of life, choose to trade money for time and experience in this world.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;My skills - self-sufficient skills that reasonably reduces living expenses and my reliance on society and others.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:list --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However,  I find it a lot more instructive in this case to think about what then would be inessential? Think about that for a moment. What is inessential in your life?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;~&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To me, there is a clear relationship between essential/inessential and needs/wants. Inessential things are things that you don&amp;rsquo;t need, but they became talking points and occupy your &amp;ldquo;brainspace&amp;rdquo; in the first place simply because you want these things. And there are many things out there that induces a sense of want, though they are not necessarily needed. This is especially so on the typical social media platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this sense, to be truly efficient and satisfied, identify things that you might once thought you really need, but not necessarily so. Then, &lt;strong&gt;Do Less&lt;/strong&gt; - focus on the essential, and do them &lt;strong&gt;Better&lt;/strong&gt;. Spend your waking time and your physical and mental energy on them to optimize or master them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am in this stage in my life right now where my focus in life gets sharper as time passes. Yes, sometimes I do get a little lost and confused, especially when my mental guard is down. However, that sense of tranquility will always kick in when you realize that at the end of the day, your time has been well-spent, improving, optimizing, and mastering the essential, while weeding out the inessential. It is indeed a satisfying experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
