<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Stats finance on The Stats Guy</title>
    <link>/categories/stats-finance/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Stats finance on The Stats Guy</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/stats-finance/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>[wip] Introduction to modern portfolio theory</title>
      <link>/post/2020/04/10/wip-introduction-to-modern-portfolio-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020/04/10/wip-introduction-to-modern-portfolio-theory/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionProblem formulationPortfolio weightsPortfolio expectation and varianceThe math behind diversificationTwo uncorrelated assetsTwo correlated assetsStarting with two assetsEfficient PortfoliosMinimum variance portfolioWIPIntroductionIn this post, I would like to talk about modern portfolio theory (MPT), a key topic in finance. The first couple of lines in the MPT Wikipedia article explains it very well:
(MPT) is a mathematical framework for assembling a portfolio of assets such that the expected return is maximized for a given level of risk.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[short] Statistical methods in finance series</title>
      <link>/post/2020/03/19/short-statistical-methods-in-finance-series/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020/03/19/short-statistical-methods-in-finance-series/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s a sleepless night, so I decided to write a little. This will be the first part of a series that I would like to write about, circling around the use of statistical methods in finance. Most of the content that I will be exploring would originate from one of my NUS M.Sc Statistics modules, Advanced Statistical Methods in Finance. I was taught by Prof Xia Yingcun when I did this module.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[short] Stylized facts in statistical finance</title>
      <link>/post/2019/04/04/short-stylized-facts-in-statistical-finance/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019/04/04/short-stylized-facts-in-statistical-finance/</guid>
      <description>In statistical finance (as well as in certain areas in social science), stylized facts are empirical observations summarized in a theory-like form, and are generally representative under broad circumstances.
Stylized facts are commonly used in statistical finance to address and summarize phenomenon directly observed from historical data, and explainable with a certain level of theoretical consistency and logic (&#34;... this makes sense to me&#34;). Stylized facts may often guide investigations and explorations into certain topics of interest, functioning perhaps as assumptions to be either built upon or proven otherwise.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>