<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The Stats Guy</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on The Stats Guy</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Fundamental Analysis 101: A basic overview of the fundamental analysis of stocks</title>
      <link>/2019/06/08/fundamental-analysis-101-a-basic-overview-of-the-fundamental-analysis-of-stocks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/06/08/fundamental-analysis-101-a-basic-overview-of-the-fundamental-analysis-of-stocks/</guid>
      <description>In this post, I would like to give an overview of the principles and concepts in the fundamental analysis of stocks.
What is fundamental analysis? Well, fundamental analysis (FA) is the analysis of the fundamentals of a company. The fundamentals of the company are trying to capture essentially the health of the company, in the present and future. The objective of FA is to discern a point of view on the current and future prospects of a company – the actionability from this point of view is of course whether to buy (or short-sell) the stock.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stylized facts in statistical finance</title>
      <link>/2019/04/04/stylized-facts-in-statistical-finance/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/04/04/stylized-facts-in-statistical-finance/</guid>
      <description>In statistical finance (as well as in certain areas in social science), stylized facts are empirical observations summarized in a theory-like form, and are generally representative under broad circumstances.
Stylized facts are commonly used in statistical finance to address and summarize phenomenon directly observed from historical data, and explainable with a certain level of theoretical consistency and logic (&#34;... this makes sense to me&#34;). Stylized facts may often guide investigations and explorations into certain topics of interest, functioning perhaps as assumptions to be either built upon or proven otherwise.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seven tips for working on analytics delivery projects</title>
      <link>/2019/03/17/seven-tips-for-working-on-analytics-delivery-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/03/17/seven-tips-for-working-on-analytics-delivery-projects/</guid>
      <description>Following are seven tips / tricks / hacks that I came to learnt (some of them the hard way) and compiled as a data scientist / delivery consultant / data science consultant. In brief, they are:
You to Yourself
 Develop a strategy
 Keep a delivery journal
 Plan your daily activities
 Frontload your projects
  You to Others
 Show mediocre output to no one</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Master of Science in Statistics programme in NUS</title>
      <link>/2019/02/09/my-master-of-science-in-statistics-programme-in-nus/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/02/09/my-master-of-science-in-statistics-programme-in-nus/</guid>
      <description>I have gotten quite a couple of questions regarding my current MSc Statistics programme in NUS. Here are some broadstroke information about the programme and how I am approaching it.
 I&amp;rsquo;m doing the MSc by Coursework programme, which means a research thesis is not part of my curriculum. A MSc by Research option is available.
 Under the Coursework programme, there is a Track 1 (40MC) programme and a Track 2 (80MC) one.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why ensemble modelling works so well - and one often neglected principle</title>
      <link>/2018/12/25/why-ensemble-modelling-works-so-well-and-one-often-neglected-principle/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/12/25/why-ensemble-modelling-works-so-well-and-one-often-neglected-principle/</guid>
      <description>Putting models together in an ensemble learning fashion is a popular technique amongst Data Scientists
Ensemble learning is the simultaneous use of multiple predictive models to arrive at a single prediction, based on a collective decision made together by all models in the ensemble. It&#39;s a common and popular technique used in predictive modelling, especially when individual models are failing to produce the required performance levels, in terms of e.g. accuracy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Rich by Retirement by Joshua Giersch</title>
      <link>/2018/09/16/book-review-rich-by-retirement-by-joshua-giersch/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/09/16/book-review-rich-by-retirement-by-joshua-giersch/</guid>
      <description>Joshua Giersch, better known as “Shiny Things”, is an investment guru who has been generously giving investing advice on HardwareZone and his blog. His advice are consistently dished out with the SG context in mind, and his book &amp;ldquo;Rich by Retirement: How Singaporeans Can Invest Smart and Retire Wealthy&amp;rdquo;, is, in essence, the consolidation of all of his tips and hacks on being a successful investor in SG.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2016 21:48:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>About this blog This blog is simply an outlet for me to write, and in the process, reflect and analyse, about things in life that I naturally leaned towards – machine learning, investing, personal finances, analyzing financial data, and stoicism.
Too true to be funny? – a post I saw on Reddit
 Data science: the blog was so named “the stats guy” largely because that became my nickname amongst some friends.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello R Markdown - test change</title>
      <link>/2015/07/23/hello-r-markdown-test-change/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/07/23/hello-r-markdown-test-change/</guid>
      <description>R MarkdownHello! This is an R Markdown document. Markdown is a simple formatting syntax for authoring HTML, PDF, and MS Word documents. For more details on using R Markdown see http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com.
You can embed an R code chunk like this:
summary(cars)## speed dist ## Min. : 4.0 Min. : 2.00 ## 1st Qu.:12.0 1st Qu.: 26.00 ## Median :15.0 Median : 36.00 ## Mean :15.4 Mean : 42.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>