<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The Stats Guy</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on The Stats Guy</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Rich by Retirement by Joshua Giersch</title>
      <link>/2018/09/16/book-review-rich-by-retirement-by-joshua-giersch/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/09/16/book-review-rich-by-retirement-by-joshua-giersch/</guid>
      <description>Joshua Giersch, better known as “Shiny Things”, is an investment guru who has been generously giving investing advice on HardwareZone and his blog. His advice are consistently dished out with the SG context in mind, and his book &amp;ldquo;Rich by Retirement: How Singaporeans Can Invest Smart and Retire Wealthy&amp;rdquo;, is, in essence, the consolidation of all of his tips and hacks on being a successful investor in SG.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Plain Markdown Post</title>
      <link>/2016/12/30/a-plain-markdown-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Dec 2016 21:49:57 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/12/30/a-plain-markdown-post/</guid>
      <description>This is a post written in plain Markdown (*.md) instead of R Markdown (*.Rmd). The major differences are:
 You cannot run any R code in a plain Markdown document, whereas in an R Markdown document, you can embed R code chunks (```{r}); A plain Markdown post is rendered through Blackfriday, and an R Markdown document is compiled by rmarkdown and Pandoc.  There are many differences in syntax between Blackfriday&amp;rsquo;s Markdown and Pandoc&amp;rsquo;s Markdown.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2016 21:48:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>About this blog This blog is simply an outlet for me to write, and in the process, reflect and analyse, about things in life that I naturally leaned towards – machine learning, investing, personal finances, analyzing financial data, and stoicism.
Too true to be funny? – a post I saw on Reddit
 Data science: the blog was so named “the stats guy” largely because that became my nickname amongst some friends.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello R Markdown - test change</title>
      <link>/2015/07/23/hello-r-markdown-test-change/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/07/23/hello-r-markdown-test-change/</guid>
      <description>R MarkdownHello! This is an R Markdown document. Markdown is a simple formatting syntax for authoring HTML, PDF, and MS Word documents. For more details on using R Markdown see http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com.
You can embed an R code chunk like this:
summary(cars)## speed dist ## Min. : 4.0 Min. : 2.00 ## 1st Qu.:12.0 1st Qu.: 26.00 ## Median :15.0 Median : 36.00 ## Mean :15.4 Mean : 42.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>