<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on The Stats Guy</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on The Stats Guy</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick start to using Git and GitHub</title>
      <link>/2020/03/21/quick-start-to-using-git-and-github/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/03/21/quick-start-to-using-git-and-github/</guid>
      <description>Git is pretty awesome. My most common &amp;ldquo;use case&amp;rdquo; for Git is working as a solo developer, working on different machines (home and work machines) and using GitHub to keep my work in place.
Following is the most straightforward way to start use Git and Github in this no-brainer manner. During development, only run steps indicated by * (7 - code, 9 - stage, 10 - commit, 12 - push).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical methods in finance series - Part 1</title>
      <link>/2020/03/19/statistical-methods-in-finance-series-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/03/19/statistical-methods-in-finance-series-part-1/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s a sleepless night, so I decided to write a little. This will be the first part of a series that I would like to write about, circling around the use of statistical methods in finance. Most of the content that I will be exploring would originate from one of my NUS M.Sc Statistics modules, Advanced Statistical Methods in Finance. I was taught by Prof Xia Yingcun when I did this module.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Random Forests in R</title>
      <link>/2020/03/15/random-forests-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/03/15/random-forests-in-r/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionAs the name suggests, random forest models basically contain an ensemble of decision tree models, with each decision tree predicting the same response variable. The response may be categorical, in which case being a classification problem, or continuous / numerical, being a regression problem.
In this short tutorial, we will go through the use of tree-based methods (decision tree, bagging model, and random forest) for both classification and regression problems.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using waterfall charts to visualize feature contributions</title>
      <link>/2020/03/15/using-waterfall-charts-to-visualize-feature-contributions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/03/15/using-waterfall-charts-to-visualize-feature-contributions/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionI am using waterfall charts drawn in ggplot2 to visualize GLM coefficients, for regression and classification.
RegressionPreparationlibrary(MASS)library(caret)## Loading required package: lattice## Loading required package: ggplot2## Warning: package &amp;#39;ggplot2&amp;#39; was built under R version 3.5.3library(magrittr)library(ggplot2)data(Boston)set.seed(123)# mean centeringb2 &amp;lt;- preProcess(Boston, method = &amp;quot;center&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;% predict(., Boston)idx &amp;lt;- createDataPartition(b2$medv, p = 0.8, list = FALSE)train &amp;lt;- Boston[idx,]test &amp;lt;- Boston[-idx,]mod0 &amp;lt;- lm(data = train, medv ~.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fundamental Analysis 101: A basic overview of the fundamental analysis of stocks</title>
      <link>/2019/06/08/fundamental-analysis-101-a-basic-overview-of-the-fundamental-analysis-of-stocks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/06/08/fundamental-analysis-101-a-basic-overview-of-the-fundamental-analysis-of-stocks/</guid>
      <description>In this post, I would like to give an overview of the principles and concepts in the fundamental analysis of stocks.
What is fundamental analysis? Well, fundamental analysis (FA) is the analysis of the fundamentals of a company. The fundamentals of the company are trying to capture essentially the health of the company, in the present and future. The objective of FA is to discern a point of view on the current and future prospects of a company – the actionability from this point of view is of course whether to buy (or short-sell) the stock.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>REITs 101: Introduction to real estate investment trusts - Part 2</title>
      <link>/2019/05/29/reits-101-introduction-to-real-estate-investment-trusts-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/05/29/reits-101-introduction-to-real-estate-investment-trusts-part-2/</guid>
      <description>https://i.etsystatic.com/6111470/r/il/35f144/1417264877/il_fullxfull.1417264877_awhp.jpg  The Singapore skyline at night. Source. This is Part 2 from the post &amp;ldquo;REITs 101: Introduction to real estate investment trusts – Part&amp;nbsp;1&amp;rdquo;. Be sure to check that out before going further here.
In my previous post, I started talking about the real estate investment trusts, or Reits for short, in the following fashion:
What are Reits –&amp;nbsp;covered in Part 1What makes Reits different from other investment vehicles –&amp;nbsp;covered in Part 1 Why invest in ReitsWhat are the different types of ReitsHow to evaluate a Reit 3.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Medtech 101: An overview of the medical device industry</title>
      <link>/2019/05/27/medtech-101-an-overview-of-the-medical-device-industry/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/05/27/medtech-101-an-overview-of-the-medical-device-industry/</guid>
      <description>https://www.flintec.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/medical.jpeg Source. In this post, I will be doing a 101 dissection of the medical device industry. It’s a somewhat not-so-popular industry from the perspective of retail investing, but I have had some prior experience in this space, so it’s a tad easier for me to conduct some levels of analysis on companies in this space.
I will work through the following pointers in this piece, and hopefully at the end of it, allow the reader to have some level of appreciation for the industry as a whole.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>REITs 101: Introduction to real estate investment trusts - Part 1</title>
      <link>/2019/05/20/reits-101-introduction-to-real-estate-investment-trusts-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/05/20/reits-101-introduction-to-real-estate-investment-trusts-part-1/</guid>
      <description>https://i.etsystatic.com/6111470/r/il/35f144/1417264877/il_fullxfull.1417264877_awhp.jpg The Singapore skyline at night. Source. This post is a 101 dissection of real estate investment trusts, REITs or Reits in short. As the full content of this topics is pretty long and I plan to make this 101 comprehensive, I will be publishing this piece in 2 parts, touching on the following:
What are ReitsWhat makes Reits different from other investment vehiclesWhy invest in Reits - covered in Part 2What are the different types of Reits - covered in Part 2 How to evaluate a Reit - covered in Part 2 As you can see, there&amp;rsquo;s plenty to talk about even in a 101 piece, so let&amp;rsquo;s get straight to it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A guide to dollar cost averaging in Singapore - Part 2</title>
      <link>/2019/04/17/a-guide-to-dollar-cost-averaging-in-singapore-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/04/17/a-guide-to-dollar-cost-averaging-in-singapore-part-2/</guid>
      <description>Dollar cost averaging and regular savings plans are good ways for long-term investors to build up their nest egg in Singapore. Image&amp;nbsp;source.  This is Part 2 from the post &amp;ldquo;A guide to dollar cost averaging in Singapore – Part 1&amp;rdquo;. Be sure to check that out first before going further here.
In my previous post back in January 2019, I introduced the various Regular Savings Plans (RSP) that can be used to do automated dollar cost averaging (DCA) in Singapore, namely:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stylized facts in statistical finance</title>
      <link>/2019/04/04/stylized-facts-in-statistical-finance/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/04/04/stylized-facts-in-statistical-finance/</guid>
      <description>In statistical finance (as well as in certain areas in social science), stylized facts are empirical observations summarized in a theory-like form, and are generally representative under broad circumstances.
Stylized facts are commonly used in statistical finance to address and summarize phenomenon directly observed from historical data, and explainable with a certain level of theoretical consistency and logic (&#34;... this makes sense to me&#34;). Stylized facts may often guide investigations and explorations into certain topics of interest, functioning perhaps as assumptions to be either built upon or proven otherwise.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reviewing means of stashing cash with impending recession in sight</title>
      <link>/2019/03/28/reviewing-means-of-stashing-cash-with-impending-recession-in-sight/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/03/28/reviewing-means-of-stashing-cash-with-impending-recession-in-sight/</guid>
      <description>Inversion of US Treasury yield spread. Source.  With the US Treasury yield curve inverting for the first time since 2007, we have our first reliable signal from the market that a recession is around the corner, perhaps by 2021 or earlier.
From a simple retail investing standpoint, an impending recession means that we want to stash away cash, and perhaps load some of it into our brokerage accounts when the fire sale swings by.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seven tips for working on analytics delivery projects</title>
      <link>/2019/03/17/seven-tips-for-working-on-analytics-delivery-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/03/17/seven-tips-for-working-on-analytics-delivery-projects/</guid>
      <description>Following are seven tips / tricks / hacks that I came to learnt (some of them the hard way) and compiled as a data scientist / delivery consultant / data science consultant. In brief, they are:
You to Yourself
 Develop a strategy
 Keep a delivery journal
 Plan your daily activities
 Frontload your projects
  You to Others
 Show mediocre output to no one</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paper Review: To Tune or Not to Tune the Number of Trees in Random Forest</title>
      <link>/2019/02/24/paper-review-to-tune-or-not-to-tune-the-number-of-trees-in-random-forest/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/02/24/paper-review-to-tune-or-not-to-tune-the-number-of-trees-in-random-forest/</guid>
      <description>Plotting different performance metrics against the number of trees in random forest. Source. I came across the following paper during my Masters coursework that addresses a practical issue in the use of the random forest model, and in general, any other bootstrap aggregating ensembles:
Probst, P. &amp;amp; Boulestix, A-L. (2018). To Tune or Not to Tune the Number of Trees in Random Forest. Journal of Machine Learning Research, 18(181), 1-18.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do Less, Better</title>
      <link>/2019/02/23/do-less-better/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/02/23/do-less-better/</guid>
      <description>The Daily Stoic podcast Here’s the simple recipe for improvement and for happiness. It comes from Marcus Aurelius and the fact that it came from such a busy man with so many obligations and responsibilities should not be forgotten.&amp;nbsp;“If you seek tranquility,” he said, “do less.”&amp;nbsp;And then he follows the note to himself with some clarification. Not nothing, less. Do only what’s essential. “Which brings a double satisfaction,” he writes “to do less, better.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Master of Science in Statistics programme in NUS</title>
      <link>/2019/02/09/my-master-of-science-in-statistics-programme-in-nus/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/02/09/my-master-of-science-in-statistics-programme-in-nus/</guid>
      <description>I have gotten quite a couple of questions regarding my current MSc Statistics programme in NUS. Here are some broadstroke information about the programme and how I am approaching it.
 I&amp;rsquo;m doing the MSc by Coursework programme, which means a research thesis is not part of my curriculum. A MSc by Research option is available.
 Under the Coursework programme, there is a Track 1 (40MC) programme and a Track 2 (80MC) one.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Machine Learning Life Cycle - how to run a ML project</title>
      <link>/2019/01/20/the-machine-learning-life-cycle-how-to-run-a-ml-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/20/the-machine-learning-life-cycle-how-to-run-a-ml-project/</guid>
      <description>The Machine Learning Life Cycle from DataRobot.
I recently came across this page in the DataRobot Artificial Intelligence Wiki. If you don&#39;t already know, DataRobot is currently one of the top automated machine learning platform in the market, with emphasis on supervised learning and citizen data science. I am quite a big fan of their platform - even though I don&#39;t use it in my work, I believe that they and their competitors in the market are heading into the right direction towards automated machine learning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A guide to dollar cost averaging in Singapore - Part 1</title>
      <link>/2019/01/13/a-guide-to-dollar-cost-averaging-in-singapore-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/13/a-guide-to-dollar-cost-averaging-in-singapore-part-1/</guid>
      <description>Dollar cost averaging and regular savings plans are good ways for long-term investors to build up their nest egg in Singapore. Image&amp;nbsp;source. Happy New Year from Korea everyone! I am currently on a business trip in Seoul, visiting our Korean counterparts for 2 weeks. Besides the weeknight / weekend day trips to popular spots like Myeongdong and Dongdaemun, I have also found some time to do a bit of writing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A repertoire of data scientist interview questions - with a twist</title>
      <link>/2018/12/28/a-repertoire-of-data-scientist-interview-questions-with-a-twist/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/12/28/a-repertoire-of-data-scientist-interview-questions-with-a-twist/</guid>
      <description>Machine Learning. Nothing to do with my intended topic, just a random xkcd comic that I thought is funny. Source.
(This post will be continually updated so as to capture more questions and answers along the way. To be honest I don&amp;rsquo;t think I have the best answers to some of these questions as well. Still learning. If you think that there&amp;rsquo;s a better way to tackle these questions, or maybe even that the question is set out in the wrong way in the first place, feel free to reach out or leave a comment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why ensemble modelling works so well - and one often neglected principle</title>
      <link>/2018/12/25/why-ensemble-modelling-works-so-well-and-one-often-neglected-principle/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/12/25/why-ensemble-modelling-works-so-well-and-one-often-neglected-principle/</guid>
      <description>Putting models together in an ensemble learning fashion is a popular technique amongst Data Scientists
Ensemble learning is the simultaneous use of multiple predictive models to arrive at a single prediction, based on a collective decision made together by all models in the ensemble. It&#39;s a common and popular technique used in predictive modelling, especially when individual models are failing to produce the required performance levels, in terms of e.g. accuracy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Good news for fans of Singapore Savings Bonds</title>
      <link>/2018/12/21/good-news-for-fans-of-singapore-savings-bonds/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/12/21/good-news-for-fans-of-singapore-savings-bonds/</guid>
      <description>The Singapore Savings Bonds programme
Been a while since I last posted on my blog - the last month or so has been hectic for me, with the semester final examinations for my part-time Masters as well as travelling for business. Still, no excuses for slipping on my 2 posts per month commitment, so will try to make up for it in December.
Also, quick update: following my analysis of the various deposit accounts here and here, I went ahead and opened my DBS Multiplier account online, together with the DBS Live Fresh credit card.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OCBC 360 Interest structure changes - Part 2</title>
      <link>/2018/11/04/ocbc-360-interest-structure-changes-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/11/04/ocbc-360-interest-structure-changes-part-2/</guid>
      <description>The OCBC 360 Account
This is part 2 from the post &#34;OCBC 360 Interest structure changes: what&#39;s the impact on me and you? - Part 1&#34;. Be sure to check that out first before going further here.
In my previous post, I illustrated the upcoming changes to the bonus interest structure of the 360 account, and how it will be affecting me. In this post, I will be making some specific comparisons between accounts from different banks and work on some simple numbers to make a decision on my next deposit account.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of the Phillip SING Income ETF</title>
      <link>/2018/10/20/analysis-of-the-phillip-sing-income-etf/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/10/20/analysis-of-the-phillip-sing-income-etf/</guid>
      <description>Earlier this month (Oct 2018), Phillip Securities introduced a brand new ETF - the Phillip SING Income ETF, to be managed by Phillip Capital Management, Based on the name of the ETF alone, it&amp;rsquo;s easy to guess the focus of this ETF: dividend income, which is an investment style popular amongst retail investors in Singapore.
Here&amp;rsquo;s how the ETF is described on poems.com.sg:
Harvest Your Regular Income with Phillip SING Income ETF The Phillip SING Income ETF focuses on 30 high quality Singapore Listed stocks to offer investors a cost-effective and diversified exposure to the Singapore market.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OCBC 360 Interest structure changes - Part 1</title>
      <link>/2018/10/20/ocbc-360-interest-structure-changes-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/10/20/ocbc-360-interest-structure-changes-part-1/</guid>
      <description>What&amp;rsquo;s changed for the OCBC 360 account bonus interest structure
Effective from 1st Nov 2018, there will be changes to the interest structure of the&amp;nbsp;OCBC 360 account. If you are either exploring deposit accounts out there or currently using OCBC 360 (like myself), you should pay attention to these changes.
Following is the existing interest structure:
Existing interest structure
It&amp;rsquo;s a relatively straightforward structure that has requirements on salary crediting (which earns you 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Rich by Retirement by Joshua Giersch</title>
      <link>/2018/09/16/book-review-rich-by-retirement-by-joshua-giersch/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/09/16/book-review-rich-by-retirement-by-joshua-giersch/</guid>
      <description>Joshua Giersch, better known as “Shiny Things”, is an investment guru who has been generously giving investing advice on HardwareZone and his blog. His advice are consistently dished out with the SG context in mind, and his book &amp;ldquo;Rich by Retirement: How Singaporeans Can Invest Smart and Retire Wealthy&amp;rdquo;, is, in essence, the consolidation of all of his tips and hacks on being a successful investor in SG.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>