<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Finance &amp; Investing on The Stats Guy</title>
    <link>/categories/finance-investing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Finance &amp; Investing on The Stats Guy</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/finance-investing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>What is a bank run?</title>
      <link>/post/2020/11/21/what-is-a-bank-run/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020/11/21/what-is-a-bank-run/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/f/f8/Bank_Run_on_American_Union_Bank.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bank run, or a run on the bank is a situation where businesses and/or ordinary folks like ourselves, lose confidence and trust in the banks where our deposits are held. In this case, we are the lenders, lending the banks our money, in return for safe keeping and interest rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a significant number of us lose confidence in the banks that we deposit our cash in, we may all choose to withdraw our money from the banks, preferring to hold physical cash instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, in case you haven&amp;rsquo;t realize, banks these days do not actually hold most, if not all, the cash that have been deposited by depositors!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of these funds are invested in assets - and not all liquid in nature, like corporate debt or government/municipal bonds (think Singapore Government Securities). Some are highly illiquid, such as land, infrastructure or properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, when all of us decide to go to the banks to withdraw our cash, the banks may not be able to fulfil their end of the stick and return our money! When this happens, more people lose confidence, resulting in more withdrawals - a worsening feedback loop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Technically&lt;/em&gt;, in order to reduce the probability of bank runs, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basel_III&#34;&gt;Basel III&lt;/a&gt; was first purposed in 2010, just after the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Financial_crisis_of_2007%E2%80%932008&#34;&gt;2007-2008 Global Financial Crisis&lt;/a&gt;. Under Basel III, banks are obligated to hold, at any point in time, sufficient high-quality liquid assets to cover total outflow (e.g. withdrawals, debt obligations) in any 30-day period. This is known as the &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/l/liquidity-coverage-ratio.asp#:~:text=The%20liquidity%20coverage%20ratio%20is,its%20short%2Dterm%20financial%20obligations.&#34;&gt;Liquidity Coverage Ratio&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Singapore, like many other countries as well, we also have the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sdic.org.sg/&#34;&gt;SDIC&lt;/a&gt;, to allay any concerns related to withdrawals and bank insolvency:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the event a Deposit Insurance (DI) Scheme member bank or finance company fails, all of your insured deposits with that member are aggregated and insured up to S$75,000 by the Singapore Deposit Insurance Corporation Limited (SDIC). Insured deposits held in trust and client accounts held by non-bank depositors are insured up to S$75,000 per account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SDIC and similar schemes in other countries work to reduce the chance of a bank run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A little bit of history: the first ever run on the bank happened in AD 33, in the Roman Empire - the first financial crisis in the history of man. There were numerous factors contributing to the bank run, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the sinking of ships filled with assets and treasures belonging to a prominent banking institute, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the then Roman Emperor (Tiberius), who ordered, with good reason, all Roman Senators to have at least a third of their wealth to invested in the Italian land.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These and a multitude of reasons caused Roman citizens, businesses, and even the Senators to hurry to the banks and withdraw their deposits, which the banks were not able to fulfil. In the end, emperor Tiberius decided to inject cash into the Roman economy, in the form of a quantitative easing and resolved the first ever financial crisis in the history of man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is interesting to note much of finance and economics work because of the confidence that people (as economic agents) have in financial systems and the economy. Stock prices are often many times that of earnings per share (even for companies that yet have to break even), credit and loan quantums are often many times that of any form of collateral (if any at all) or annual income. We often talk about abstract concepts like the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consumer_confidence_index&#34;&gt;Consumer Confidence Index&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sec.gov/files/investor_confidence_noteOct2017.pdf&#34;&gt;investor confidence&lt;/a&gt;. We even use money (paper or otherwise) to make high-value transactions, with the confidence that the dollar bills&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:Which-used-to-be&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:Which-used-to-be&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that we receive or the digital account balance displayed on our banking applications, well, mean anything at all. Increasing confidence amongst economic agents lead to more economic activities which leads to more confidence, while likewise for the opposite - a positive feedback loop. As such, governments often have to step up, at both ends of the spectrum, in order to ensure that some form of stability is achieved - through the use of policies (fiscal, monetary), regulations, supervision and enforcement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:Which-used-to-be&#34;&gt;Which used to be backed by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gold_standard&#34;&gt;gold standard&lt;/a&gt; - confidence in the value of gold. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:Which-used-to-be&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A gentle introduction to the modern portfolio theory</title>
      <link>/post/2020/09/27/a-gentle-introduction-to-the-modern-portfolio-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020/09/27/a-gentle-introduction-to-the-modern-portfolio-theory/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div id=&#34;TOC&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#problem-formulation&#34;&gt;Problem formulation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#portfolio-weights&#34;&gt;Portfolio weights&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#portfolio-expectation-and-variance&#34;&gt;Portfolio expectation and variance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-math-behind-diversification&#34;&gt;The math behind diversification&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#two-uncorrelated-assets&#34;&gt;Two uncorrelated assets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#two-correlated-assets&#34;&gt;Two correlated assets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#starting-with-two-assets&#34;&gt;Starting with two assets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#efficient-portfolios&#34;&gt;Efficient Portfolios&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#minimum-variance-portfolio&#34;&gt;Minimum variance portfolio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#risk-free-assets&#34;&gt;Risk-free assets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#one-risky-asset-and-one-risk-free-asset&#34;&gt;One “risky” asset and one risk-free asset&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#two-risky-assets-and-one-risk-free-asset&#34;&gt;Two “risky” assets and one risk-free asset&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;introduction&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I would like to talk about modern portfolio theory (MPT), a key topic in finance. The first couple of lines in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modern_portfolio_theory&#34;&gt;MPT Wikipedia article&lt;/a&gt; explains it very well:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(MPT) is a mathematical framework for assembling a portfolio of assets such that the expected return is maximized for a given level of risk. It is a formalization and extension of diversification in investing, the idea that owning different kinds of financial assets is less risky than owning only one type. Its key insight is that an asset’s risk and return should not be assessed by itself, but by how it contributes to a portfolio’s overall risk and return. It uses the variance of asset prices as a proxy for risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The objective of the MPT is to simultaneously maximise the returns of a portfolio, while at the same time, minimise the risk of the portfolio. Generally, we all know that higher returns come with higher risk, and therefore the dual goals of maximising returns while minimising risk are at odds with each other. After all, why would an investor place himself in a riskier position without any due reward or &lt;strong&gt;risk premium&lt;/strong&gt;? It wouldn’t make sense. Note that in this and many statistical finance frameworks, risk is often measured by means of standard deviation of returns, either that of the asset or the portfolio&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a “gentle introduction” to MPT, in this post, all you need is the basic understanding of mean, variance, and covariance. I will do the rest by repeatedly applying these three statistics in the context of a portfolio - nothing more, nothing less!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Terminology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Risk premium&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; refers to the difference between the expected return between a risky asset, like a stock, and that of something that basically has no risk, like cash, Treasury Bills or Singapore Savings Bonds. Without any risk premium, there’s no reason to invest in anything other than risk-free assets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;problem-formulation&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Problem formulation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose there are &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; assets with &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(R_i, i = 1, ..., N\)&lt;/span&gt; denoting the random variables that represent their respective returns in a given time period, and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\mathbf{R} = (R_1, ..., R_N)^{T}\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their returns and risks are respectively&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[
\begin{array}{c}
r_i = ER_i \\\
\sigma_i = Var(R_i)\\\
cov(\mathbf{R}) = \Sigma = (\sigma_{ij})_{1 \le i,j \le N}
\end{array}
\]&lt;/span&gt;
We can then form a portfolio consisting of the &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; assets such that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[
\begin{array}{c}
R_{pf} = w_1R_1 + ... + w_NR_N = w^T\mathbf{R},
\end{array}
\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(R_{pf}\)&lt;/span&gt; is the return of the portfolio and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(w_i\)&lt;/span&gt; is the weight of the &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt;th asset in the portfolio, with&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[\sum_{i = 1}^{N} w_i = 1\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, the portfolio is the linear combination of the various assets under consideration. Of course, the question that becomes: how to choose &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\mathbf{w} = (w_1, ..., w_N)^T\)&lt;/span&gt; such that expected returns are maximised while minimising risk?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;portfolio-weights&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Portfolio weights&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A technical point to bring out here is that while &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\sum_{i = 1}^{N} w_i = 1\)&lt;/span&gt;, there is no constraint on individual &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(w_i\)&lt;/span&gt; to be non-negative. In fact, a negative &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(w_i\)&lt;/span&gt; implies a short position in the &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt;th asset, i.e. &lt;strong&gt;short selling&lt;/strong&gt;. This is in constrast to a &lt;em&gt;long&lt;/em&gt; position, i.e. buying the &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt;th asset. In this post, we will only consider positive &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(w_i\)&lt;/span&gt; only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Terminology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holding a &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;long&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; position in a particular asset simply means buying that particular asset. On the other hand, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;short selling&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is where one sells an asset without owning it in the first place. The asset, e.g. a stock, is borrowed from a broker or another customer of the broker. At a later point in time, a stock must then be bought back from the market and then returned to the lender. This closes the short position, and the idea is that if one is able to sell the borrowed stock at a higher price and return it at a lower price, a profit is made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;portfolio-expectation-and-variance&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Portfolio expectation and variance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this set-up, the expectation and variance of the portfolio would be&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ER_{pf} = \sum_iw_iER_i = \mathbf{w}^TE\mathbf{R}\]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[Var(R_{pf}) = \sum_iw_i^2\sigma_i^2 + \sum_i\sum_{j\neq i}w_iw_j\sigma_{ij}\]&lt;/span&gt;
where &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\sigma_{ij}\)&lt;/span&gt; is the covariance between the &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt;th and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(j\)&lt;/span&gt;th asset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[Var(R_{pf}) = \sum_i\sum_jw_iw_j\sigma_{ij} = \mathbf{w}_T\Sigma \mathbf{w}\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-math-behind-diversification&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The math behind diversification&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all know “not to put our eggs in one basket”, and have a diversified portfolio. Intutitively, we know that if we were to put all our money on a single stock, then we have placed a large bet on that one company. While we could instantly make it big just by having our one stock making it big, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loss_aversion&#34;&gt;loss aversion&lt;/a&gt; would dictate that we would rather minimise the risk of losing it all in a single stock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this sense, what diversification does to a portfolio is that it minimises risk of the portfolio. While the mean return of a portfolio depends on the mean returns of the individual assets and their respective weights, the risk of the portfolio depends on both the risk of the individual assets, as well as each asset’s relationships with the others, in terms of correlations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that placing a right mix of weights and assets would reduce the risk of the portfolio - a fundamental idea in portfolio theory. Diversification, by way of investing in multiple assets, reduces risks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s consider two instructive examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;two-uncorrelated-assets&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Two uncorrelated assets&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose we have 2 assets with returns &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(R_1\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(R_2\)&lt;/span&gt;, with the same mean and variance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[
\begin{array}{}
ER_1 = ER_2 = \mu \\\
Var(R_1) = Var(R_2) = \sigma^2
\end{array}
\]&lt;/span&gt;
Also, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(R_1\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(R_2\)&lt;/span&gt; are uncorrelated, i.e. &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\rho_{12} = 0\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investing 100% in either &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(R_1\)&lt;/span&gt; or &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(R_2\)&lt;/span&gt; would yield exactly the same return and the same risk. Now consider a portfiolio with some weight on both assets. Let &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(w\)&lt;/span&gt; be the weight for &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(R_1\)&lt;/span&gt; - then we would have &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(1-w\)&lt;/span&gt; for &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(R_2\)&lt;/span&gt;. In this portfolio, we would have&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ER_{pf} = wER_1 + (1-w)ER_2 = w\mu + (1-w)\mu = \mu\]&lt;/span&gt;
With this, we know that the return of this portfolio does not depend on &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(w\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, given that the assets are uncorrelated, we would have&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[Var(R_{pf}) = w^2Var(R_1) + (1-w)^2Var(R_2) + cov(R_1, R_2)\]&lt;/span&gt;
where &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(cov(R_1, R_2) = 0\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we would have&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[Var(R_{pf}) = (w^2 + (1-w)^2)\sigma^2\]&lt;/span&gt;
When &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(w\)&lt;/span&gt; = &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(0\)&lt;/span&gt; or &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(1\)&lt;/span&gt;, we would have &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(Var(R_{pf}) = \sigma^2\)&lt;/span&gt;. However, for any other value of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(w\)&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(0&amp;lt;w&amp;lt;1\)&lt;/span&gt;, we would have &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(Var(R_{pf}) &amp;lt; \sigma^2\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;two-correlated-assets&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Two correlated assets&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s consider a similar scenario, but this time, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(cov(R_1, R_2) \neq 0\)&lt;/span&gt;. This also means that &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(-1&amp;lt; \rho_{12} &amp;lt; 1\)&lt;/span&gt;. Consider a portfolio where &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(w = \frac{1}{2}\)&lt;/span&gt;, i.e. placing equal weight on both assets &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(R_1\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(R_2\)&lt;/span&gt;. We would then have &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(ER_{pf} = \frac{1}{2}ER_1 + \frac{1}{2}ER_2 = \mu\)&lt;/span&gt;. More importantly,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[
Var(R_{pf}) = \frac{1}{4}Var(R_1) + \frac{1}{4}Var(R_2) + 2\frac{1}{2}\frac{1}{2}Cov(R_1, R_2) \\\
= \frac{1}{4}\sigma^2 + \frac{1}{4}\sigma^2 + \frac{1}{2}\rho_{12}\sigma^2 \\\
= \frac{1}{2}(1+\rho_{12})\sigma^2
\]&lt;/span&gt;
Therefore, for any value of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\rho_{12}\)&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(-1 &amp;lt; \rho_{12} &amp;lt; 1\)&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(Var(R_{pf}) &amp;lt; \sigma^2\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;starting-with-two-assets&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Starting with two assets&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, the objective of treating portfolio selection as a statistical problem is to select individual &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(w_i\)&lt;/span&gt; such that &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(ER_{pf}\)&lt;/span&gt; is large and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(Var(R_{pf})\)&lt;/span&gt; is small. As with our two instructive examples above, we can start solving this problem by first considering &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(N = 2\)&lt;/span&gt;, that is, choosing the weights &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(w_i\)&lt;/span&gt; between two assets only. Inevitably, we would have&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[
\begin{array}{c}
ER_{pf} = \sum_iw_iER_i = w_1ER_1 + w_2ER_2 \\\
Var(R_{pf}) = \sum_iw_i^2\sigma_i^2 + \sum_i\sum_{j\neq i}w_iw_jcov(R_1, R_2) = w_1^2\sigma_1^2 + w_2^2\sigma_2^2 + w_1w_2\rho_{12}\sigma_1\sigma_2 \\\
w_1+w_2 = 1, w_2 = 1 - w_1
\end{array}
\]&lt;/span&gt;
where &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\rho_{12}\)&lt;/span&gt; is the correlation between &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(R_1\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(R_2\)&lt;/span&gt;. Again, we can let &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(w\)&lt;/span&gt; be the weight for &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(R_1\)&lt;/span&gt; - then we would have &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(1-w\)&lt;/span&gt; for &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(R_2\)&lt;/span&gt;. Simplifying,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[
ER_{pf} = wER_1 + (1-w)ER_2 = w\mu_1 + (1-w)\mu_2 \\\
Var(R_{pf}) = w^2Var(R_1) + (1-w)^2Var(R_2) + 2w_1w_2cov(R_1, R_2) \\\
= w^2\sigma_1^2+ (1-w)^2\sigma_2^2 + 2w(1-w)\rho_{12}\sigma_1\sigma_2
\]&lt;/span&gt;
Notice that in this set-up, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\mu_1\)&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\mu_2\)&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\sigma_1\)&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\sigma_2\)&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\rho_{12}\)&lt;/span&gt; are considered to be known and constant&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. We are concerned with choosing a value for &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(w\)&lt;/span&gt; such that &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(ER_{pf}\)&lt;/span&gt; is maximised, while &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(Var(R_{pf})\)&lt;/span&gt; is minimised, i.e. we treat both &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(ER_{pf}\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(Var(R_{pf})\)&lt;/span&gt; as univariate functions of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(w\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s visualise this with a numerical example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# expected returns, standard deviation, and correlation of two assets
mu1 &amp;lt;- 0.2
mu2 &amp;lt;- 0.1
sigma1 &amp;lt;- 0.1
sigma2 &amp;lt;- 0.05
rho12 &amp;lt;- 0.25

# calculate return and risks based on w
cal_pf_return &amp;lt;- function(w){
  return(w*mu1 + (1-w)*mu2)
}
cal_pf_risk &amp;lt;- function(w){
  return(w^2*sigma1^2 + (1-w)^2*sigma2^2 + 2*w*(1-w)*rho12*sigma1*sigma2)
}

# weights span from -1 to 1; this considers short positions as well for illustration
weights &amp;lt;- seq(-1, 1, by = 0.01)

returns &amp;lt;- NULL
risks &amp;lt;- NULL

for(w in weights){
  returns &amp;lt;- c(returns, cal_pf_return(w))
  risks &amp;lt;- c(risks, cal_pf_risk(w))
}

plot(risks, returns,
     xlab = &amp;quot;Portfolio risk&amp;quot;,
     ylab = &amp;quot;Portfolio return&amp;quot;,
     main = &amp;quot;Risk-return relationship across weights&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2020-09-27-a-gentle-introduction-to-the-modern-portfolio-theory_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; style=&#34;display: block; margin: auto;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;efficient-portfolios&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Efficient Portfolios&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a look at the plot above. Notice that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For every possible value of return, there is one corresponding value of risk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;However, for every possible value of risk, there are two corresponding values of returns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, for a given amount of risk that we would like to take on, we would want a higher return than a lower one. Therefore, any combination of risk-return that belongs to the top half of the plot would be portfolios that we would want, as compared to the lower half. In particular, each combination in the top half of the plot are considered as &lt;strong&gt;efficient portfolios&lt;/strong&gt;. At this point, we might also want to know which is the portfolio or weight that has the lowest risks. This portfolio is also known as the &lt;strong&gt;minimum variance portfolio&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Terminology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Efficient portfolios&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; lie on on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Efficient_frontier&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;efficient frontier&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the top half of our plot. By definition, the efficient frontier consists of portfolios such that for each of these portfolios and their respective returns, there exists no other portfolios that carries a lower portfolio risk for a given return (hence “efficient”&lt;a href=&#34;#fn5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). The &lt;strong&gt;minimum variance portfolio&lt;/strong&gt; is one special case of an efficient portfolio - no other portfolios carries a lower portfolio risk than itself, and is the leftmost point of our plot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;min_risk_w &amp;lt;- weights[which(risks == min(risks))]
min_risk_return &amp;lt;- mean(cal_pf_return(min_risk_w))

efficient_idx &amp;lt;- which(returns &amp;gt;= min_risk_return)
inefficient_idx &amp;lt;- which(returns &amp;lt; min_risk_return)

plot(risks[efficient_idx], returns[efficient_idx],
     xlab = &amp;quot;Portfolio risk&amp;quot;,
     ylab = &amp;quot;Portfolio return&amp;quot;,
     main = &amp;quot;The Efficient Frontier&amp;quot;,
     ylim = c(0,0.2), xlim = c(0.002, 0.01))

lines(risks[inefficient_idx], returns[inefficient_idx], lty = &amp;quot;dotted&amp;quot;)

abline(h = min_risk_return)
text(x = 0.003, y = min_risk_return-0.01, &amp;quot;min variance portfolio&amp;quot;)
text(x = 0.006, y = 0.15, &amp;quot;efficient frontier&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2020-09-27-a-gentle-introduction-to-the-modern-portfolio-theory_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-2-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; style=&#34;display: block; margin: auto;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;minimum-variance-portfolio&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Minimum variance portfolio&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the example above, we arrived at the minimum variance portfolio by doing some simple calculations. A more robust method would be arrive at the minimum variance portfolio analytically by treating the problem as a optimization problem, minimizing &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(Var(R_{pf})\)&lt;/span&gt;. This can be done by simply solving some basic calculus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[
Var(R_{pf}) = w^2\sigma_1^2+ (1-w)^2\sigma_2^2 + 2w(1-w)\rho_{12}\sigma_1\sigma_2 \\
\frac{dVar(R_{pf})}{dw} = 2w\sigma_1^2 - 2(1-w)\sigma_2^2 + 2(1-2w)\rho_{12}\sigma_1\sigma_2 \\
\]&lt;/span&gt;
Also, since&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[
\frac{d^2Var(R_{pf})}{dw^2} = 2\sigma_1^2 + 2\sigma_2^2 - 4\rho_{12}\sigma_1\sigma_2
\geqslant 2\sigma_1^2 + 2\sigma_2^2 - 4\sigma_1\sigma_2 = 2(\sigma_1 - \sigma_2)^2 \geqslant 0 
\]&lt;/span&gt;
where &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\rho_{12} &amp;lt; 1\)&lt;/span&gt;. We would have &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\frac{d^2Var(R_{pf})}{dw^2} &amp;gt; 0\)&lt;/span&gt;, i.e. solving &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\frac{dVar(R_{pf})}{dw} = 0\)&lt;/span&gt; minimizes &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(Var(R_{pf})\)&lt;/span&gt;, giving the minimium variance portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solving,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[
w \equiv w_{minvar} = \frac{\sigma_2^2 - \rho_{12}\sigma_1\sigma_2}{\sigma_1^2 + \sigma_2^2 - 2\rho_{12}\sigma_1\sigma_2}
\]&lt;/span&gt;
and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[
1 - w_{minvar} = \frac{\sigma_1^2 - \rho_{12}\sigma_1\sigma_2}{\sigma_1^2 + \sigma_2^2 - 2\rho_{12}\sigma_1\sigma_2}
\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;risk-free-assets&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Risk-free assets&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let’s make this a little more interesting than just 2 assets. Since it’s always possible to not invest all our capital in these assets, and in fact leave a portion of capital in something that is &lt;strong&gt;risk-free&lt;/strong&gt;, such as cash, we could include risk-free assets as part of our framework as well. In particular, we could have &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(w_1 + w_2 &amp;lt; 1\)&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(1 - w_1 - w_2\)&lt;/span&gt; being the portion not invested, but instead diverted to risk-free assets. Doing this directly reduces portfolio variance, and of course reduces portfolio return.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Terminology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As pointed out above, &lt;strong&gt;risk-free assets&lt;/strong&gt; are simply assets that are generally deemed as 100% safe&lt;a href=&#34;#fn6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref6&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, such as cash in a deposit account&lt;a href=&#34;#fn7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref7&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Treasury Bills, or Singapore Savings Bonds. Typically, the three-month &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.treasury.gov/resource-center/data-chart-center/interest-rates/pages/textview.aspx?data=yield&#34;&gt;US Treasury Bills&lt;/a&gt; are used as proxies for risk-free assets, and their yield or return are considered accordingly. In context of Singapore, we could consider the yield of SSBs as risk-free returns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(R_{free}\)&lt;/span&gt; be the random variable representing the return of a risk-free asset. Then we have &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(ER_{free} = \mu_{free}\)&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(Var(R_{free}) = 0\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref8&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Naturally, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(ER_{free}\)&lt;/span&gt; would be small and contributes a small return to portfolio. On the other hand, directly adjusting the &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(1 - w_1 - w_2\)&lt;/span&gt; provides a convenient of controlling portfolio variance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, note that since &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(Var(R_{free}) = 0\)&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\forall i cov(R_{free}, R_i) = 0\)&lt;/span&gt;, i.e. the risk-free is not correlated with any other “risky” assets&lt;a href=&#34;#fn9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref9&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;one-risky-asset-and-one-risk-free-asset&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;One “risky” asset and one risk-free asset&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let’s consider combining a “risky” asset with a risk-free one. Let &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(w\)&lt;/span&gt; be the weight invested in the risky asset, with its return being &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(ER\)&lt;/span&gt; and variance being &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(Var(R)\)&lt;/span&gt;. The portfolio would look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[
ER_{pf} = wER + (1-w)R_{free} \implies \mu_{pf} = w\mu_R + (1-w)\mu_{free} \\
Var(R_{pf}) = w^2Var(R) \implies \sigma_{pf} = w\sigma_R
\]&lt;/span&gt;
In particular, observe that the portfolio variance is now a function of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(w\)&lt;/span&gt;, i.e. solving &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(Var(R_{pf}) = w^2Var(R)\)&lt;/span&gt; gives &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(w = \frac{\sigma_{pf}}{\sigma_R}\)&lt;/span&gt;, where &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\sigma_{pf}\)&lt;/span&gt; is the standard deviation of the portfolio and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\sigma_R\)&lt;/span&gt; is the standard deviation of the risky asset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This gives the following relationship between the portfolio return &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\mu_{pf}\)&lt;/span&gt; and variance &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\sigma_{pf}\)&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[
\mu_{pf} = \mu_{free} + \frac{\mu_R - \mu_{free}}{\sigma_R}\sigma_{pf}
\]&lt;/span&gt;
Again, let’s visualize this relationship with a numerical example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# expected returns of both &amp;quot;risky&amp;quot; and risk-free asset, variance
mu_R    &amp;lt;- 0.2
mu_free &amp;lt;- 0.04
sigma_R &amp;lt;- 0.1

# calculate return and risks based on w
cal_pf_return &amp;lt;- function(w){
  return(w*mu_R + (1-w)*mu_free)
}
cal_pf_sd &amp;lt;- function(w){ # standard deviation, not variance
  return(w*sigma_R)
}

weights &amp;lt;- seq(0, 1, by = 0.01)

returns &amp;lt;- NULL
risks &amp;lt;- NULL

for(w in weights){
  returns &amp;lt;- c(returns, cal_pf_return(w))
  risks &amp;lt;- c(risks, cal_pf_sd(w))
}

plot(risks, returns,
     xlab = &amp;quot;Portfolio sd&amp;quot;,
     ylab = &amp;quot;Portfolio return&amp;quot;,
     main = &amp;quot;Risk-return relationship across weights&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2020-09-27-a-gentle-introduction-to-the-modern-portfolio-theory_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; style=&#34;display: block; margin: auto;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;two-risky-assets-and-one-risk-free-asset&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Two “risky” assets and one risk-free asset&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s go one step further, and look at having two “risky” assets with one risk-free asset. What does the math look like? Again, Let &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(w_1\)&lt;/span&gt; be the weight invested in the first risky asset, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(w_2\)&lt;/span&gt; in the second risky asset and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(w_{free}\)&lt;/span&gt; in the risk-free asset, with respective returns being &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(ER_1\)&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(ER_2\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(ER_{free}\)&lt;/span&gt;, and variances being &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(Var(R_1)\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(Var(R_2)\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since there are now two risky assets, we also need to consider their correlation, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\rho_{12}\)&lt;/span&gt;. The portfolio would look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[
ER_{pf} = w_1ER_1 + w_2ER_2 + (1-w_1-w_2)R_{free} \implies \mu_{pf} = w_1\mu_{R_1} + w_2\mu_{R_2} + (1-w_1-w_2)\mu_{free} \\
Var(R_{pf}) = w_1^2Var(R_1) + w_2^2Var(R_2) + 2w_1w_2cov(R_1, R_2) = w_1^2\sigma_1^2 + w_2^2\sigma_2^2 + 2w_1w_2\rho_{12}\sigma_1\sigma_2 \\
w_{free} = 1-w_1-w_2
\]&lt;/span&gt;
In particular, note that we can write &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(ER_{pf}\)&lt;/span&gt; in the following manner as well:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[
ER_{pf} = (1-w_{free})(\bar{w_1}R_1 + \bar{w_2}R_2) + w_{free}R_{free} \\
\bar{w_1} = \frac{w_1}{1-w_{free}}, \bar{w_2} = \frac{w_2}{1-w_{free}} \implies \bar{w_1} + \bar{w_2} = 1
\]&lt;/span&gt;
In this sense, we can now view portfolio selection as a two-stage problem. First, we construct a portfolio based on risky assets only (e.g. chooosing &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\bar{w_1}\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\bar{w_2}\)&lt;/span&gt; only). Then, we include the risk-free asset by choosing &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(w_{free}\)&lt;/span&gt;. From the perspective, we gain an interesting tool in controlling for the risk we take on in our portfolio, by the inclusion of the risk-free asset - since its inclusion always decreases the portfolio risk, regardless of the risky assets we take on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also note that once the first stage is completed, we are effectively dealing with one risky asset and one risk-free asset again, with the “single risky asset” being a combination of 2 risky assets, with &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\bar{w_1}\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\bar{w_2}\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the scenario of using two risky assets and one risk-free asset simplifies that of using one risky asset and one risk-free asset! This results also generalises to &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; assets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;conclusion&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I have attempted to give a brief and hopefully gentle enough introduction to the Modern Portfolio Theory, using only statistics like mean, variance, and covariance. We looked at the math behind diversification, computed the Efficient Frontier, and generalised the problem from &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(N=2\)&lt;/span&gt; assets to &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(N&amp;gt;2\)&lt;/span&gt; assets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested to go a bit further, you might want to find out more about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://pgpfm.wordpress.com/tag/tangency-portfolio/&#34;&gt;Tangency Portfolio&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sharpe_ratio&#34;&gt;Sharpe Ratio&lt;/a&gt; - both further extends our analysis and this post would have given you sufficient understanding for further exploration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s all from me today, thank you for reading!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In my personal opinion, using standard deviation as a measure of risk is a little iffy, for several reasons. For example, risk could be better represented as a probability of huge losses, rather than the sd of expected returns - but let’s stick to this for now.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In particular, choosing &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(w\)&lt;/span&gt; = &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\frac{1}{2}\)&lt;/span&gt; minimizes &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(Var(R_{pf})\)&lt;/span&gt; at &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\frac{\sigma}{\sqrt{2}}\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s commonly said that stocks and bonds are considered to be negatively correlated. Assuming this is true, consider the two subdomains &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\rho_{12} &amp;lt; 0\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\rho_{12} &amp;gt; 0\)&lt;/span&gt;. We have &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\forall\rho_{12} &amp;lt; 0, Var(R_{pf}) &amp;lt; \frac{1}{2}\sigma^2\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\forall\rho_{12} &amp;gt; 0, Var(R_{pf}) &amp;gt; \frac{1}{2}\sigma^2\)&lt;/span&gt;, i.e. portfolio risk reduces when you have two negatively correlated assets in the portfolio - an intuitive result and justification for proper diversification and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/s/strategicassetallocation.asp&#34;&gt;strategic asset allocation&lt;/a&gt;. This of course begs the question on whether stocks and bonds are indeed negatively correlated, in good economic times and in bad, and correlated by how much. We can explore this topic deeper in the future. Also, the math here is similar to that of &lt;a href=&#34;https://thestatsguy.rbind.io/post/2018/12/25/why-ensemble-modelling-works-so-well-and-one-often-neglected-principle/&#34;&gt;ensemble modelling&lt;/a&gt; in machine learning.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course the challenge in real life is to estimate them using historical data.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn5&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The same way an estimator &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\hat{\theta}\)&lt;/span&gt; is &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Efficient_estimator&#34;&gt;efficient&lt;/a&gt; if &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(Var(\hat{\theta})\)&lt;/span&gt; is minimized.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn6&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course there is no such thing in real life.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn7&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Singapore, up to SGD75K is insured by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sdic.org.sg/&#34;&gt;SDIC&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn8&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;We could in fact use a constant instead of a random variable.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn9&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Again, this is not always true in real life. For example, we have a coronavirus pandemic decimating the return of both “risky” and risk-free assets.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Declining interest rates amidst Covid-19 - and a hidden star</title>
      <link>/post/2020/05/07/declining-interest-rates-amidst-covid-19-and-a-hidden-star/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020/05/07/declining-interest-rates-amidst-covid-19-and-a-hidden-star/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;As Covid-19 continues to wreck havoc in many countries around the world, including the US, massive sell-offs have taken place in Wall Street and other markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a move to protect the US economy from the effects of the pandemic, the US Federal Reserve has cut interest rates twice during March 2020 - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.channelnewsasia.com/news/business/in-an-emergency-move-us-federal-reserve-cuts-interest-rates-to-12496552&#34;&gt;first in early March&lt;/a&gt;, cutting rates by 50 basis points to a targeted range of 1% to 1.25%, then &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.straitstimes.com/business/economy/us-federal-reserve-cuts-interest-rates-to-near-zero-coordinates-with-other-central&#34;&gt;another cut in mid March&lt;/a&gt; to a targeted range of 0% to 0.25%. At the same time, a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cnbc.com/2020/03/15/federal-reserve-cuts-rates-to-zero-and-launches-massive-700-billion-quantitative-easing-program.html&#34;&gt;quantitative easing&lt;/a&gt; (QE) programme was also launched, entailing US$700 billion worth of asset purchases comprising US Treasury bonds and mortgage-backed securities, i.e. the Fed buys these securities from the market, and basically inject liquidity back into the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last time the Fed has taken steps similiar to this, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/07/31/business/economy/federal-reserve-interest-rate-cut.html&#34;&gt;was during the 08 Global Financial Crisis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;impact-on-singapore-and-ordinary-singaporeans&#34;&gt;Impact on Singapore and ordinary Singaporeans&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inevitably, interest rates in Singapore (SIBOR, SOR) have always been closely tied to US Fed rates, and hence these rates have been falling as well. For retail investors and lay Singaporeans like myself, there are several effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Falling mortgage rates - housing loans will be cheaper, and refinancing may be viable if it&amp;rsquo;s an option for you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.straitstimes.com/business/companies-markets/some-singapore-retail-investors-using-cheap-cash-to-load-up-on-stocks&#34;&gt;Or, you can even go on leverage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Local banks and the STI suffer - our favorite DBS, OCBC, and UOB will have their Net Interest Margin (NIM) decrease, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.businesstimes.com.sg/companies-markets/analysts-downgrade-singapore-banks-after-us-fed-rate-cut&#34;&gt;affecting their earnings&lt;/a&gt;. And with &lt;a href=&#34;https://sginvestors.io/market/sgx-share-price-performance/straits-times-index-constituents&#34;&gt;~35% of the STI&lt;/a&gt; is made up of these banks (at time of writing), the STI will drop as well. Of course the banks are not the only reason why the STI suffers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deposit account rates fall - likewise, our favorite DBS Multiplier, OCBC 360, UOB One, and the likes will see a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.straitstimes.com/business/banking/banks-here-cut-deposit-rates-in-line-with-global-markets&#34;&gt;cut in interest rates&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Singapore Government Securities rates fall - additionally, SGS bonds and SSBs will also see a decrease in yield.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-three-main-cash-stashes-uob-one-singapore-savings-bond-and-cimb-fastsaver&#34;&gt;My three main cash stashes: UOB One, Singapore Savings Bond, and CIMB FastSaver&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;uob-one&#34;&gt;UOB One&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uob.com.sg/personal/save/chequeing/one-account.page&#34;&gt;UOB One&lt;/a&gt; has been my workhorse account for salary crediting, GIRO, credit card spend etc for several months now. The effective rate of the UOB One for 75K used to be 2.436%, if you meet the bonus interest requirements. Effective 1st May 2020, here is what it looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/thestatsguy/thestatsguy/master/public/images/2020-05-07%20uob%20one.png&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
Bonus interest structure for the UOB One account, effective 1st May 2020.
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The effective interest rates is now 1.796% for 75K. On the upside, UOB has retained the existing qualifying criteria so that there are no disruptions to our savings routine. Other deposit accounts have also cut their interest rates accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;singapore-savings-bond&#34;&gt;Singapore Savings Bond&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/thestatsguy/thestatsguy/master/public/images/2020-05-07%20BT%205th%20May%202020%20SSB%20FD%20mortgage%20rates%201.PNG&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
Article from The Business Times 5th May 2020.
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SSB rates have fallen significantly over the past months, since early 2019. The June 2020 issue of SSB has a first year yield of 0.57% (10-year yield average of 1.05%) - the lowest it has ever been since the launch of SSBs in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://investmentmoats.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/20200506-Singapore-Savings-Bond-1.png&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
SSB first year and 10-year yields. &lt;a href=&#34;https://investmentmoats.com/saving-and-investing-my-money/singapore-savings-bonds-ssb-june-2020/&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, SSBs are issued and guaranteed by the Singapore government. Nonetheless, the current state of SSBs, with a first year yield of 0.57% and 10-year average of 1.05%, is a shadow of its former self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;cimb-fastsaver-the-hidden-star&#34;&gt;CIMB FastSaver - the hidden star&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cimbbank.com.sg/en/personal/products/accounts/savings-accounts/cimb-fastsaver-account.html&#34;&gt;CIMB FastSaver&lt;/a&gt; is my third cash stash. Unlike the typical high-interest workhorse accounts like DBS Multiplier or OCBC 360, the CIMB FastSaver does not have any special requirements of salary crediting, credit card spend, bill payments etc in order to be granted an interest rate of 1% (for first 50K). Considering there is no special requirements, 1% is definitely on the high side, especially in comparison to SSB and current FD rates:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/thestatsguy/thestatsguy/master/public/images/2020-05-07%20BT%205th%20May%202020%20SSB%20FD%20mortgage%20rates%202.PNG&#34; width=&#34;60%&#34;&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
Article from The Business Times 5th May 2020.
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compare that with the CIMB FastSaver interest rates, as a deposit account:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/thestatsguy/thestatsguy/master/public/images/2020-05-07%20cimb%20fastsaver.PNG&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
CIMB FastSaver interest structure.
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of the time of writing this, there doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to be any indications from CIMB to adjust the interest rate of the FastSaver account. I sure hope I didn&amp;rsquo;t jinxed it and it stays this way! Instead of buying any more SSBs, I will place spilled over cash from my UOB One into CIMB FastSaver for now - but I guess I won&amp;rsquo;t be surprised if there is going to be an adjustment to the CIMB FastSaver rates, putting out the light from the hidden star.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical methods in finance series</title>
      <link>/post/2020/03/19/statistical-methods-in-finance-series/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020/03/19/statistical-methods-in-finance-series/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://miro.medium.com/max/1280/1*LZnClq6o0kEU88-BZnkvCw.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a sleepless night, so I decided to write a little. This will be the first part of a series that I would like to write about, circling around the use of statistical methods in finance. Most of the content that I will be exploring would originate from one of my NUS M.Sc Statistics modules, Advanced Statistical Methods in Finance. I was taught by Prof Xia Yingcun when I did this module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of all the modules that I did during my M.Sc, I always found this one to resonate with me the most - guess that&amp;rsquo;s mainly because I like topic, as well as of the fact that I was heavily experimenting with investing on my own during that time. I also found that using finance as the backdrop or context to study certain statistical concepts, such as copula or factor analysis, to be more engaging than perhaps studying these topics in vaccum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;statistical-methods-in-finance&#34;&gt;Statistical methods in finance&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of statistical methods that can be directly mapped to their applications in finance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Statistical distributions: Value-at-Risk (VaR)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Linear regression: Capital Asset Pricing Model (CAPM)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Factor analysis: Arbitrage Pricing Theory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logit/probit models: credit scoring/rating&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Time series analysis: price forecast, volatility modelling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nonlinear regression: term structures of interest rates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Monte-Carlo simulations: pricing of assets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Copulae: tail dependence of asset prices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Estimation of covariance matrix and optimization: Markowitz&amp;rsquo;s portfolio theory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and many more&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this series, I would like to tackle some of these topics, by combining statistical theory, finance theory, and the use of R where relevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;broader-question-can-statistics-be-used-to-make-a-profit&#34;&gt;Broader question: can statistics be used to make a profit?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since there are folks who decided to spend the time and energy to study the application of statistical methods in capital markets, surely it&amp;rsquo;s a worthwhile effort and making money is possible? Well, yes and no. It&amp;rsquo;s well known in statistical finance is that financial data has extremely low signal-to-noise (SNR) ratio. This means that for a model that predicts price, even if the model is correctly specified, due to the low SNR, it&amp;rsquo;s unlikely for the predictions to be useful. Most folks would hence consider the study of price volatility to be more important than price itself. If we are able to have an informed point of view about future volatility (perhaps due to the fact that volatility autocorrelation is strong =&amp;gt; volatility may be predicted in a GARCH/ARCH model), we would be able to act accordingly. We will talk about this along the way in this series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;stylized-fact-in-statistical-finance&#34;&gt;Stylized fact in statistical finance&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I previously (well, a year ago) wrote about &lt;a href=&#34;https://thestatsguy.rbind.io/post/2019/04/04/short-stylized-facts-in-statistical-finance/&#34;&gt;stylized facts&lt;/a&gt; in statistical finance, where I briefly listed without explanations various &amp;ldquo;facts&amp;rdquo;. Stylized facts are commonly used in statistical finance to address and summarize phenomenon directly observed from historical data, and explainable with a certain level of theoretical consistency and logic. There are a number of well-known ones, such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Financial data has extremely low signal-to-noise ratio.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Price changes are less volatile in bull markets and more volatile bear markets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Volatility clustering is typically observed in financial data; that is, large changes tend to be followed by large changes of either sign, and small changes tend to be followed by small changes of either sign.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and others&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this series, we will necessarily also delve a little deeper into some of these stylized facts, by considering both empirical (historical data) and theoretical perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it for a brief introduction to series - looking forward to do deep dives into various topics!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fundamental Analysis 101: A basic overview of the fundamental analysis of stocks</title>
      <link>/post/2019/06/08/fundamental-analysis-101-a-basic-overview-of-the-fundamental-analysis-of-stocks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019/06/08/fundamental-analysis-101-a-basic-overview-of-the-fundamental-analysis-of-stocks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://frugalinvesting.files.wordpress.com/2018/07/market-analysis-1024x682.jpg?w=900&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I would like to give an overview of the principles and concepts in the fundamental analysis of stocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What is fundamental analysis?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, fundamental analysis (FA) is the analysis of the fundamentals of a company. The fundamentals of the company are trying to capture essentially the health of the company, in the present and future. The objective of FA is to discern a point of view on the current and future prospects of a company – the actionability from this point of view is of course whether to buy (or short-sell) the stock. If our FA suggests that the company is likely to perform well in the future, we would like a piece of the action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this sense, there is an inherent notion of valuation – based on our view of the stock, we could, for example, conclude that the stock is currently under-valued and is likely to grow to at least a fair valuation. Therefore, we buy. Nonetheless, we don’t know when our under-valued stock would grow to our fair valuation. It could take days, months or years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The efficient market hypothesis, technical analysis, and fundamental analysis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any current under- or over-valuation of a stock implies that the market is not valuing the stock “correctly”, and is hence inefficient. One of the dominant criticisms against FA is the efficient market hypothesis (EMH). EMH states that at any point in time, the market is efficient and security prices are exactly where they should be – every security is valued correctly, taking into account all aspects of the security and the company. For example, the resultant price plunge from a JNJ lawsuit or a Boeing plane crash is exactly reflective of the inherent value of JNJ or Boeing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corollary to the EMH is as follows – it would be impossible to derive any form of “correct” valuation or insights based on e.g. the fundamentals of JNJ or Boeing, no matter how we analyse the fundamentals. Research has shown that the strong condition of the EMH is largely true (reference), and there are occasions where inefficiencies occur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, proponents of technical analysis (TA) argue that price movements are driven by signals in the historical prices themselves. TA relies on e.g. trading on momentum of the stock, and similar to the EMH, suggests that the JNJ lawsuit or Boeing plane crash has already been priced into the stock, and stock prices constantly moves to capture these news and signals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on my current understanding on securities and prices, FA makes sense to me. As someone with scientific and statistical background, it is challenging for me to convince myself that TA is not some variant of data dredging or confirmation bias. But of course, you can always take what you will and maintain healthy skepticism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The objective of fundamental analysis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we mentioned above, the objective of FA is to discern a point of view on the current and future prospects of a company. The actionability from this point of view is of course whether to buy (or short-sell) the stock. More specifically, what are we interested in from an exercise of FA is to answer questions such as the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is the company actually making money?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Can the company continue to make money?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Can the company beat its competition in time to come?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is the company is able to fulfil its debt obligations?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As simple as they are crafted, these questions are difficult to tackle and sometimes give ambiguous answers, leaving the analyst to provide a subjective opinion. Personally, this is one reason why FA appeals to me – the fact that the same set of numbers can lead to different analysis and stories meant that there’s more to the performance of a company than financials, much like data scientists would use data to tell a story and derive insights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The ancient dichotomy – Quantitative and qualitative fundamentals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no need to further elaborate the difference between quantitative and qualitative fundamentals. While revenue, sales, and costs can be objectively measured, notions like brand loyalty, intellectual product, and management competence are hard to place a price tag on. Following table illustrates examples what we would like to look for in both aspects of FA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&#34;wp-block-table&#34;&gt;&lt;table class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example quantitative factors&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example qualitative factors&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;Balance sheet&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;    Assets&lt;br&gt;    Liabilities&lt;br&gt;    Equity&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Income statement&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;    Revenue&lt;br&gt;    Cost of goods sold&lt;br&gt;    Selling, general and admin expenses&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Cash flow statement&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;    Operations&lt;br&gt;    Financing&lt;br&gt;    Investing &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Business model&lt;br&gt;Industry outlook&lt;br&gt;Competitive landscape&lt;br&gt;Regulation&lt;br&gt;Management competence&lt;br&gt;Governance    &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look at each of them, starting from the qualitative factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Qualitative factors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Business model&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What exactly does a company do? The nature of a company’s business can vary from simplistic to downright complex and opaque. Something like McDonalds is not difficult to look at, while it is challenging to comprehensively evaluate Amazon or Google. The whole idea of understanding a company’s business model is consider whether its profits are sustainable in the short and long term, or a fluke. In addition, in this digital era, is the company and industry that we are looking at prone to disruption (think Kodak), or are the barriers to entry significant? It’s wiser and much easier to invest with a piece of mind on companies that we understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Industry outlook&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, is the industry a weary and inefficient one, or something that investment dollars are pouring into? Is it on the fringe of disruption or well-protected? Is the industry growing or shrinking?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Competitive landscape&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do the competitors in the same space match up? What is their respective market share? Is it a duopoly like Boeing and Airbus, or are there plenty of strong players? Are there any up and coming small players that could disrupt? Or are there any external, non-traditional players looking to enter the market? Are the R&amp;amp;D initiatives bearing fruits that can shake things up? Or are customers simply to loyal to certain brands for anything to change at all? Knowing the competitive landscape helps in making that informed decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Regulation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industries that are heavily regulated by authorities typically spend significant amounts of money lobbying, or have to be reactive to policy changes. Something like Medicare for all would make a dent on the bottomlines of healthcare companies.  Therefore, understanding the relationship between the company and the government helps in making an informed forecast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Management competence&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A solid business model won’t fly if the management is incompetent, leading to poor execution. For a retail investor, there is no truly good or robust way to assessing management competence. We would be able to fling a few million dollars around and demand attendance from the C-suite. The best would be to rely on Wall Street analyst opinions as well as to attend quarterly earnings calls with the CEO and/or CFO and judge for yourself. Are they open to tough line of questioning or are they dodging, spinning, or giving non-answers? We could also consider their historical records. In all, not easy to judge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Governance&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, checks and balances are required to ensure that a company is compliant with laws and regulations. Financial transparency allows shareholders and investors information that they should rightly have access to. Conflicts of interest in management structure should be nonexistent and shareholders’ rights and interests should be upheld and represented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Quantitative factors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quantitative fundamentals of a company can all be found in its financial statements, which are quarterly, semi-annually or annually compiled and published. There are three major financial statements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Balance sheet&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Income statement&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cash flow statement&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we elaborate on each of these, note that these statements and other variants are filed and published with the respective bourses. For stocks listed on the SGX, annual reports and related documents can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://www2.sgx.com/securities/annual-reports-related-documents&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. On the other hand, stocks listed in the US following &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sec.gov/&#34;&gt;SEC&lt;/a&gt; regulations and periodically file reports known as 10-K and 10-Q. The 10-K is an annual filing that publishes the company&#39;s performance over the previous fiscal year. It consists of the balance sheet, income statement, cash flow statement, as well as other types of information, including that of operations, future plans, headwinds, etc. The 10-Q,&amp;nbsp; on the other hand, is the quarterly version of the 10-K, and is not audited, unlike the 10-K. There would typically be three 10-Q filings and one 10-K filing in a year, and they are vital sources of information and research for any serious stock picker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Balance sheet&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The balance sheet is a record of the company’s assets, liabilities, and equities at a given point in time. Assets are the all resources in the company, inclusive of free cash, inventory, real estate, machinery etc. The relationship between assets, liabilities, and equities are given in the fundamental accounting equation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assets = Liabilities + Shareholders’ equity&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The right hand side of the equation represents the way in which these assets are financed, either by debt, i.e. liabilities, or by equity, i.e. all the value that has been contributed to the company by shareholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The balance sheet is essentially a snapshot of the company at point in time, like an X-ray or MRI. While important, investors oftentimes overlook the balance sheet as revenue or earnings, which require a notion of time elapsed e.g. quarterly earnings, are not found in the balance sheet. On the other hand, the balance sheet informs investors about the amount of debt that the company has, how much cash and cash-like assets it possesses and so on – like how we take a blood test to look at various biomarkers like blood glucose or red blood cell count.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two categories of assets – current and non-current assets. Current assets are largely liquid, perhaps with a latency of up to 12 months or less. Examples of current assets include cash, inventories, and account receivables, of course with cash being the most liquid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically, we can think of large amounts of free cash in a company as being an attractive investment. Simply put, there is an option value in cash for companies to grow in strategic directions, or provide some cushion during tough times – the proverbial “saving for the rainy day”. Another way to think about free cash is that the company is so caught up in earning money that its management has yet to figure a way to put the free cash into good use. Yet another way to see this is that its management is not far-sighted enough to know how to invest the cash. You can see that a small stockpile of cash can be argued accordingly in both ways as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inventories are goods that yet to be sold, while account receivables are outstanding payments due to the company by its customers. Inventories can be thought of as “held up” revenue, in that the goods have already been produced, but no revenue comes in because they are not sold yet. Like free cash, inventory levels can be analyzed accordingly. For example, inventory turnover (sales / average inventory) indicates how fast goods are moving through the system to customers. We would want inventories to remain at a steady level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Account receivables are credit issued to customers for their purchases. This allows the company to book top-line revenue and stimulate sales. Inevitably, too long of a credit is bad for the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Non-current assets are essentially assets that cannot be liquidated in a jiffy – these includes real estate, factories etc. Even though non-current assets are counted in the balance sheet as assets, in reality they are not exactly resources that the company can rally in times of difficulty for any quick maneuvers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liabilities are essentially debt, and can also be categorized under current liabilities and non-current liabilities, with the time horizon of current liabilities being say a year or less. For example, when a company issues a corporate bond of 10 years in tenure, this would be a non-current liability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Debt is critical for a company to succeed, when it manages to leverage appropriately. Of course, too much debt is unhealthy. The quick ratio, (current assets - inventories) / current liabilities, is a quick indicator – a quick ratio of more than 1 implies that short term debt obligations can be taken care of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equity is the difference between assets and liabilities, represents what the shareholders own in the company. There are two key items in equity, namely the paid-in capital and retained earnings. Paid-in capital is the amount of money shareholders paid in the first place during public offering to own a share in the company. Retained earnings represent all the earnings made by the company, that instead of being paid out as dividend to shareholders, are retained to further the growth and operations of the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Income statement&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The income statement is a little less boring than the balance sheet, because it directly shows the revenue numbers of the company over a period of time. Numbers like revenue, earnings, earnings per share (EPS) illustrates the performance of the company. Revenue, specifically revenue growth is often a strong investing signal as it can show potential of the company and the market as well as the company’s positioning in the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get from revenue to earnings, we need to consider expenses. There are typically two key types of expenses, namely cost of goods sold (COGS) and selling, general, and administrative expenses (SG&amp;amp;A) – both are rather self-explanatory. With these, we can then get to gross margin (net sales – COGS) and operating income (gross income – operating expenses, i.e. excluding expenses related to e.g. taxes and interest).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Cash flow statement&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the cash flow statement sounds similar to the income statement, they are very different beasts for a simple reason – while the income statement captures revenue and expense transaction, if there’s no actual cash flow, no records will be made on the cash flow statement. This manner of recording in the income statement is known as accrual accounting. Cash flow records in the cash flow statement could come from operations, financing, and investing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we discussed previously, cash is an important component in the health of the company. Cash means flexibility and agility. One of the key considerations in looking at a company’s cash flow statement is to assess its ability to generate free cash flow, or FCF. Think of it as all our monthly expenses being accounted for from our salary – the rest is free for us to save, invest, or spend on a little indulgence. The same logic applies to a company. A company with plenty of FCF can embark on various ways to make use of the cash, perhaps in R&amp;amp;D or paying some of them back to shareholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A closely related topic in cash flow, or specifically, discounted cash flow, is that of valuation, which I would like to touch on more in-depth in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summing up, another key topic in fundamental analysis is the use of valuation ratio, such as earnings per share, or EPS, or price-to-earnings or P/E ratio, to evaluate and summarize a company – another topic that justifies a separate in-depth exploration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s all for now! Hope you have gained something from this brief introduction. Thanks for reading 😊&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Medtech 101: An overview of the medical device industry</title>
      <link>/post/2019/05/27/medtech-101-an-overview-of-the-medical-device-industry/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019/05/27/medtech-101-an-overview-of-the-medical-device-industry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.medtecheurope.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/shutterstock_691546471-1049x590.jpg&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this post, I will be doing a 101 dissection of the medical device industry. It’s a somewhat not-so-popular industry from the perspective of retail investing, but I have had some prior experience in this space, so it’s a tad easier for me to conduct some levels of analysis on companies in this space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I will work through the following pointers in this piece,
and hopefully at the end of it, allow the reader to have some level of appreciation
for the industry as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:list --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Introduction to the medical device industry&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The medical devices themselves&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Key features of the industry&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Being a retail investor in this space&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:list --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unless otherwise stated, all facts and information are obtained from my desktop research from BMI Research and Fitch Solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Introduction to the medical device industry&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Medical devices refer to a variety of mostly hardware instruments used in the diagnosis, treatment or prevention of a multitude of diseases. These instruments range from surgical gloves and masks, to advanced devices like drug-eluting stents (DES). Technologically simple products are competed in the market via price and volume, just like any other household or everyday products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.mddionline.com/sites/default/files/images/Boston-Sci-Synergy-Stent.jpg&#34; width=&#34;60%&#34;&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
Boston Scientific Synery Drug Eluting Stent system. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mddionline.com/boston-scis-synergy-stent-worth-price&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What we are more interested in is the opposite end of this spectrum. Products like DES or other implantable medical devices (IMD) are technologically advanced and provide differentiated ways in treating complex diseases like heart arrhythmia and chronic arthritis. They are costly devices and are rarely paid for by individual patients – that is, their usage is co-paid or reimbursed by insurers or government healthcare schemes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By definition, a medical device is different from a drug in that the successful use of the device is not dependent on the absorption or metabolism of the device. In this sense, a wheelchair is a medical device in the same way as a pacemaker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading {&#34;level&#34;:3} --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;The industry at a glance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following table illustrates the size of the medical device industry (Source: Fitch Solutions, &lt;a href=&#34;https://store.fitchsolutions.com/global-medical-devices-report&#34;&gt;Global Medical Devices Report Q2 2019&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:table --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;wp-block-table&#34;&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;
  &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2018   &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2019 forecast   &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2020 forecast   &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2021 forecast   &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Total sales USDmn   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;387,393.61   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;408,173.28   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;
  434,477.48
  &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;461,548.71   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Totals sales %y/y   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;7.6   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;5.4   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;6.4   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;6.2   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Total sales 5-yr CAGR   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;5.9   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;6.0   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;5.8   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;5.7   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Totals sales per capita USD   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;61.6   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;64.3   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;67.9   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;71.6   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:table --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following is an infographic published by Technavio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.technavio.com/image/medical%20device%20market.jpg&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
Technavio Global Medical Devices Report 2018-2022. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.technavio.com/report/global-medical-devices-market-analysis-share-2018&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to both the Fitch Solutions Global Medical Devices Report Q2 2019 as well as the Technavio Global Medical Devices Report 2018 -2022, the industry is forecasted to grow at a CAGR of about 5% or more, up to a forecasted market size of 460 billion by 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading {&#34;level&#34;:3} --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;The US Market&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The US is both a dominant player and consumer in the medical device industry. On top of having the world’s highest health spending as percentage GDP and per capita, the US medical device market accounts for over 40% of the global market and has the world’s highest per capita medical device expenditure. The US is also home to many of the world’s largest medical device companies. The following table illustrates the top 12 players in the industry, which is dominated by the Americans. Most of these companies have a presence in California, Massachusetts, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.medicaldesignandoutsourcing.com/minnesota-2-0-major-u-s-medical-device-cluster/&#34;&gt;Minnesota (the so-called “Medical Alley”)&lt;/a&gt; (Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mpo-mag.com/issues/2018-07-01/view_features/the-2018-top-30-global-medical-device-companies&#34;&gt;Medical Product Outsourcing 2018 Top 30 Global Medical Device Companies&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:table --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;wp-block-table&#34;&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rank   &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Company   &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Country   &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Medical device revenue USDbn   &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Market cap USDbn   &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Price-to-Sales   &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ticker symbol   &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;1   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Medtronic   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;US   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;29.7   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;125   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;4.21   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;MDT   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;2   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;US   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;26.6   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;369*   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-*   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;JNJ   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;3   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;GE Healthcare   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;US   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;19.1   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;82.4   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;4.31   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;GE**   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;4   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Royal Philips   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;The Netherlands   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;16.3   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;37.5   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;2.30   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;PHIA   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;5   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Siemens Healthineers   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Germany   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;16.3   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;40.4   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;2.48   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;SHL   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;6   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Abbott Laboratories   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;US   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;16.2   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;136   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;8.40   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;ABT   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;7   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Cardinal Health   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;US   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;13.5   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;13.7   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.01   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;CAH   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;8   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Stryker   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;US   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;12.4   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;69.1   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;5.57   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;SYK   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;9   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Becton Dickinson   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;US   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;12.1   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;63.4   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;5.24   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;BDX   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;10   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Baxter   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;US   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;10.6   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;38.4   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;3.62   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;BAX   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;11   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Boston Scientific   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;US   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;9.0   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;53.5   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;5.94   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;BSX   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;12   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Essilor   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;France   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;9.0   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;52.0   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;5.78   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;EL   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:table --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson’s businesses extend well beyond that of medical devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;** GE Healthcare remains to be a healthcare unit within GE. While &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cnbc.com/2018/12/19/ge-reportedly-confidentially-files-for-ipo-of-health-care-unit.html&#34;&gt;GE has filed for IPO to spin off GE Healthcare&lt;/a&gt; during December 2018, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cnbc.com/2019/02/25/ge-withdraws-plans-for-healthcare-ipo-after-danaher-deal-bloomberg.html&#34;&gt;a 2019 IPO “looks unlikely after Danaher deal”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;The medical devices themselves&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading {&#34;level&#34;:3} --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Classification of devices&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the US, the primary regulatory body that governs the entire medical device industry is the Food and Drug Administration, or FDA. By FDA standards, medical devices are classified into three classes, namely Class I, II and III. A device falls into one of these classes by virtue of their risk level to patient, Class III being the riskiest. The following table illustrates examples of these classes. Most if not all major countries follow similar standards, e.g. Class I to IV in Japan, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hsa.gov.sg/content/hsa/en/Health_Products_Regulation/Consumer_Information/Consumer_Guides/Medical_Devices.html&#34;&gt;Class A to D in Singapore&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:table --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;wp-block-table&#34;&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;
  &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Level of risk   &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Examples   &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Class I   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Low   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Surgical gloves, scalpers, wheelchairs   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Class II   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Moderate   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Powered wheelchairs, infusion pumps, surgical drapes   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Class III   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;High   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Heart valves, silicone breast implants, stents and balloons   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:table --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading {&#34;level&#34;:3} --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Segmentation by device type and diseases&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Medical device companies typically tackle conditions in the following areas of specialty, like this example from &lt;a href=&#34;https://global.medtronic.com/xg-en/patients/conditions.html&#34;&gt;Medtronic&lt;/a&gt;, with example conditions in each of them. Going into each specialty would be too much here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:table --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;wp-block-table&#34;&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;
  &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example condition   &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Device/therapy   &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Airway and lungs   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Pulmonary valve disease   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Transcatheter pulmonary valve (TPV) Therapy   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Brain   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Epilepsy&amp;nbsp;   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Deep brain simulation   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Diabetes   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type 2 diabetes   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Continuous glucose monitoring (CGM)   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Digestive and gastrointestinal   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Crohn’s Disease   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Disease visualization   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Ear, Nose, Throat (ENT)   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Thyriod conditions   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Minimally invasive video-assisted   thyroidectomy   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Heart and Vascular   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Bradycardia, Tachycardia   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Pacemakers   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Pain Management   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Chronic pain   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Spinal cord stimulation   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Spine and Orthopedic   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Cervical herniated discs   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Cervical disc replacement   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Urinary   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Overactive bladder   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Bladder control therapy   &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:table --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Key features of the industry&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:list --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The role of regulatory bodies&lt;/em&gt;. The FDA in the US plays a key role in regulating the medical device industry. For starters, in order for companies to market their devices, these devices must go through one of two FDA approval processes, namely the pre-market approval (PMA) or the pre-market notifications (510k), where the latter is less stringent than the former. Most devices go through the 510k process (3-6 months), while more advanced or novel devices go through the PMA process (~ 270 days) (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.medpac.gov/docs/default-source/reports/jun17_ch7.pdf&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;). The FDA is also continuously involved in the post-market surveillance of devices, by reviewing studies done be researchers or the companies themselves to evaluate device effectiveness and efficacies. If required, the FDA issues product recalls to stop all device marketing and usage in the market.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Low price transparency&lt;/em&gt;. While list prices of products are typically known, due to the complexity of reimbursements on a procedure (rather than a device) basis, patients often have next to zero inkling on how much their devices truly cost. Likewise, physicians, hospitals, and e.g. Medicare all have limited knowledge on actual device transaction price. Only the medical device companies know how much they are selling these devices for. Talk about corporate capitalism.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Relationship between medical devices companies and physicians&lt;/em&gt;. Medical devices companies have often developed deep ties with physicians (not hospitals) themselves, in a setting where physicians often make purchasing decisions on devices, e.g. preferring an equivalent product from one company to another, due to e.g. familiarity or inertia to change. There are other ways in which these companies interact directly with physicians (FDA) (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.medpac.gov/docs/default-source/reports/jun17_ch7.pdf&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;). These includes:&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;royalty payments to physicians who help develop medical devices;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;consulting fees to physicians for providing feedback about the performance and design of a company’s devices;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;funding for physicians to conduct research;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;funding for medical education activities; and,&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;for physicians who use IMDs, regular interactions with the manufacturer’s sales representatives, who are often present at the physician’s invitation in the operating room during procedures and may help the physician make a final decision about which devices to use.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;High barrier of entry even amongst the tech giants&lt;/em&gt;. While the likes of Google Health, Apple Watch, or &lt;a href=&#34;https://thenextweb.com/artificial-intelligence/2018/10/15/amazons-new-patent-will-allow-alexa-to-detect-your-illness/&#34;&gt;Alexa detecting a cold or cough&lt;/a&gt; have attempted to break into the healthcare space, success in developing and marketing medical devices requires significant scientific expertise and market knowledge. Combine that with navigating the red tape and bureaucracy, something like Netflix producing and distributing films probably won’t happen for quite some time.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Big eat small&lt;/em&gt;. Start-up companies that develop promising new products are often acquired by one of the large medical devices companies. These acquisitions are beneficial to both sides of the equation: small companies can find it challenging to market their products, while major device companies have established distribution networks and relationships with hospitals and other providers. Large companies can also provide additional resources to further develop and improve new medical devices. An acquisition also allows the venture capital firms that supported the start-up company to withdraw their funding and realize a profit. For the large companies, acquisitions provide another way to conduct research and development and can either complement or substitute for the company’s internal efforts. Large companies can also use acquisitions to branch out into new therapeutic areas or bolster existing product lines (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.medpac.gov/docs/default-source/reports/jun17_ch7.pdf&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:list --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Being a retail investor in the medical device industry&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Short of being an entrepreneur, a private equity, a venture capital or even a medical researcher, investing in the medical device industry would mean investing in stocks or investing in index ETFs. Suppose due diligence is done and fundamental analysis validates that a company is suitably priced in the market. It would be reasonable then to approach stock picking in this industry based on events such as the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:list --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Research breakthroughs, new product launch, acquisition of new, non-cannibalizing technology&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Lawsuits, FDA product recalls, ethical scandals&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:list --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Being aware of who’s who in specific areas is critical in assessing changes in the competitive landscape. For example, Boston Scientific continues to dominate in the left atrial appendage closure (LAAC) market with Watchman, while Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson has fallen from grace in the DES market, giving up space to Abbott Labs, Boston Scientific, and Medtronic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, the best bet on the space as a lay retail investor is probably the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ishares.com/us/products/239516/ishares-us-medical-devices-etf&#34;&gt;iShares US Medical Devices ETF&lt;/a&gt; (IHI), listed on NYSE. IHI tracks the Dow Jones U.S. Select Medical Equipment Index, with its current top holdings including Abbott Labs, Medtronic, and Strkyer. At an expense ratio of 43 basis points, it’s a fairly reasonable ETF to hold on to for broad medical device exposure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s all for this 101! Hope you have gained a little something from it. Thank you for reading :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>REITs 101: Introduction to real estate investment trusts</title>
      <link>/post/2019/05/20/reits-101-introduction-to-real-estate-investment-trusts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019/05/20/reits-101-introduction-to-real-estate-investment-trusts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.etsystatic.com/6111470/r/il/35f144/1417264877/il_fullxfull.1417264877_awhp.jpg&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This post is a 101 dissection of real estate investment trusts, REITs or Reits in short. As the full content of this topic is pretty long and I will try to make this 101 comprehensive, touching on the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:list {&#34;ordered&#34;:true} --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;What are Reits&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;What makes Reits different from other investment vehicles&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Why invest in Reits&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;What are the different types of Reits&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;How to evaluate a Reit&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:list --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As you can see, there&amp;rsquo;s plenty to talk about even in a 101 piece, so let&amp;rsquo;s get straight to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;1. What are Reits?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reits, by virtue of their long form name, are essentially instruments that allow investors to get exposure to the real estate market, be it locally, regionally, or globally. The easiest way to give an explanation of what is a Reit is to take on the perspective of the Reit manager. As the Reit manager, to start an investment trust on real estate, you would first need to secure financing from, say a bank, to finance your portfolio of properties. That&amp;rsquo;s one portion of the financing. The other portion comes from listing the Reit in an exchange through an IPO, and get investors to invest in your Reit as a unitholder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From there, your entire portfolio of properties are financed from these two parties and your Reit is established. Afterwhich, you would do whatever that is required to rent these properties out on a lease, and start to collect rental income.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading {&#34;level&#34;:3} --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Reits as a passive income stream&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And here&amp;rsquo;s where plenty of retails investors, especially those in Singapore, have came to love Reits - Reits are obligated to pay out a minimum of 90% of its income as distributions (i.e. dividends) to enjoy tax exemptions. Suffice to say that the math works out for the Reit manager to indeed to pay at least 90%. This obligation is often viewed favorably by investors as a means to achieve consistent passive income stream - it has been suggested that Reits can be used as a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.todayonline.com/singapore/choosing-steady-retirement-income&#34;&gt;supplement or even alternative to a retiree&amp;rsquo;s annuity&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading {&#34;level&#34;:3} --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;The different parties within a Reit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following illustrates clearly how each party in a Reit interacts with another. Let&amp;rsquo;s take a brief look at each of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src= &#34;https://www.moneysense.gov.sg/-/media/moneysense/images/content-graphics-infographics/a-typical-reit-structure.jpg?la=en&amp;amp;hash=C618E33305CB50C523C8A226DB39D2684F532A1A&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
A typical Reit structure. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.moneysense.gov.sg/articles/2018/10/understanding-real-estate-investment-trusts-reits&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:list --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The Trustee: the trustee, as the name suggests, is responsible for the holding of the Reit units for investors. The trustee may also ensure compliance on the Reit on behalf of unitholders, and in gist, act in all manners in the interest of unitholders.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The Reit manager: the Reit manager is the one or the team that manages the strategic oversight of the Reit and its investment strategies. A Reit manager, may for instance, decide to expand out of Singapore real estate and venture into say, the Australian market.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The Property manager: on the other hand, the property manager is in charge of the actual management of the properties, e.g. running marketing campaigns or strategizing to maximise rental income.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The Sponsor: the sponsor is basically the &amp;ldquo;big boss&amp;rdquo; in the Reit. They are usually big developers like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.capitaland.com/sg/en.html&#34;&gt;CapitaLand&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mapletree.com.sg/&#34;&gt;Mapletree&lt;/a&gt;. They may be the ones who initially developed the properties and assets in the Reit. A sponsor, especially a larger one, would typically run and manage several Reits at once with different Reit manager teams - e.g. CapitaLand with &lt;a href=&#34;https://sg.finance.yahoo.com/quote/c38u.si&#34;&gt;CapitaLand Mall Trust&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://sg.finance.yahoo.com/quote/C61U.SI&#34;&gt;CapitaLand Commercial Trust&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://sg.finance.yahoo.com/quote/A68U.SI/&#34;&gt;Ascott Residence Trust&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://sg.finance.yahoo.com/quote/AU8U.SI&#34;&gt;CapitaLand Retail China Trust&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://sg.finance.yahoo.com/quote/5180.KL/&#34;&gt;CapitaLand Malaysia Trust&lt;/a&gt; (listed on the Kuala Lumpur Stock Exchange).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:list --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;2. Why makes Reits different from other investment vehicles?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:list --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Fundamentally, Reits have no relations with stocks, bonds or commodities, only real estate. Therefore Reits are often thought of as an alternative asset class.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Public companies operate in accordance to typical business regulations set out by e.g. SEC in the US, and different companies operate under different guidelines for different industries, e.g. a medical devices company with the FDA. On the other hand, Reits are more strictly regulated and more homogeneous. In Singapore, &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Reits cannot undertake any development activities (e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reitsweek.com/2017/11/asset-enhancement-initiative.html&#34;&gt;asset enhancement initiatives&lt;/a&gt; or AEI) directly or indirectly, when the value of these activities are in excess of 10% of the Reit&amp;rsquo;s portfolio value.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Reits can have a maximum leverage (i.e. gearing ratio) of 45%.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;As mentioned above, Reits are obligated to pay out a minimum of 90% of its income as distributions (i.e. dividends) to enjoy tax exemptions.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:list --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unlike Reits, these or equivalent measures on leverage and distributions are not applicable in public stocks or companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading {&#34;level&#34;:3} --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;What about Reits vs physical property?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Well that&amp;rsquo;s all good, but what about having real estate exposure by simply owning a property? How does that match up? In Singapore,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:list --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Investing in a Reit requires a brokerage account, a CDP account, and the transaction fees in buying and selling. There is no capital gain tax nor dividend tax in Singapore. For a physical property, there&amp;rsquo;s the following to think about, on top of time and money spent in e.g. sourcing for tenants:&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;3-4% Buyer Stamp Duty&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;12-25% Additional Buyer Stamp Duty&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;legal fees&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;property tax of ~10% Annual Value&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;rental income tax&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;maintenance cost&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;insurance&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;mortgage&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;4-12% Seller Stamp Duty&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;agent commission&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Physical properties are more illquid that the exchange-traded Reit unit&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Due to the price of physical properties, it is unlikely for a retail investor to have say more than 5 or 10 properties, thus incurring concentration risk in location. A well diversified Reit would have no such issues.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Yield of a Reit is typically in the 4-8% range, while it could be challenging to replicate or better this yield from a physical property.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:list --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading {&#34;level&#34;:3} --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;(Good to know) Reits versus Business trusts, stapled securities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not all the counters you see on SGX that seem like Reits, are actually Reits. For example, Ascendas Reit (&lt;a href=&#34;https://sg.finance.yahoo.com/quote/A17U.SI/&#34;&gt;A17U.SI&lt;/a&gt;) is a Reit, while Ascendas Htrust (&lt;a href=&#34;https://sg.finance.yahoo.com/quote/Q1P.SI&#34;&gt;Q1P.SI&lt;/a&gt;) is a &lt;strong&gt;stapled security&lt;/strong&gt;, i.e. one unit of Q1P constitutes buying into the Ascendas Hospitality Real Estate Trust plus the Ascendas Hospitality Business Trust. Think of it as stapling two pieces of paper together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From a regulatory standpoint, there are significant differences between a Reit and a business trust. This &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reitas.sg/singapore-reits/differences-between-s-reits-business-trusts-in-singapore/&#34;&gt;REITAS page&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reitas.sg/&#34;&gt;REITAS&lt;/a&gt; is short for REIT Association of Singapore) is clear on the differences. For retail investors, it would be good to be cognizant of the following (lifted from the same page):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:table --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;wp-block-table&#34;&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Business Trust&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distribution&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Reits must distribute at least 90% of their specified income to their unitholders to enjoy tax transparency under the Income Tax Act.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;There is no statutory requirement to distribute a certain percentage of its income, but business trusts may pledge to distribute a certain percentage of income to their unitholders. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gearing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;The Code on Collective Investment Schemes sets a 45% cap on gearing.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;There is no statutory gearing limit, but business trusts may commit to a self-imposed borrowing limit.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:table --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a stapled security, all Reits regulation (e.g. the Income Tax Act and the Code on Collective Investment Schemes) apply to the Reit portion only. The business trust is nothing but a company, regulated under typical public company regulations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;3. Why invest in Reits?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:list --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Reits allow for property exposure without the significant hassle of property ownership.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Reits are most commonly thought of as a source of passive income stream, and rightfully so. As we pointed out earlier in this 101, Reits are obligated to pay out a minimum of 90% of its income as distributions to enjoy tax exemptions. Suffice to say that the math works out for the Reit manager to indeed pay out at least 90%. This obligation is viewed as a plus point for retail investors as a consistent passive income. This is in addition to the fact that most Reits distribute on a quarterly basis.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Because the relatively high yields (~6-8%), Reits can play a part in a retiree&amp;rsquo;s holdings, where passive income and/or principal drawback kicks in. Instead of selling of units, Reits function as a perpetual income stream, of course provided that you have accumulated enough units during your career years.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Unlike evaluating companies coming from a variety of industries, from e-commerce to shipping, Reits are relatively homogeneous and easier to understand. The notion of buying and managing a property, then collect rental income is much easier to grasp than e.g. how Medicare and Medicaid policy changes will affect the outlook of pharmaceutical companies. This relative ease makes it more straightforward to evaluate Reits, and act on your decision.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;In addition to high yields, Reits also avail themselves to capital gains and losses. Reits have been performing well since the second half of 2018 and continues to do so. Make of that what you will.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:list --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;4. What are the different types of Reits?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reits are typically thought of as coming under these five categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:list {&#34;ordered&#34;:true} --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Retail Reits&lt;/strong&gt; are those comprising of shopping malls, focusing on the retail sector. Example Reit: &lt;a href=&#34;https://sg.finance.yahoo.com/quote/c38u.si/&#34;&gt;CapitaMall Trust&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Commercial Reits&lt;/strong&gt; go for commercial properties, such as office buildings. Example Reit: &lt;a href=&#34;https://sg.finance.yahoo.com/quote/t82u.si/&#34;&gt;Suntect Reit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Industrial Reits&lt;/strong&gt; consist of properties like factories, warehouses and other specialized facilities. Example Reit: &lt;a href=&#34;https://sg.finance.yahoo.com/quote/me8u.si/&#34;&gt;Mapletree Industrial Trust&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hospitality Reits&lt;/strong&gt; are the ones with hotels and serviced apartments. Example Reit: &lt;a href=&#34;https://sg.finance.yahoo.com/quote/q1p.si/&#34;&gt;Ascendas hTrust&lt;/a&gt; (a stapled security).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Healthcare Reits&lt;/strong&gt; are, well, hospitals and other healthcare facilities like medical centers or nursing homes. Example Reit: &lt;a href=&#34;https://sg.finance.yahoo.com/quote/AW9U.si/&#34;&gt;First Reit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:list --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As you can imagine, each category of Reits would flourish or suffer under whichever prevailing economic conditions. The clearest example would be that hospitality Reits would typically suffer during economic downturns, where consumers are less likely to travel (discretionary spending). High unemployment numbers could mean lower occupancy in commercial Reits, while a boost from the government to transform the country into a medical tourism hub would do well for healthcare Reits. As such, these broad economic and policy changes plays significant role in Reit evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is also a bunch of Reit-ETFs, such as the &lt;a href=&#34;https://sg.finance.yahoo.com/quote/CLR.SI&#34;&gt;Lion-Phillip S-Reit ETF&lt;/a&gt;, which I personally don&amp;rsquo;t fancy - it&amp;rsquo;s kind of &amp;ldquo;fee-on-top-of-fee&amp;rdquo;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://thestatsguy.rbind.io/post/2019/01/13/a-guide-to-dollar-cost-averaging-in-singapore/&#34;&gt;Using regular saving plans products like the POEMS Shares Builder Plans&lt;/a&gt; can allow us to assemble &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.poems.com.sg/rsp/#counters&#34;&gt;a diverse portfolio of Reits&lt;/a&gt; without the ETF expense ratio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;5. How to evaluate a Reit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Due to their homogeneity, there are a number of standardized ways of Reit evaluation, with the use of a number of metrics that capture different aspects of a Reit. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be going too in-depth here as I would like to explore this topic in greater detail in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here are some ways in which Reits are evaluated:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:list {&#34;ordered&#34;:true} --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distribution per Unit (DPU)&lt;/strong&gt;. The DPU is simply the distributed amount to unitholders during e.g. quarterly distributions. For example, the most recent distribution from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dividends.sg/view/C38U&#34;&gt;CapitaMall Trust&lt;/a&gt; (C38U) in May 2019 was 0.0444 per unit, which is a quarterly yield (see 2. below) and yield-to-date of 1.83%.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distribution Yield&lt;/strong&gt;. Slightly different from DPU is the yield. The yield is simply your dividends divided by your principal, i.e. instead of having units as a denominator in DPU, we are talking here about the price of the Reit. More important than maximizing yield (the so-called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fool.com/retirement/2018/01/28/what-is-a-dividend-trap.aspx&#34;&gt;dividend trap&lt;/a&gt;) is to look for stable and growing distributions. An increasing yield over time could mean that the Reit is stable, and is able to attract tenants. For example, the yield of C38U grew from 3.44% in 2013 to 7.68% in 2018 full year.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Price-to-NAV&lt;/strong&gt;. The price-to-NAV ratio, also known as book value, compares the market valuation of the Reit to the value of the Reit in its books. NAV stands for net asset value, which captures the amount of money, in principle, that the Reit would have if the Reit manager liquidates all assets and returns the money back to investors. We would consider any price-to-NAV ratio of less than 1 to signal undervaluation by the market. Following are some examples (as of May 2019):&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sg.finance.yahoo.com/quote/t82U.SI/key-statistics?p=t82U.SI&#34;&gt;Suntec Reit&lt;/a&gt; - 0.87&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sg.finance.yahoo.com/quote/k71U.SI/key-statistics?p=k71U.SI&#34;&gt;Keppel Reit&lt;/a&gt; - 0.85&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sg.finance.yahoo.com/quote/ME8U.SI/key-statistics?p=ME8U.SI&#34;&gt;Mapletree Industrial Trust&lt;/a&gt; - 1.39&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gearing Ratio&lt;/strong&gt;. Also known as leverage, the gearing ratio is the ratio between the amount of debt divided by the Reit&amp;rsquo;s total assets. Recall we talked about the maximum gearing ratio of a Reit in Singapore has to be less than 45%. Generally, we are seeing an average of &amp;lt; 40% amongst our S-Reits.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weighted Lease Average Expiry (WALE)&lt;/strong&gt;. As the name suggests, WALE is simply the mean remaining lease duration, weighted by the rental income, in the Reit&amp;rsquo;s portfolio. Needless to say, a WALE of 10 years is better than that of 5 years. WALE typically differs depending on the type of Reit - for example, industrial Reits tend to have longer leases than a retail Reit.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Capitalization Rate&lt;/strong&gt;. Also know as property yield, the cap rate simply captures the income derived from the properties (net operating income) to the value of the properties.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:list --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And there&amp;rsquo;s more. Some of these metrics, like WALE, are obviously Reit-specific, while others apply to most if not all listed company stocks. I will go over more of these metrics, as well as viewing Reits under a fundamental analysis lens, in a later, post-101 series of posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s all for now - thank you for reading! :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stylized facts in statistical finance</title>
      <link>/post/2019/04/04/stylized-facts-in-statistical-finance/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019/04/04/stylized-facts-in-statistical-finance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://miro.medium.com/max/1280/1*LZnClq6o0kEU88-BZnkvCw.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In statistical finance (as well as in certain areas in social science), &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stylized_fact&#34;&gt;stylized facts&lt;/a&gt; are empirical observations summarized in a theory-like form, and are generally representative under broad circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stylized facts are commonly used in statistical finance to address and summarize phenomenon directly observed from historical data, and explainable with a certain level of theoretical consistency and logic (&#34;... this makes sense to me&#34;). Stylized facts may often guide investigations and explorations into certain topics of interest, functioning perhaps as assumptions to be either built upon or proven otherwise. Specifically, invalidating a stylized fact could be considered insightful, much like using data analysis and machine learning to invalidate certain entrenched assumptions held by business users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this first statistical finance post, I would like to list out a couple of stylized facts (SF), without explanation, that are observed and used in finance, for future referencing as well as for my own explorations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(SF1)&lt;/strong&gt; Financial data has extremely low signal-to-noise ratio.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(SF2)&lt;/strong&gt; Price changes are less volatile in bull markets and more volatile bear markets.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(SF3)&lt;/strong&gt; The autocorrelations of the returns of an asset is weak, hence univariate prediction of returns is not possible. However, volatility autocorrelation is strong, and volatility can be reasonably predicted (using e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Autoregressive_conditional_heteroskedasticity&#34;&gt;GARCH&lt;/a&gt; models).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(SF4)&lt;/strong&gt; Financial data usually have more extreme events or values than expected (fat tails, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_swan_theory&#34;&gt;black swans&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(SF5)&lt;/strong&gt; Tail dependence between different assets are high, making &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Copula_(probability_theory)&#34;&gt;copula&lt;/a&gt; fitting worthwhile.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(SF6)&lt;/strong&gt; Past price changes are negatively correlated with future volatility.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(SF7)&lt;/strong&gt; Aggregate stock market returns (e.g. an index) display negative skewness; individual stock returns display positive skewness.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(SF8)&lt;/strong&gt; In the long run, stocks in a given market will be positively correlated.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(SF9)&lt;/strong&gt; Volatility clustering is typically observed in financial data; that is, large changes tend to be followed by large changes of either sign, and small changes tend to be followed by small changes of either sign.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are probably more and more advanced ones that I have yet to come across, so I will probably add on to the list over time. In any case, I will start with these SFs and other techniques in the meantime, in my exploration of statistical finance. I also be using these SF indices (SF1 etc.) as references in future posts to reduce verbose.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reviewing means of stashing cash with impending recession in sight</title>
      <link>/post/2019/03/28/reviewing-means-of-stashing-cash-with-impending-recession-in-sight/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019/03/28/reviewing-means-of-stashing-cash-with-impending-recession-in-sight/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- wp:image --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;wp-block-image&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://assets.bwbx.io/images/users/iqjWHBFdfxIU/ikhFGzC1peMs/v4/pidjEfPlU1QWZop3vfGKsrX.ke8XuWirGYh1PKgEw44kE/775x-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Inversion of US Treasury yield spread. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2019-03-22/u-s-treasury-yield-curve-inverts-for-first-time-since-2007&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:image --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2019-03-22/u-s-treasury-yield-curve-inverts-for-first-time-since-2007&#34;&gt;US Treasury yield curve inverting for the first time since 2007&lt;/a&gt;, we have our first reliable signal from the market that a recession is around the corner, perhaps &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2019-02-25/most-economists-see-u-s-recession-by-2021-nabe-survey-shows&#34;&gt;by 2021&lt;/a&gt; or earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From a simple retail investing standpoint, an impending recession means that we want to stash away cash, and perhaps load some of it into our brokerage accounts when the fire sale swings by. Load and ready.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;My current means of stashing cash - DBS Multiplier and Singapore Savings Bonds&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dbs.com.sg/personal/landing/dbs-multiplier/&#34;&gt;DBS Multiplier&lt;/a&gt; account is of course &lt;a href=&#34;https://thestatsguy.rbind.io/post/2018/10/20/ocbc-360-interest-structure-change-whats-the-impact-on-you-and-me/&#34;&gt;one of my workhorse accounts&lt;/a&gt; for monthly working capital. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sgs.gov.sg/savingsbonds/About-SSB/Overview.aspx&#34;&gt;Singapore Savings Bonds&lt;/a&gt; (SSB) have been a crucial part of my funds management, and form part of my monthly savings and source of passive income (with a &lt;a href=&#34;https://kpo-and-czm.blogspot.com/2018/04/dbs-multiplier-ssbs-joint-account-higher-interest.html&#34;&gt;SSB bond ladder&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I view SSBs as an intermediate form of liquidity with moderate yields, with cash in my DBS Multiplier account being more liquid and my dollar cost averaging (DCA) investments being less liquid (may inevitably realize losses if cash is required). On the other hand, SSBs have pro-rated interest payout and a one-month redemption latency with no penalty - functioning well as intermediate liquidity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(In addition, MAS recently (February 2019) &lt;a href=&#34;https://thestatsguy.rbind.io/post/2018/12/21/short-good-news-for-fans-of-singapore-savings-bonds/&#34;&gt;announced that SSBs can be purchased using SRS funds, via the respective SRS operators&lt;/a&gt;. This meant that the new risk-free rate in our &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mof.gov.sg/MOF-For/Individuals/Supplementary-Retirement-Scheme-SRS&#34;&gt;SRS&lt;/a&gt; accounts becomes the SSB yields, making the use of SRS for tax breaks that much more attractive.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;A reasonable point of view on future SSB interest rates trends&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:image {&#34;align&#34;:&#34;center&#34;,&#34;id&#34;:300,&#34;width&#34;:697,&#34;height&#34;:424} --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;wp-block-image&#34;&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;aligncenter is-resized&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://thestatsguyhome.files.wordpress.com/2019/03/image-3.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;wp-image-300&#34; width=&#34;697&#34; height=&#34;424&#34;/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Trending of historical SSB per annum interest rates&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:image --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This month&amp;rsquo;s (purchase March 2019 for April 2019 issue) average 10-year yield is sitting at 2.16%. If you paid attention to SSB yields in the recent months, there seem to be an imminent downward trend, down from a peak of 2.57% in the December 2019 issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2019-03-20/fed-sees-no-2019-hikes-plans-september-end-to-asset-drawdown&#34;&gt;US Federal Reserve making an announcement in earlier this month there will likely be no more interest hikes in 2019&lt;/a&gt;, it does look to me that the SSB interest rates will be remaining at current levels of about 2.15% to 2.20%, give or take. For context, DBS Multiplier is able to give me between 2.20% to 2.30% on 50K of funds. The appeal of SSBs is certainly going to pale in the months to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s actionable for me?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When these pieces of information are assembled, in addition to my anticipation of some big-item purchases within the mid-term horizon, it seems worthy of my time and effort to do review my monthly funds management. Specifically, after discounting for expenses and payments, in between keeping 50K in DBS Multiplier and monthly purchases of SSB, there can be one additional location for me to stash cash - in decreasing liquidity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:list --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;(salary minus expenses and payments)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;(cash) Cash in DBS Multiplier, up to bonus interest cap&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(cash) Additional cash stash&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;(SSB) Monthly purchase of SSB&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;(investments) Monthly DCA investments via RSPs&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:list --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Where to stash cash?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this context, I figured the best way to fulfill my need is &lt;em&gt;another high-yield savings account that does not rely on salary, GIRO payments, credit card spending or any of such requirements&lt;/em&gt;, as these are generally already taken up by my DBS Multiplier account. Fixed deposits and the like won&amp;rsquo;t cut it, due to low relative yields and even lower liquidity. With that mind, a quick internet search gave the following shortlist:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:list --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.posb.com.sg/personal/deposits/savings-accounts/saye&#34;&gt;POSB Save-As-You-Earn (SAYE) account&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cimbbank.com.sg/en/personal/products/accounts/savings-accounts/cimb-fastsaver-account.html&#34;&gt;CIMB FastSaver account&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.citibank.com.sg/gcb/deposits/mxgn-savacc.htm&#34;&gt;Citi MaxiGain Savings account&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:list --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And following is a straightforward comparison:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:table --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;wp-block-table&#34;&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Account&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interest rate&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My take for my needs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;POSB SAYE&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;2%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Save fixed amount every month, no touching for 2 years&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;2 years is ok, though I prefer more flexibility for the step-up amount. Fixing the amont does not appeal to me.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;CIMB FastSaver&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Flat, no conditions no nothing&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Too low - though &amp;ldquo;no conditions&amp;rdquo; seems terrific as a workhorse account post-retirement. Haven&amp;rsquo;t research on this yet.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Citi MaxiGain&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;~2.2%, depending on 1-month SIBOR&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;70K to enjoy base interest rate of 70% of 1-month SIBOR (currently at &lt;a href=&#34;https://abs.org.sg/rates-sibor&#34;&gt;1.83%&lt;/a&gt;);&lt;br&gt;Step-up bonus of 0.1% per month, up to 1.2%&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;(70K is also meets the criteria for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.citibank.com.sg/citi-priority/index.htm&#34;&gt;Citi Priority&lt;/a&gt; banking.)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Seems right, aligned with my needs. 70K is reasonable for the base rate, high potential rates, step-up amount is flexible unlike SAYE. Citi Priority as a bonus.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:table --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Citi MaxiGain Savings Account&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is pretty clear to me what I should go for. A bit more details on the Citi MaxiGain Savings account (quoted from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.citibank.com.sg/gcb/deposits/mxgn-savacc.htm&#34;&gt;MaxiGain page&lt;/a&gt; FAQ - emphasis my own):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:list --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The Bank shall pay you a base interest rate (&amp;ldquo;Base Interest Rate&amp;rdquo;) at 70% of the 1 month Singapore Dollar Singapore Interbank Offer Rate (&amp;ldquo;1 month SIBOR&amp;rdquo;) on your daily balance, up to the first S$150,000 in your MaxiGain account. For example, if 1 month SIBOR is 1.43% p.a., the Base Interest Rate shall be 1% p.a.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;You need to maintain a daily end of day balance of at least $70,000 in your MaxiGain account to earn (the base) interest. Interest at the Base Interest Rate will accrue daily, if you maintain at least S$70,000 in your MaxiGain account, based on the daily end of day balance and will be paid on the last day of the month.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Your balances capped at S$150,000 shall accrue bonus interest at a rate (&amp;ldquo;Bonus Interest Rate&amp;rdquo;) that steps up each month, from 0.10% p.a. to a maximum of 1.20% p.a., &lt;strong&gt;if the lowest balance in your MaxiGain account in a month is equal to or greater than the lowest balance in the previous month&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The Counter increases by 1 each time the Bonus Interest Rate steps up. &lt;strong&gt;The Bonus Interest Rate steps up in a month if the lowest balance in that month is equal to or greater than the lowest balance in the preceding month&lt;/strong&gt;. Bonus interest is computed based on the preceding month&amp;rsquo;s lowest balance and number of calendar days in the preceding month. &lt;strong&gt;The lowest amount of funds in your MaxiGain account at any point in time in a month shall be the &amp;ldquo;lowest balance&amp;rdquo; of that month&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:list --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seems to me it is easy to manage the monthly account balance to ensure that the Counter increases by 1 every month, up to 12 times. Certainly easier than the SAYE account which is less flexible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With that, the final picture should look like this - again in decreasing liquidity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:list --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;(salary minus expenses and payments)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;(cash) Cash in DBS Multiplier, up to bonus interest cap&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(cash) Monthly deposit into Citi MaxiGains&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;(SSB) Monthly purchase of SSB&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;(investments) Monthly DCA investments via RSPs&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:list --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Time to get off the laptop and drop by a Citibank branch!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A guide to dollar cost averaging in Singapore</title>
      <link>/post/2019/01/13/a-guide-to-dollar-cost-averaging-in-singapore/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019/01/13/a-guide-to-dollar-cost-averaging-in-singapore/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.sgmoneymatters.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/collect-passive-income.jpg&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Happy New Year from Korea everyone! I am currently on a business trip in Seoul, visiting our Korean counterparts for 2 weeks. Besides the weeknight / weekend day trips to popular spots like Myeongdong and Dongdaemun, I have also found some time to do a bit of writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the new year comes the new year resolutions of many Singaporeans. If you have been trying to get started on investing but not very exactly sure how to get started, then this post on dollar cost averaging and regular savings plans should be a good guide for you. Here goes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/d/dollarcostaveraging.asp&#34;&gt;Dollar cost averaging&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;(DCA) is a tool in the repertoire of the long term investor to minimize impact on portfolios due to market turbulence. DCA works because cost of investing reduces to some average amount that generally performs better than if a lump sum amount is straightaway placed into the market, especially if the market is volatile. There are many resources explaining the numbers behind DCA and its pros and cons, so I won&amp;rsquo;t talk about those in this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What I would to present in this post, however, is a guide to getting started in practicing DCA in Singapore. DCA in Singapore is generally referenced using the term &amp;ldquo;regular savings plan&amp;rdquo; (RSP), and if you do a quick Google search on RSPs in Singapore, you should be able to see a couple of prominent articles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:list --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Moneysmart -&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.moneysmart.sg/this-vs-that/posb-ocbc-poems-maybank-kim-eng-which-regular-savings-plan-to-use/&#34;&gt;https://blog.moneysmart.sg/this-vs-that/posb-ocbc-poems-maybank-kim-eng-which-regular-savings-plan-to-use/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Seedly -&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.seedly.sg/which-regular-savings-plan-is-the-cheapest/&#34;&gt;https://blog.seedly.sg/which-regular-savings-plan-is-the-cheapest&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Dollarsandsense -&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dollarsandsense.sg/which-monthly-investment-plan-is-suitable-for-you/&#34;&gt;https://dollarsandsense.sg/which-monthly-investment-plan-is-suitable-for-you/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:list --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And from there, you should be able to see that there are four main providers of RSPs in Singapore, namely:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:list {&#34;ordered&#34;:true} --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;The&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.posb.com.sg/personal/investments/investing-in-funds/invest-saver&#34;&gt;POSB Invest-Saver&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;(IS)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ocbc.com/personal-banking/investments/bluechip.html&#34;&gt;OCBC Blue Chip Investment Plan&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;(BCIP)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.poems.com.sg/rsp/&#34;&gt;Phillip POEMS Shares Builder Plan&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;(SBP)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.maybank-ke.com.sg/latest-offerings/listing/sgd0-commission-with-monthly-investment-plan/&#34;&gt;Maybank Kim Eng Monthly Investment Plan&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;(MIP)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:list --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Each has their pluses and minuses, so in this post, I will build a simple framework to draw the important comparisons between each of these RSPs. If you decide to join the club and be a DCA-er like me, then hopefully this post can help you make a more informed decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading {&#34;level&#34;:3} --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comparison metrics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Can&amp;rsquo;t build a framework for analysis without having our basis of comparison:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:list {&#34;ordered&#34;:true} --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Range of counters available&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Transaction fees and minimum charges&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Dividend reinvestment&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Payment modes and order execution&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Selling and other hidden fees&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Other factors of consideration&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:list --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading {&#34;level&#34;:3} --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;1. Range of counters available&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following illustrates the range of counters available in each RSP:&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:table {&#34;className&#34;:&#34;is-style-regular&#34;} --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;wp-block-table is-style-regular&#34;&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SGX&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other exchanges&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ETFs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bond-based&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;IS&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;BCIP&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;18&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;18&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;SBP&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;39&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;39&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;MIP&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&amp;gt;230&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;45&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;The rest (US, HK, MY, TH)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:table --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is immediately clear that the MIP gives investors acccess to a significantly larger range of counters, including those in the US and Hong Kong. MIP does not provide access to any ETFs. The other three provides only counters in SGX, with the SBP being the most varied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arguably, if you are thinking of doing DCA, then it&amp;rsquo;s unlikely that you would want to dabble in any counters traded in Malaysia or Thailand - maybe Hong Kong as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In terms of ETF coverage, following illustrates:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:table --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;wp-block-table&#34;&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Equity-based ETFs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bond-based ETFs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;IS&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;G3B.SI&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;A35.SI&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;BCIP&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;G3B.SI&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;SBP&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;ES3.SI, OVQ.SI, CLR.SI&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;A35.SI, MBH.SI&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;MIP&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;ES3.SI&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:table --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading {&#34;level&#34;:3} --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;2. Transaction fees and minimum charges&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The next thing we have to consider is of course transaction fees. Pitched as a low barrier of entry product for investors to start investing, transaction fees in RSPs are typically lower than that of brokerage accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:table {&#34;className&#34;:&#34;is-style-regular&#34;} --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;wp-block-table is-style-regular&#34;&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transaction fees&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;IS&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1% for G3B.SI, 0.5% for A35.SI&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;BCIP&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.3% or $5 per counter, whichever is higher&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;SBP&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&amp;lt; $1,000 transactions and  ≤ 2 counters: $6&lt;br&gt;&amp;lt; $1,000 transactions and  ≥ 3 counters: $10&lt;br&gt;&amp;gt; $1,000 transactions: 0.2% or $10, whichever is higher&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;MIP&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&amp;lt; $1,000 transactions: 1%&lt;br&gt;&amp;gt; $1,000 transactions: 0.18% for SGX, 0.2% otherwise&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:table --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From this, it&amp;rsquo;s clear that the selection of RSP product is a function of your total monthly investment amount, ceteris paribus. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:table --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;wp-block-table&#34;&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;lt; $500&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$500 - $1,000&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;gt; $1,000&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;IS&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; ≤ $5&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;$5 - $10&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1% or 0.5%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;BCIP&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;$5&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;$5&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; 0.3%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;SBP&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;$6&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;$6 - $10&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.2%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;MIP&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; ≤ $5&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;$5 - $10&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.18% or 0.2%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:table --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Simply put, if you have $500 tops to invest per month, then IS or MIP are probably your best options, as there are no minimum charges. On the other hand, if you have more than $1,000 to invest per month, then SBP or MIP would be better options for you as you would have crossed the minimum charges threshold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That leaves the $500 - $1,000 range. If you are in this range, I would think it&amp;rsquo;s reasonable to assume that in the short-term you should be able to increase your investment to above $1,000 per month. Therefore I would recommend making your decision with that in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading {&#34;level&#34;:3} --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;3. Dividend reinvestment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many investors are divided (pun intended) between dividend withdrawal and dividend reinvestment. Personally I prefer to have the free cash for me to divert to other locations, but that&amp;rsquo;s me. For RSPs, here&amp;rsquo;s the lowdown:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:table --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;wp-block-table&#34;&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dividend reinvestment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;IS&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Both available&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;BCIP&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Dividend withdrawal&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;SBP&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Both available&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;MIP&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Dividend withdrawal &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:table --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading {&#34;level&#34;:3} --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;4. Payment Modes and Order Execution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another straightforward factor of consideration&amp;hellip;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:table --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;wp-block-table&#34;&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Payment mode&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Order execution&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;IS&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Debit from DBS/POSB a/c*&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Debit on 15th, buy&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;BCIP&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Debit from OCBC a/c&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Debit on 22nd, buy&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;SBP&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;GIRO into SBP cash ledger&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Debit 6BD from 18th, buy on 18th&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;MIP&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;GIRO into KE prefunded a/c&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Debit 1st BD, buy on 8th&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:table --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; with some specific details on mechanisms:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:list --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The SBP cash ledger is a special ledger created for the purposes of the SBP. It is not the Phillip Money Market Fund and pays no interest. Dividends, if any, are paid into the cash ledger and can be withdrawn accordingly. Don&amp;rsquo;t have to worry about this. Nonetheless, you will still need to create a POEMS account first. Both KC or prepaid can be used for the SBP.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The KE prefunded account is a pre-requisite to the MIP. You will have to create a prefunded account in order to use the MIP. Dividends, if any, are paid into the prefunded account. You can also use the prefunded account to execute ordinary trades.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;EPS (Electronic Payment for Shares) and CDP (SGX Central Depository) facilities are not required for any of the RSPs, though they are always good to have.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;On the respective order execution dates (15th, 22nd, 18th, 8th), if it falls on a non-business day the order will be executed on the next BD.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;If you are sharp enough, you would realize that GIRO equates to bill payments and can be used to qualify for certain deposit account bonus interest components.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:list --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;*New IS applications count towards the Invest component of the &lt;a rel=&#34;noreferrer noopener&#34; aria-label=&#34;DBS Multiplier account (opens in a new tab)&#34; href=&#34;https://www.dbs.com.sg/personal/landing/dbs-multiplier/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;DBS Multiplier account&lt;/a&gt;, but only for the first 12 months of transactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;5. Selling and other hidden fees&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Selling shares is not typically explained in great detail, as most DCA-ers are looking for long-term, buy-and-hold type of investing system. That said, it is still important to understand the fees associated with selling your shares, as well as other hidden fees that are buried in the terms and conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Selling shares&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:table --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;wp-block-table&#34;&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Selling transaction fees&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;IS&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dollarsandsense.sg/posb-invest-saver-heres-automatically-invest-strongest-singapore-companies-bonds-every-month/&#34;&gt;None&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;BCIP&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ocbc.com/personal-banking/investments/bluechip.html#fees&#34;&gt; 0.30% of the total sales proceeds or S$5 per counter, whichever is higher &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;SBP&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Same as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.poems.com.sg/products/stocks/&#34;&gt;POEMS&lt;/a&gt; itself&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;MIP&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Same as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.maybank-ke.com.sg/pricing/pricing-listing/stocks/&#34;&gt;KE&lt;/a&gt; itself&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:table --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other hidden fees&lt;/strong&gt; - this is largely driven by my personal experience with these products! Which means there could be things that I have missed out e.g. BCIP&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:list --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;IS: None that I know of - IS is a really simple and efficient product to work with :)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;BCIP: I don&amp;rsquo;t use BCIP, so I don&amp;rsquo;t have any hands-on experience with it&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;SBP: &lt;strong&gt;Dividend charges&lt;/strong&gt; - while it is listed &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.poems.com.sg/docs/SBP-Infosheet.pdf&#34;&gt;here &lt;/a&gt;that dividends are charged at 1% with a minimum of $1 capped at $50, what&amp;rsquo;s not mentioned is that this dividend charge is applied &lt;strong&gt;per dividend line item&lt;/strong&gt;. For example, just last month (March 2019), Mapletree Industrial Trust (ME8U) did their &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mapletreeindustrialtrust.com/en/Investor-Relations/Distribution/Distribution-History.aspx&#34;&gt;3QFY18/19 and advanced 4QFY18/19 distribution, at 3.07 cents and 1.71 cents per unit&lt;/a&gt;, on pay dates of 8th March and 26th March respectively. However, due to either legal or tax reasons that I have yet to understand fully, typical REIT dividend distributions are split across multiple line items, such as that listed &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dividends.sg/view/ME8U&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. As such and rather incredulously, the SBP dividend charge is applied across each line item. What&amp;rsquo;s more, for every line item that do not meet the $1 minimum, the entire dividend line item is forfeited. Therefore, the best way to really mitigate this is to accumulate sufficient units and transfer them into your CDP ($20.40 per counter inclusive of GST) when the time comes. I did write to Phillip complaining about the application of the dividend charge in this manner, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t manage to effect any change. To be honest, in view of the cheap SBP transaction fees relative to actual monthly DCA execution via other means, I will just have to live with this for now.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;MIP: based on my experience, the MIP in itself is rather transparent. The thing to note here however, is that the associated KE Prefunded account comes with its set of charges and fees, such as the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.maybank-ke.com.sg/pricing/pricing-listing/stocks/&#34;&gt;foreign custody fee&lt;/a&gt; for non-CDP securities. In my view, these charges are fairly reasonable by Singapore market standards.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:list --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:heading --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;6. Other factors of consideration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:heading --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It must be mentioned that the factors that I am listing below must be weighed against all the prior pointers, especially transaction fees. For example, low transaction fees could jolly well compensate for bad user experience, depending of course on how low is low and how bad is bad. It&amp;rsquo;s all subjective anyway. Also, goes without saying that a good user experience is preferable to a bad one, ceteris paribus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;POSB IS is definitely the easiest to work with and get started&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;IS is hands-down the simplest of the gang to get started with investing and DCA. First of all, it is probably accurate to say that every Singaporean son and daughter has a POSB account of some sorts, likely to be the Savings account. That&amp;rsquo;s already half the requirements for IS - the other half is to have iBanking. After which you can simply log on and kick start the RSP. No additional account, no GIRO arrangements, no additional platform or portal to log on. No fuse no nothing. And it&amp;rsquo;s really transparent in terms of  transaction costs. For these reasons, IS is my favorite for its pure and joyful simplicity. POSB Savings account + IS was also how I got started as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By extension, even though I don&amp;rsquo;t have any hands-on experience with the BCIP, I can imagine it to be as simple as the IS within OCBC internet banking, relative to the SBP or MIP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The DBS/POSB iBanking user experience is not be taken granted for&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you are like me and never had prior experience in using any other internet banking platforms beyond DBS and OCBC, then you would really take their UI/UX (user interface/user experience) for granted. While the POEMS platform is what I would deemed as acceptable, the KE platform is rather horrendous. I am no UX expert but there are definitely plenty of areas of improvements for both POEMS and KE. You can stick a query into Google Images to sneak a peek at both. I could feel like I was using a Bloomberg terminal with way less platform capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What IS lacks in ETF and general coverage, SBP and MIP more than makes up for it&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That said, IS only provides two ETFs, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nikkoam.com.sg/etf/sti&#34;&gt;G3B&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nikkoam.com.sg/etf/abf&#34;&gt;A35&lt;/a&gt;. Even for a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bogleheads.org/wiki/Lazy_portfolios&#34;&gt;lazy portfolio&lt;/a&gt; consideration, this is insufficient. A Singaporean lazy portfolio could look like something like &lt;a href=&#34;https://thestatsguy.rbind.io/post/2018/09/16/short-book-review-rich-by-retirement-by-joshua-giersch/&#34;&gt;IWDA.LN + ES3 + A35&lt;/a&gt;, or any other variation on global equity exposure, local equity exposure, local bond exposure (e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nikkoam.com.sg/etf/sgd-investment-grade-corp-bond&#34;&gt;MBH&lt;/a&gt;), with or without EM exposure (e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/quote/EIMI:LN&#34;&gt;EIMI.LN&lt;/a&gt;), small cap exposure or alternatives exposure (e.g. REITs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With this, IS is in itself definitely insufficient even for the laziest of portfolios. In terms of ETF coverage, both SBP and MIP is much broader, allowing DCA access into &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.spdrs.com.sg/etf/fund/spdr-straits-times-index-etf-ES3.html&#34;&gt;ES3&lt;/a&gt;, A35, MBH, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lionglobalinvestors.com/en/funds/lion-phillip-s-reit-etf/index.html&#34;&gt;CLR&lt;/a&gt;, as well as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.phillipfunds.com/home/sing-income-etfs&#34;&gt;OVQ&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(In particular, OVQ is one that I particular watched and took a slightly &lt;a href=&#34;https://thestatsguy.rbind.io/post/2018/10/20/analysis-of-the-phillip-sing-income-etf/&#34;&gt;deeper look)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Therefore, it seems ideal to complement IS with either of SBP and MIP (MIP especially for DCA access to non-SGX securities), or simply skip IS all together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IS can be used to fulfill DBS Multiplier Investment component, while SBP/MIP GIRO deductions can be used to fulfill GIRO bill payment requirements for OCBC 360 etc.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This one is trivial. New IS applications count towards the Invest component of the &lt;a rel=&#34;noreferrer noopener&#34; href=&#34;https://www.dbs.com.sg/personal/landing/dbs-multiplier/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;DBS Multiplier account&lt;/a&gt;, but only for the first 12 months of transactions. (If you already had IS running off another DBS/POSB account, simply switching the funding account to the DBS Multipler account counts as a &amp;ldquo;new IS application&amp;rdquo;.) On the other hand, GIRO deductions used to fund the SBP or MIP can count as bill payments for accounts like OCBC 360 and UOB One.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finally, my personal implementation of DCA includes the IS, SBP, and MIP.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I decided early on that the BCIP seems expensive relative to the others. Having started out with IS, I now use IS for G3B and A35, SBP for OVQ, MBH, and a variety of REITs and stocks, and MIP for &lt;a href=&#34;https://sg.finance.yahoo.com/quote/JNJ?p=JNJ&#34;&gt;JNJ.N&lt;/a&gt;. That said, what that works for me may not work for you. Do your own research!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- wp:paragraph --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s all for this post, hope you gained a little something. Thanks for reading :) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- /wp:paragraph --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Good news for fans of Singapore Savings Bonds</title>
      <link>/post/2018/12/21/good-news-for-fans-of-singapore-savings-bonds/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018/12/21/good-news-for-fans-of-singapore-savings-bonds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src= &#34;https://thestatsguyhome.files.wordpress.com/2018/12/SSB.jpg&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
The Singapore Savings Bonds programme
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Been a while since I last posted on my blog - the last month or so has been hectic for me, with the semester final examinations for my part-time Masters as well as travelling for business. Still, no excuses for slipping on my 2 posts per month commitment, so will try to make up for it in December.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, quick update: following my analysis of the various deposit accounts &lt;a href=&#34;https://thestatsguy.rbind.io/post/2018/10/20/ocbc-360-interest-structure-change-whats-the-impact-on-you-and-me/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, I went ahead and opened my DBS Multiplier account online, together with the DBS Live Fresh credit card. Now all I need to do is to redirect both my salary crediting and the CDP Direct Crediting Service to the Multiplier account, and I am all set to enjoy my interest rates :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to my intended topic - good news for folks who have particularly enjoyed the SSB programme - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sgs.gov.sg/~/media/SGS/SGS%20Announcements%20pdf/SSB%20PDF/MAS%20Media%20Release%20on%20SSB%20Applications%20via%20SRS%20Funds.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;MAS has announced three big moves for SSB on 17th Dec 2018&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With effect from 1st February 2019, SSBs can be purchased using SRS funds, via the respective SRS operators (DBS/POSB, OCBC, UOB).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With effect from 1st February 2019, the Individual Limit for SSBs will be increased from SGD100,000 to SGD200,000.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In March 2019, MAS will be launching a &#34;My Savings Portal&#34; to allow investors to review their SSB portfolios, for both cash and SRS purchases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;SRS + SSB = Awesome Combo&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are really terrific news for anyone who utilizes SSBs in their portfolios. Firstly, SRS funds can finally be parked in an essentially risk-free instrument - a first. I will definitely be using this new feature of the SRS account to get &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; my tax breaks and risk-free rate (which was basically 0.05% p.a. in the SRS account).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quick reminder - before you do any top-ups to your SRS accounts, please do fully understand the SRS scheme and evaluate how the SRS account can play a part in your portfolio or finances. Here&#39;s a good&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dollarsandsense.sg/supplementary-retirement-scheme-4-things-need-understand-opening-srs-account/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;primer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Individual Limit of SGD200,000&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The increase in Individual Limit is great as well. Since SSBs can be considered as free cash flow (pro-rated interest payouts + redemption latency of 1 month), SGD100,000 is not difficult for working professionals with decent savings rates to hit. The increase in Individual Limit is certainly more than welcomed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;My Savings Portal&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, a SSB portal to review holdings - yea, why not? Currently, investors have to log in into CDP accounts to review our SSB holdings, which is good enough an user experience. Hopefully this new portal encompasses all relevant information regarding SSBs, including purchase calendars, redemption calendars, payout calendars, historical rates, bond ladders, planning tools... At least that&#39;s how I would like the UX for such a portal to be - probably wishful thinking on my part :P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking forward to the implementation of these changes in February 2019. For more information on SSBs, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sgs.gov.sg/savingsbonds.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;SSB website&lt;/a&gt; would be in itself a great resource.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of the Phillip SING Income ETF</title>
      <link>/post/2018/10/20/analysis-of-the-phillip-sing-income-etf/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018/10/20/analysis-of-the-phillip-sing-income-etf/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://thestatsguyhome.files.wordpress.com/2018/10/47348-etf-poems-landing-page-2.jpg&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this month (Oct 2018), Phillip Securities introduced a brand new ETF - the Phillip SING Income ETF, to be managed by Phillip Capital Management, Based on the name of the ETF alone, it&#39;s easy to guess the focus of this ETF: dividend income, which is an investment style popular amongst retail investors in Singapore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s how the ETF is described on &lt;a href=&#34;http://poems.com.sg/&#34;&gt;poems.com.sg&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #0000ff;&#34;&gt;Harvest Your Regular Income with Phillip SING Income ETF&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Phillip SING Income ETF focuses on 30 high quality Singapore Listed stocks to offer investors a cost-effective and diversified exposure to the Singapore market. By using a rule/factor-based approach for stocks selection, the ETF aims to deliver stable and quality income for investors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;m-top&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Phillip SING Income ETF provides investors with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy access to 30 high quality Singapore Listed Stocks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Liquidity, transparency and diversification across the Singapore market&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stable and quality income with semi-annual dividend distribution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strategic Beta for stocks selection with emphasis on
&lt;ol type=&#34;1&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Business Quality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Financial Health&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dividend Yield&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s a compilation of articles written by various sources on this ETF:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://fifthperson.com/phillip-sing-income-etf/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Fifth Person&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fool.sg/2018/10/02/the-phillip-sing-income-etf-a-new-option-for-income-hungry-singapore-investors/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Motley Fool Singapore&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dollarsandsense.sg/an-alternative-to-the-sti-etf-introducing-the-phillip-sing-income-etf/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dollars And Sense&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://bedokianportfolio.blogspot.com/2018/09/the-phillip-sing-income-etf.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bedokian Portfolio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.smallcapasia.com/5-things-to-know-about-phillip-sing-income-etf/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Small Cap Asia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I will be doing my analysis on this ETF and evaluate the potential role it can play in my portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Comparison to other Singapore exposure-only ETFs on SGX&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the first questions to ask when evaluating new ETFs is how this new ETF compares with existing ETFs on the exchange. For context, there are plenty of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sgx.com/wps/wcm/connect/eccd3a44-73bf-4f03-a665-db9abb5432d5/ETF_Summary_Info_27+Aug+2018.pdf?MOD=AJPERES&amp;amp;CONVERT_TO=url&amp;amp;CACHEID=eccd3a44-73bf-4f03-a665-db9abb5432d5&#34;&gt;ETFs listed on the SGX&lt;/a&gt;, and there are 7 of them that are specific to gaining Singapore exposure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;O9A.SI - Xtrackers MSCI Singapore UCITS ETF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CLR.SI - Lion Phillip S-REIT ETF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;G3B.SI - Nikko AM Singapore STI ETF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ES3.SI - SPDR Straits Times Index ETF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A35.SI - ABF Singapore Bond Index ETF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MBH.SI - Nikko AM SGD Investment Grade Corporate Bond ETF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;KV4.SI - Xtrackers II Singapore Government Bond UCITS ETF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of these 7,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 of them (A35, MBH, KV4) are fixed income ETFs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 (CLR) is a REIT ETF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 of them (G3B, ES3) are essentially the same (both tracks the STI).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence those valid for comparison are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;O9A.SI - Xtrackers MSCI Singapore UCITS ETF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Either of the STI ETFs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Underlying indices and their constituents&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The STI is, well, the flagship index for the SGX, and tracks the top 30 stocks (by market cap) listed on the SGX. O9A, on the other hand, tracks the MSCI Singapore Index, and the Phillip SING Income ETF will be tracking the Morningstar Singapore Yield Focus Index.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;The Morningstar Singapore Yield Focus Index&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A brief note on the historical performance of the Morningstar Singapore Yield Focus Index (MSYF) - the index has delivered an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fool.sg/2018/10/02/the-phillip-sing-income-etf-a-new-option-for-income-hungry-singapore-investors/&#34;&gt;annualized return of 9.6%&lt;/a&gt; since 2005, which can be broken down into capital gains of 5.2% and dividend returns of 4.4%. Bear in mind that the this period also includes the 2007-2008 financial crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key feature of the MSYF is the avoidance of dividend traps - stocks that generate high yield and yet have weak fundamentals. This is done by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.poems.com.sg/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/Sing-Inc-Index-Information.pdf&#34;&gt;index construction process of the MSYF&lt;/a&gt;. I won&#39;t be covering the math part of it here, because even just by eyeballing the index, we can tell what it can do for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;separator&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;Smart Beta ETF&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;separator&#34;&gt;One thing to point out here is that the Phillip SING Income ETF is a classic example of a Smart Beta ETF. Unlike a typical market cap-weighted index ETF, a Smart Beta ETF usually relies on rules, such as the MSYF index construction rules, to lay out parameters to build the ETF, so as to beat the beta. Once these rules are constructed, the ETF is autonomously functional - hence Smart Beta ETFs are typically regarded as semi-passive ETFs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Top 10 holdings&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following is how the indices differ in top 10 holdings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://thestatsguyhome.files.wordpress.com/2018/10/e07ea-capture.png&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
Top 10 holdings of respective indices
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;separator&#34;&gt;The first thing you should notice is that the top 4 holdings of the three indices are the same, albeit in different order. DBS, OCBC, UOB, and Singtel all feature in the respective top 4. The STI is well-known to be overweighted in our local banks (40.96%), which is similar for the MSCI Singapore Index (47.43%). Whether it&#39;s good for an index to be overweighted in banks is another topic all together - however what&#39;s refreshing here is that the &lt;b&gt;banks take up only 23.9% of the MSYF&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;separator&#34;&gt;This is the first key characteristic for lay investors like us to consider: the &lt;b&gt;MSYF has a hard cap of 10% per stock&lt;/b&gt;. To me, this is biggest upside of this ETF - an ETF on SGX that&#39;s not overweighted in banks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;separator&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;Full holdings and sector distribution&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;separator&#34;&gt;Following are the full holdings of each index.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://thestatsguyhome.files.wordpress.com/2018/10/156f5-full2bholdings.png&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
Full holdings of respective indices
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;separator&#34;&gt;And here are the sector distributions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://thestatsguyhome.files.wordpress.com/2018/10/78bbc-sector2bdistri.png&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
Sector distributions of respective indices
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;separator&#34;&gt;Again, just by eyeballing, what catches my lay investor&#39;s attention immediately is the &lt;b&gt;30.1% representation of real estate&lt;/b&gt; (mainly REITs) in the ETF. Personally, I like S-REITs as dividend generating vehicles, but neither STI nor the S-REIT ETF can offer a diversified and cheap solution to gain REITs exposure in Singapore (the S-REIT ETF is pretty expensive with a 0.6% expense ratio).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;separator&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Dividend yield and expense ratio&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;separator&#34;&gt;Of course, two important things that must be considered for an ETF are the dividend yield and expense ratio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://thestatsguyhome.files.wordpress.com/2018/10/b3761-dividend2byield2band2bexpense2bratio.png&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
Dividend yields and expense ratios of respective indices
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;separator&#34;&gt;For the Phillip SING Income ETF, both 5% yield and 0.4% management fees are indicative numbers given by the fund managers as the most probable. If both numbers come true, this would be another plus point for this ETF - competitive fees with superior yield. The 5% indicative yield comes from the fact that there is a combined 60% of banks and real estate in the ETF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;separator&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;What to think about when the ETF starts trading&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;u&gt;Tax transparency&lt;/u&gt;: something that I didn&amp;rsquo;t thought about previously, so quoting the &lt;a href=&#34;https://fifthperson.com/phillip-sing-income-etf/&#34;&gt;article from The Fifth Person&lt;/a&gt; here - &amp;ldquo;Distributions from S-REITs are tax-free for investors. From 1 July 2018, this tax transparency treatment was also extended to ETFs invested in S-REITs. Previously, distributions from S-REITs to ETFs were taxed at 17%, which made investing in S-REIT ETFs tax inefficient. However, this treatment only applies to ETFs that invest entirely in REITs (like the Lion-Phillip S-REIT ETF). The Phillip SING Income doesn’t qualify for tax transparency as it invests in other securities besides REITs. Phillip Capital Management plans to speak to the authorities about extending the tax transparency treatment to any ETF that invests in REITs, but for now the dividend yield for the Phillip SING Income ETF is effectively 4.8% after factoring the 17% withholding tax on S-REIT distributions.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;u&gt;Tracking error:&lt;/u&gt; Tracking error matters for an ETF: the closer the ETF is to its target index, the better. Since the ETF has not began trading, it remains to be seen whether tracking error will be acceptable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;u&gt;Inclusion into Regular Savings Plan&lt;/u&gt;: since this ETF is managed by Phillip, you can be sure that it will be included into the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.poems.com.sg/rsp/&#34;&gt;POEMS SBP&lt;/a&gt;, potentially even the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.posb.com.sg/personal/investments/investing-in-funds/invest-saver&#34;&gt;POSB Invest-Saver&lt;/a&gt;. Something for the DCA-ers like myself to think about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;separator&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Conclusion&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;separator&#34;&gt;My take is that the Phillip SING Income ETF is a superior alternative to the STI ETF, given the&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Non-overweightage of banks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hard cap of 10% per stocks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;30% representation in REITs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reasonable fees of 0.4%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And that sweet, sweet 5% yield &lt;i&gt;if it comes true&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I have participated in the subscription of this ETF, putting in a few grand, and potentially including it into my DCA if it turns out well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Phillip SING Income ETF will go live on the SGX on 29th Oct 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OCBC 360 Interest structure change: what&#39;s the impact on you and me?</title>
      <link>/post/2018/10/20/ocbc-360-interest-structure-change-whats-the-impact-on-you-and-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018/10/20/ocbc-360-interest-structure-change-whats-the-impact-on-you-and-me/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://thestatsguyhome.files.wordpress.com/2018/10/76eb9-changes2beffective2b1nov.jpg&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
What&amp;rsquo;s changed for the OCBC 360 account bonus interest structure
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Effective from 1st Nov 2018, there will be changes to the interest structure of the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ocbc.com/personal-banking/accounts/360-account.html&#34;&gt;OCBC 360 account&lt;/a&gt;. If you are either exploring deposit accounts out there or currently using OCBC 360 (like myself), you should pay attention to these changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following is the existing interest structure:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://thestatsguyhome.files.wordpress.com/2018/10/0d873-ocbc2b3602bcurrent.jpg&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
Existing interest structure
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;separator&#34;&gt;It&#39;s a relatively straightforward structure that has requirements on salary crediting (which earns you 1.2% p.a.), at least 3 bill payments (0.3%), at spending $500 spending (0.3%), and investing on selected products (either 0.6% or 1.2%).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;separator&#34;&gt;Moving forward, this is the updated structure:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://thestatsguyhome.files.wordpress.com/2018/10/fef2c-ocbc2b3602bupdated.jpg&#34; width=&#34;75%&#34;&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
Updated interest structure (effective 1st Nov 2018)
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;separator&#34;&gt;Major differences between the updated and old structure are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;u&gt;Introduction of 2-tiering&lt;/u&gt;: first 35K and next 35K&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;u&gt;Step-up bonus&lt;/u&gt;: as long as you can increase your account balance by at least $500 relative to previous month, you can earn 0.3% or 0.6% depending on tier. This step-up bonus was offered as an ad-hoc promotion sometime earlier this year (Aug and Sep 2018), but will become a permanent feature in the 360 account.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;u&gt;Grow bonus&lt;/u&gt;: for balances above $200K, the first 70K gets another 1%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;u&gt;Boost bonus&lt;/u&gt;: positive delta between current and previous month-end balance gets another 1%, up to 1mil. Read carefully - it&#39;s only the difference between the month-end balances that gets the 1%, not the month-end balance itself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;u&gt;Payment bonus&lt;/u&gt;: no longer offered. So there&#39;s no bonus/requirement on bill payments anymore.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;What&#39;s the impact on me?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been using the 360 account since I graduated from university in 2015. Back then I didn&#39;t really put too much thought into it, as I was damn broke anyway. I was already using the FRANK account and OCBC internet banking, so it became natural for me to move into the 360 account and get the accompanying 365 credit card.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Earning that 1.8% per annum&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I never had any issues hitting the interest requirements, other than the Invest bonus. The products that can allow me to get this bonus are products that I have no interest in, such as ILPs, structured deposits, and unit trusts, and in minimum amounts of 20K. Makes no sense to me at all. Therefore, for the longest time, I have been getting 1.2% + 0.3% + 0.3%&amp;nbsp; = 1.8% of interest - which is decent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Then and now&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward 3 years and my income and net worth has grown by, well, a rather pleasant amount. This also made the 360 account less and less viable for me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was already drawn to the fact that my month-end balances are becoming flat-lined or dipping, simply because my monthly dollar cost averaging investments are getting higher and higher each month. With this new OCBC 360 interest structure, I will definitely&amp;nbsp;not be able to consistently earn the Step-up bonus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 2-tier structure means that I need to put more than 35K in the account in order to sit in the next tier, as compared to a 1-tier structure with no such requirement. Personally, the 360 account serves also as the location of my emergency funds, and I have no intention to keep that much emergency funds. 70K is too much to be able to utilize this new interest structure to the fullest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ocbc.com/personal-banking/investments/bluechip.html&#34;&gt;OCBC BCIP&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;is still not included in the Invest bonus component. On the other hand, the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dbs.com.sg/personal/landing/dbs-multiplier/&#34;&gt;DBS Multiplier account&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;considers the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.posb.com.sg/personal/investments/investing-in-funds/invest-saver&#34;&gt;POSB Invest-Saver&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;as a qualifying investment. Seems like DBS is more progressive?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, this has triggered my search for the next deposit account that can meet my needs. In the following sections, I will put together some numbers and make a decision from there. If you are using OCBC 360 account as well, I strongly encourage you to review whether this account is optimal for your needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shortlisted accounts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some quick research (OK, this one &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.moneysmart.sg/savings-accounts/best-savings-accounts-singapore/&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; summarized it all up), I will be focusing specifically on the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OCBC 360 account&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DBS Multiplier account&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UOB One account&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bank of China SmartSaver account&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maybank SaveUp account&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, a special mention of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hsbc.com.sg/advance/&#34;&gt;HSBC Advance programme&lt;/a&gt;. I won&#39;t be elaborating on it here, but do check it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comparison metrics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What would be our basis of comparison?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interest structure&lt;/strong&gt;, and how much interest I will be getting &lt;strong&gt;realistically &lt;/strong&gt;- it may not be possible to fulfill all components in the interest structure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Balance cap on the bonus interest&lt;/strong&gt; - how much of my balance qualify for the bonus interest?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Banking convenience&lt;/strong&gt; - since I will be using this account for salary crediting, emergency funds, and everyday expenses, it&#39;s important that I can bank with this account conveniently. This means plenty of ATMs and a decent online banking system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here we go!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;OCBC 360 account&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s start with 360 first. Based on the new structure, I doubt I can consistently get the Step-up bonus, and there&#39;s no way I will purchase any insurance or investment products from OCBC - so here&#39;s how much I think I can get. &#34;Realistic interest rates&#34; are in (brackets).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;125&#34;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;125&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Salary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;125&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spend&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;125&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step-up&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;125&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Invest&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;125&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First 35K&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;125&#34;&gt;1.2% (1.2%)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;125&#34;&gt;0.3% (0.3%)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;125&#34;&gt;0.3% (0%)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;125&#34;&gt;0.6% (0%)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;125&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next 35K&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;125&#34;&gt;1.5% (1.5%)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;125&#34;&gt;0.6% (0.6%)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;125&#34;&gt;0.6% (0%)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;125&#34;&gt;1.2% (0%)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Realistic average interest rate for me: 1.8% (from Salary and Spend)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Balance cap on bonus interest: 70K&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Banking convenience: High (OCBC shares ATMs with UOB and others, and I am already a satisfied user of their online banking system.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;DBS Multiplier account&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dbs.com.sg/personal/landing/dbs-multiplier/&#34;&gt;DBS Multiplier account&lt;/a&gt; is by far one of the most lenient accounts when it comes to qualifying for bonus interest. There are five qualifying components, namely salary, credit card spend, home loan installments, insurance, and investments. The salary component is compulsory, and for every thing else, it&#39;s based on total flow of funds across 2 or 3 components. What do I mean by that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if I have a salary credit of $3,000 per month, with just $1 spend on credit card and $1 on investments (I will explain this later), then it would be total flow of $3,002 across 3 components. This means I can qualify for 2.00% p.a. No minimum amounts on specific components, just considering total flow of funds. It&#39;s that simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://thestatsguyhome.files.wordpress.com/2018/11/51b97-capture.png&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
DBS Multiplier Account Interest Structure
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that, it&#39;s easy to immediately see how much bonus interest I would be getting:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Realistic average interest for me: 2.20%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Balance cap on bonus interest: 50K&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Banking convenience: Medium-High (POSB/DBS ATMs have the longest queues.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the investment component, the easiest way to qualify is via either using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.posb.com.sg/personal/investments/investing-in-funds/invest-saver&#34;&gt;POSB Invest-Saver&lt;/a&gt; (only for the first 12 months - read the fineprint under the investment component &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dbs.com.sg/personal/landing/dbs-multiplier/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) or using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sgs.gov.sg/savingsbonds.aspx&#34;&gt;Singapore Savings Bonds&lt;/a&gt;. I won&#39;t elaborate further on this here, but be sure to check out this &lt;a href=&#34;https://kpo-and-czm.blogspot.com/2018/04/dbs-multiplier-ssbs-joint-account-higher-interest.html&#34;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;UOB One account&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uob.com.sg/personal/save/chequeing/one-account.page&#34;&gt;UOB One account&lt;/a&gt; is pretty straightforward in their interest structure. There are only two qualifying components:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Min. card spend of $500 in the month&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Min. card spend of $500 with either salary crediting or 3 GIRO deductions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So for most folks, hitting both should be relatively easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table style=&#34;height: 247px;&#34; width=&#34;375&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;76&#34;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;302&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2 components&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;76&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First 15K&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;302&#34;&gt;1.85%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;76&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next 15K&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;302&#34;&gt;2.00%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;76&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next 15K&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;302&#34;&gt;2.15%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;76&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next 15K&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;302&#34;&gt;2.30%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;76&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next 15K&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;302&#34;&gt;3.88%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Realistic average interest for me: 2.075% (Probably going to keep up to 60K of cash at any point in time. It&#39;s already a rather significant amount to keep in cash.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Balance cap on bonus interest: 75K&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Banking convenience: High&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;BOC SmartSaver account&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bankofchina.com/sg/pbservice/pb1/201611/t20161130_8271280.html&#34;&gt;BOC SmartSaver account&lt;/a&gt; is probably more suited for relatively higher income earners and spenders, based on their minimum requirements of $1,500 monthly spending (1.60%) and $6,000 income (1.20%). Anything short and you would be losing out by using this account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Realistic average interest for me: 1.55%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Balance cap on bonus interest: 60K&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Banking convenience: Low (in the next 3 seconds, think of a location where you can recall seeing a BOC ATM.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Maybank SaveUp account&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://info.maybank2u.com.sg/saveup/&#34;&gt;Maybank SaveUp account&lt;/a&gt; is Maybank&#39;s attempt at competing in deposit accounts. There are 9 (!) bonus components to choose from which you would need to qualify for 3. As long as you can qualify for 3, the bonus interest would be straight out 3.0625%. Qualifying for 2 gives less than 1.20%, so the jump is tremendous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was first doing my homework on all these deposit accounts, Maybank looked like the obvious choice to me - I didn&#39;t think I would have any problems hitting the 3.06%. This was until I realized that minimum monthly credit card spend of $500 - which incredulously, is a challenge for me. Yes, the amount of money I spend every month is very low and a significant chunk of my spending cannot come from credit cards - unless kopitiams and hawker centers are ready to accept them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, unless credit card spending on insurance or income tax counts, it is unlikely that I can get the 3.06%. Which turns out to be the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Realistic average interest for me: 1.11%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Balance cap on bonus interest: 60K&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Banking convenience: Medium&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;156&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Account&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;156&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Realistic average interest for me&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;156&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Balance cap&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;156&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Banking convenience&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;156&#34;&gt;OCBC 360&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;156&#34;&gt;1.80%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;156&#34;&gt;70K&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;156&#34;&gt;High&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;156&#34;&gt;DBS Multiplier&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;156&#34;&gt;2.20%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;156&#34;&gt;50K&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;156&#34;&gt;Medium-High&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;156&#34;&gt;UOB One&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;156&#34;&gt;2.08%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;156&#34;&gt;75K&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;156&#34;&gt;High&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;156&#34;&gt;BOC SmartSaver&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;156&#34;&gt;1.55%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;156&#34;&gt;60K&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;156&#34;&gt;Low&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;156&#34;&gt;Maybank SaveUp&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;156&#34;&gt;1.11%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;156&#34;&gt;60K&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&#34;156&#34;&gt;Medium&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;Looks like the answer is clear - keep 50K of cash in DBS Multiplier account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assumptions  / Points to note&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This turns out that a large part of this analysis hinges on an assumption of monthly credit card spending of less than $500 - which is true &lt;em&gt;most of the time&lt;/em&gt; for me. There are definitely months where I am able to exceed $500 of credit card spending, but it&#39;s pretty inconsistent. Mostly dependent on whether there&#39;s a special occasion during the month.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The above assumption will no longer be valid if it&#39;s possible to rack up credit card spend with insurance premiums, income tax payments, or other consistent forms of payments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another assumption I made was that I would be unable to consistently increase my month end balances. This assumption is valid simply because of the presence of SSBs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OCBC may one fine day emulate DBS and include the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ocbc.com/personal-banking/investments/bluechip.html&#34;&gt;BCIP&lt;/a&gt; into the 360 investment component. Then the 360 account would work out for me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, do your own homework, and especially consider whether my assumptions make sense in your situation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s all for this post!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Rich by Retirement by Joshua Giersch</title>
      <link>/post/2018/09/16/book-review-rich-by-retirement-by-joshua-giersch/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018/09/16/book-review-rich-by-retirement-by-joshua-giersch/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/I/51kcmMI3s7L._SX331_BO1,204,203,200_.jpg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34;&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joshua Giersch, better known as “Shiny Things”, is an investment guru who has been generously giving investing advice on &lt;a href=&#34;https://forums.hardwarezone.com.sg/money-mind-210/%2Aofficial%2A-shiny-things-club-part-2-a-5813566.html&#34;&gt;HardwareZone&lt;/a&gt; and his &lt;a href=&#34;https://moneygowherefind.com/joshua-giersch-aka-shiny-things-hwz/&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;. His advice are consistently dished out with the SG context in mind, and his book &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Rich-Retirement-Singaporeans-Invest-Wealthy-ebook/dp/B01JXW17ZM&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Rich by Retirement: How Singaporeans Can Invest Smart and Retire Wealthy&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, is, in essence, the consolidation of all of his tips and hacks on being a successful investor in SG.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most interesting component of his philosophy is his very simple portfolio strategy. Whether it is too simple for your liking is for you to decide, and in this post I will summarize, from my perspective, the key points in his book. Enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;emergency-fund&#34;&gt;Emergency fund&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep an emergency fund with 6 months worth of expense&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;insurance&#34;&gt;Insurance&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get hospitalization plan (paid in part using Medisave), and term life if you have dependents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All other forms of insurance are neither necessary nor worthwhile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Especially avoid ILPs and endowments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;brokerage-accounts&#34;&gt;Brokerage accounts&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only pay &amp;lt;= 0.2% for trading SG stocks, &amp;lt;= 0.3% for US/UK stocks; UTs/ETFs with &amp;lt;= 0.5% expense ratio are ok&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anything beyond these percentages are not acceptable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ideally regulated in SG or US&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No custody or dividend handling fees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recommended: SCB, Interactive Brokers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exception to the &amp;lt;= 0.2% recommendation: POSB Invest-Saver, because of the lack of min amount per txn. Good for small investors who are just starting out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;asset-class-allocation&#34;&gt;Asset class allocation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stocks: 110 – current age; bonds: the rest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For stocks, 50:50 on SG and int’l&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For bonds, only SG&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;exchange-traded-funds&#34;&gt;Exchange traded funds&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ETFs are great because of the instant diversification. The ideal ETF would be one with &amp;lt;= 0.3% expense ratio, &amp;gt; 100mil in assets, and is a physical ETF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-shiny-things-3-etf-portfolio&#34;&gt;The Shiny Things 3-ETF portfolio&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IWDA.LN (iShares Core MSCI World UCITS ETF – for Int’l exposure)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ES3.SI (SPDR Straits Times Index ETF – for SG exposure)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A35.SI (ABF Singapore Bond Index Fund – for SG bonds)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;cpf-srs&#34;&gt;CPF/SRS&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep CPF in cash, don’t buy any counters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider using SRS top-ups for tax breaks; can use SRS to buy ES3 (use OCBC BCIP – though A35 is not available)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;dollar-cost-averaging&#34;&gt;Dollar cost averaging&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t time the market – “time in market” &amp;gt; “time the market”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;POSB Invest-Saver is great for DCA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;portfolio-rebalancing&#34;&gt;Portfolio rebalancing&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only rebalance in May and Nov every year&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simple enough? Pick up his book from Amazon or NLB (I had to make a reservation – $1.55 reservation fee) and you will be able to understand his justifications for each of these pointers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
