<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Finance &amp; Investing on The Stats Guy</title>
    <link>/categories/finance-investing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Finance &amp; Investing on The Stats Guy</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/finance-investing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Declining interest rates amidst Covid-19 - and a hidden star</title>
      <link>/post/2020/05/07/declining-interest-rates-amidst-covid-19-and-a-hidden-star/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020/05/07/declining-interest-rates-amidst-covid-19-and-a-hidden-star/</guid>
      <description>As Covid-19 continues to wreck havoc in many countries around the world, including the US, massive sell-offs haven taken place in Wall Street and other markets.
In a move to protect the US economy from the effects of the pandemic, the US Federal Reserve has cut interest rates twice during March 2020 - first in early March, cutting rates by 50 basis points to a targeted range of 1% to 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fundamental Analysis 101: A basic overview of the fundamental analysis of stocks</title>
      <link>/post/2019/06/08/fundamental-analysis-101-a-basic-overview-of-the-fundamental-analysis-of-stocks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019/06/08/fundamental-analysis-101-a-basic-overview-of-the-fundamental-analysis-of-stocks/</guid>
      <description>In this post, I would like to give an overview of the principles and concepts in the fundamental analysis of stocks.
What is fundamental analysis? Well, fundamental analysis (FA) is the analysis of the fundamentals of a company. The fundamentals of the company are trying to capture essentially the health of the company, in the present and future. The objective of FA is to discern a point of view on the current and future prospects of a company – the actionability from this point of view is of course whether to buy (or short-sell) the stock.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Medtech 101: An overview of the medical device industry</title>
      <link>/post/2019/05/27/medtech-101-an-overview-of-the-medical-device-industry/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019/05/27/medtech-101-an-overview-of-the-medical-device-industry/</guid>
      <description>In this post, I will be doing a 101 dissection of the medical device industry. It’s a somewhat not-so-popular industry from the perspective of retail investing, but I have had some prior experience in this space, so it’s a tad easier for me to conduct some levels of analysis on companies in this space.
I will work through the following pointers in this piece, and hopefully at the end of it, allow the reader to have some level of appreciation for the industry as a whole.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>REITs 101: Introduction to real estate investment trusts</title>
      <link>/post/2019/05/20/reits-101-introduction-to-real-estate-investment-trusts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019/05/20/reits-101-introduction-to-real-estate-investment-trusts/</guid>
      <description>This post is a 101 dissection of real estate investment trusts, REITs or Reits in short. As the full content of this topic is pretty long and I will try to make this 101 comprehensive, touching on the following:
What are ReitsWhat makes Reits different from other investment vehiclesWhy invest in ReitsWhat are the different types of ReitsHow to evaluate a Reit As you can see, there&amp;rsquo;s plenty to talk about even in a 101 piece, so let&amp;rsquo;s get straight to it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reviewing means of stashing cash with impending recession in sight</title>
      <link>/post/2019/03/28/reviewing-means-of-stashing-cash-with-impending-recession-in-sight/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019/03/28/reviewing-means-of-stashing-cash-with-impending-recession-in-sight/</guid>
      <description>Inversion of US Treasury yield spread. Source.   With the US Treasury yield curve inverting for the first time since 2007, we have our first reliable signal from the market that a recession is around the corner, perhaps by 2021 or earlier.
From a simple retail investing standpoint, an impending recession means that we want to stash away cash, and perhaps load some of it into our brokerage accounts when the fire sale swings by.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A guide to dollar cost averaging in Singapore</title>
      <link>/post/2019/01/13/a-guide-to-dollar-cost-averaging-in-singapore/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019/01/13/a-guide-to-dollar-cost-averaging-in-singapore/</guid>
      <description>Happy New Year from Korea everyone! I am currently on a business trip in Seoul, visiting our Korean counterparts for 2 weeks. Besides the weeknight / weekend day trips to popular spots like Myeongdong and Dongdaemun, I have also found some time to do a bit of writing.
With the new year comes the new year resolutions of many Singaporeans. If you have been trying to get started on investing but not very exactly sure how to get started, then this post on dollar cost averaging and regular savings plans should be a good guide for you.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[short] Good news for fans of Singapore Savings Bonds</title>
      <link>/post/2018/12/21/short-good-news-for-fans-of-singapore-savings-bonds/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018/12/21/short-good-news-for-fans-of-singapore-savings-bonds/</guid>
      <description>The Singapore Savings Bonds programme 
Been a while since I last posted on my blog - the last month or so has been hectic for me, with the semester final examinations for my part-time Masters as well as travelling for business. Still, no excuses for slipping on my 2 posts per month commitment, so will try to make up for it in December.
Also, quick update: following my analysis of the various deposit accounts here, I went ahead and opened my DBS Multiplier account online, together with the DBS Live Fresh credit card.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of the Phillip SING Income ETF</title>
      <link>/post/2018/10/20/analysis-of-the-phillip-sing-income-etf/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018/10/20/analysis-of-the-phillip-sing-income-etf/</guid>
      <description>Earlier this month (Oct 2018), Phillip Securities introduced a brand new ETF - the Phillip SING Income ETF, to be managed by Phillip Capital Management, Based on the name of the ETF alone, it&#39;s easy to guess the focus of this ETF: dividend income, which is an investment style popular amongst retail investors in Singapore.
Here&#39;s how the ETF is described on poems.com.sg:
Harvest Your Regular Income with Phillip SING Income ETF The Phillip SING Income ETF focuses on 30 high quality Singapore Listed stocks to offer investors a cost-effective and diversified exposure to the Singapore market.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OCBC 360 Interest structure change: what&#39;s the impact on you and me?</title>
      <link>/post/2018/10/20/ocbc-360-interest-structure-change-whats-the-impact-on-you-and-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018/10/20/ocbc-360-interest-structure-change-whats-the-impact-on-you-and-me/</guid>
      <description>What&amp;rsquo;s changed for the OCBC 360 account bonus interest structure 
Effective from 1st Nov 2018, there will be changes to the interest structure of the&amp;nbsp;OCBC 360 account. If you are either exploring deposit accounts out there or currently using OCBC 360 (like myself), you should pay attention to these changes.
Following is the existing interest structure:
   Existing interest structure 
It&#39;s a relatively straightforward structure that has requirements on salary crediting (which earns you 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[short] Book Review: Rich by Retirement by Joshua Giersch</title>
      <link>/post/2018/09/16/short-book-review-rich-by-retirement-by-joshua-giersch/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018/09/16/short-book-review-rich-by-retirement-by-joshua-giersch/</guid>
      <description>Joshua Giersch, better known as “Shiny Things”, is an investment guru who has been generously giving investing advice on HardwareZone and his blog. His advice are consistently dished out with the SG context in mind, and his book &amp;ldquo;Rich by Retirement: How Singaporeans Can Invest Smart and Retire Wealthy&amp;rdquo;, is, in essence, the consolidation of all of his tips and hacks on being a successful investor in SG.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>