<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Finance &amp; Investing on The Stats Guy</title>
    <link>/categories/finance-investing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Finance &amp; Investing on The Stats Guy</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/finance-investing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Fundamental Analysis 101: A basic overview of the fundamental analysis of stocks</title>
      <link>/2019/06/08/fundamental-analysis-101-a-basic-overview-of-the-fundamental-analysis-of-stocks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/06/08/fundamental-analysis-101-a-basic-overview-of-the-fundamental-analysis-of-stocks/</guid>
      <description>In this post, I would like to give an overview of the principles and concepts in the fundamental analysis of stocks.
What is fundamental analysis? Well, fundamental analysis (FA) is the analysis of the fundamentals of a company. The fundamentals of the company are trying to capture essentially the health of the company, in the present and future. The objective of FA is to discern a point of view on the current and future prospects of a company – the actionability from this point of view is of course whether to buy (or short-sell) the stock.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stylized facts in statistical finance</title>
      <link>/2019/04/04/stylized-facts-in-statistical-finance/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/04/04/stylized-facts-in-statistical-finance/</guid>
      <description>In statistical finance (as well as in certain areas in social science), stylized facts are empirical observations summarized in a theory-like form, and are generally representative under broad circumstances.
Stylized facts are commonly used in statistical finance to address and summarize phenomenon directly observed from historical data, and explainable with a certain level of theoretical consistency and logic (&#34;... this makes sense to me&#34;). Stylized facts may often guide investigations and explorations into certain topics of interest, functioning perhaps as assumptions to be either built upon or proven otherwise.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A guide to dollar cost averaging in Singapore - Part 1</title>
      <link>/2019/01/13/a-guide-to-dollar-cost-averaging-in-singapore-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/13/a-guide-to-dollar-cost-averaging-in-singapore-part-1/</guid>
      <description>Dollar cost averaging and regular savings plans are good ways for long-term investors to build up their nest egg in Singapore. Image&amp;nbsp;source. Happy New Year from Korea everyone! I am currently on a business trip in Seoul, visiting our Korean counterparts for 2 weeks. Besides the weeknight / weekend day trips to popular spots like Myeongdong and Dongdaemun, I have also found some time to do a bit of writing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Good news for fans of Singapore Savings Bonds</title>
      <link>/2018/12/21/good-news-for-fans-of-singapore-savings-bonds/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/12/21/good-news-for-fans-of-singapore-savings-bonds/</guid>
      <description>The Singapore Savings Bonds programme
Been a while since I last posted on my blog - the last month or so has been hectic for me, with the semester final examinations for my part-time Masters as well as travelling for business. Still, no excuses for slipping on my 2 posts per month commitment, so will try to make up for it in December.
Also, quick update: following my analysis of the various deposit accounts here and here, I went ahead and opened my DBS Multiplier account online, together with the DBS Live Fresh credit card.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OCBC 360 Interest structure changes: what&#39;s the impact on me and you? - Part 2</title>
      <link>/2018/11/04/ocbc-360-interest-structure-changes-whats-the-impact-on-me-and-you-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/11/04/ocbc-360-interest-structure-changes-whats-the-impact-on-me-and-you-part-2/</guid>
      <description>The OCBC 360 Account
This is part 2 from the post &#34;OCBC 360 Interest structure changes: what&#39;s the impact on me and you? - Part 1&#34;. Be sure to check that out first before going further here.
In my previous post, I illustrated the upcoming changes to the bonus interest structure of the 360 account, and how it will be affecting me. In this post, I will be making some specific comparisons between accounts from different banks and work on some simple numbers to make a decision on my next deposit account.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of the Phillip SING Income ETF</title>
      <link>/2018/10/20/analysis-of-the-phillip-sing-income-etf/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/10/20/analysis-of-the-phillip-sing-income-etf/</guid>
      <description>Earlier this month (Oct 2018), Phillip Securities introduced a brand new ETF - the Phillip SING Income ETF, to be managed by Phillip Capital Management, Based on the name of the ETF alone, it&amp;rsquo;s easy to guess the focus of this ETF: dividend income, which is an investment style popular amongst retail investors in Singapore.
Here&amp;rsquo;s how the ETF is described on poems.com.sg:
Harvest Your Regular Income with Phillip SING Income ETF The Phillip SING Income ETF focuses on 30 high quality Singapore Listed stocks to offer investors a cost-effective and diversified exposure to the Singapore market.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OCBC 360 Interest structure changes: what&#39;s the impact on me and you? - Part 1</title>
      <link>/2018/10/20/ocbc-360-interest-structure-changes-whats-the-impact-on-me-and-you-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/10/20/ocbc-360-interest-structure-changes-whats-the-impact-on-me-and-you-part-1/</guid>
      <description>What&amp;rsquo;s changed for the OCBC 360 account bonus interest structure
Effective from 1st Nov 2018, there will be changes to the interest structure of the&amp;nbsp;OCBC 360 account. If you are either exploring deposit accounts out there or currently using OCBC 360 (like myself), you should pay attention to these changes.
Following is the existing interest structure:
Existing interest structure
It&amp;rsquo;s a relatively straightforward structure that has requirements on salary crediting (which earns you 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Rich by Retirement by Joshua Giersch</title>
      <link>/2018/09/16/book-review-rich-by-retirement-by-joshua-giersch/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/09/16/book-review-rich-by-retirement-by-joshua-giersch/</guid>
      <description>Joshua Giersch, better known as “Shiny Things”, is an investment guru who has been generously giving investing advice on HardwareZone and his blog. His advice are consistently dished out with the SG context in mind, and his book &amp;ldquo;Rich by Retirement: How Singaporeans Can Invest Smart and Retire Wealthy&amp;rdquo;, is, in essence, the consolidation of all of his tips and hacks on being a successful investor in SG.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>