<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Corporate rat race on The Stats Guy</title>
    <link>/categories/corporate-rat-race/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Corporate rat race on The Stats Guy</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/corporate-rat-race/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>[short] Travelling and productivity</title>
      <link>/post/2017/03/05/travelling-and-productivity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017/03/05/travelling-and-productivity/</guid>
      <description>Two things I want to talk about here: how travelling affects productivity and how to alleviate some of its effects.
Since October 2016, I have been travelling in out of the Philippines for a data science project. Between October 2016 to February 2017, I made 11 trips to the Philippines, each trip spanning on average about 1 work week.
At first it seems fun; which young professional wouldn’t want to experience a work life of constant flying, staying in 4 or 5 stars hotels while working on interesting projects?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[short] Scientific desktop research: tentative conclusions</title>
      <link>/post/2017/02/13/scientific-desktop-research-tentative-conclusions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017/02/13/scientific-desktop-research-tentative-conclusions/</guid>
      <description>Useful tip I got from &amp;ldquo;Extreme Productivity&amp;rdquo; by Robert Pozen, still reading.
Desktop research, or simply known as googling in today&amp;rsquo;s context, is the act of collecting information about a particular topic or domain, with a broad/generic question in mind, or even without any question at all.
One way to do this is simply keep googling related search terms and noting down facts and statistics, and constantly drilling down on a specific term until it&amp;rsquo;s milked - sort of like a depth-first search of collecting information.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[short] Types of tasks</title>
      <link>/post/2017/02/12/types-of-tasks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017/02/12/types-of-tasks/</guid>
      <description>In my work so far, there are typically a few type of tasks:
Analytics tasks (planning, architecture, setup, coding etc) Writing (documentations, reflections) Desktop research Emails (replying, drafting new ones) Ideations Team huddles External meetings with customers Internal project meetings Preparing decks and presentations Organising materials Admin
I think they can divided into four quadrants:
  High amount of visible results, low value  Emails (replying, drafting new ones) Organising materials   High amount of visible results, high value  Analytics tasks (coding, planning) Writing Preparing decks and presentations Customer meetings     Low amount of visible results, low value  Admin   Low amount of visible results, high value  Desktop research Ideations, brainstorming Team huddles Internal project meetings     There&amp;rsquo;s a lot of unpack here, so one by one:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Three Needs Theory - Power, Achievement, Affliation</title>
      <link>/post/2017/01/02/three-needs-theory-power-achievement-affliation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017/01/02/three-needs-theory-power-achievement-affliation/</guid>
      <description>The Three Needs Theory was developed by psychologist David McClelland in the 1960s. The theory identifies three main needs in the professional setting, which form the drivers of motivation. These needs are
 The need for power (n-Pow) The need for achievement (n-Ach) The need for affiliation (n-Aff)  I first encountered this idea in the book Managing Scientists: Leadership Strategies in Scientific Research by Alice Sapienza, which I have yet to finish reading.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[short] Book Review: The McKinsey Edge</title>
      <link>/post/2016/12/31/book-review-the-mckinsey-edge/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2016/12/31/book-review-the-mckinsey-edge/</guid>
      <description>The McKinsey Edge by Shu Hattori is a collection of &amp;ldquo;principles&amp;rdquo; that the author collected while he was at consultant at McKinsey. The forty-odd principles in the book, while easily understood, stood out when they are collated together in a single book, as many productivity and professional hacks strung together. A rather interesting read.
Following are his principles divided into four chapters, and in bold are those that I thought to be particularly useful, and would like to expound on them in future writings.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>